<page>
<title>Apollo program</title>
<text>
{{Infobox space program
|name= Apollo program
|image= Apollo program insignia.png
|image_size=
|alt=
|caption=
|country= United States
|organization= [[NASA]]
|status= completed
|duration= 1961–1972
|firstflight= [[AS-201]], February 26, 1966
|firstcrewed= [[Apollo 7]], October 11–22, 1968
|lastflight= [[Apollo 17]], December 7–19, 1972
|successes= 16
|failures= 2: [[Apollo 1]], [[Apollo 13]]
|partialfailures= 1: [[Apollo 6]]
|launchsite= 
* [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station Launch Complex 34|Cape Kennedy Air Force Station LC-34]]
* [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station Launch Complex 37|Cape Kennedy Air Force Station LC-37]]
* [[Kennedy Space Center Launch Complex 39|Kennedy Space Center LC-39]]
|vehicletype= capsule
|crewvehicle= 
* [[Apollo Command/Service Module]]
* [[Apollo Lunar Module]]
|capacity= 3
|launcher=
* [[Saturn IB]]
* [[Saturn V]]
}}
[[File:Aldrin Apollo 11.jpg|thumb|[[Buzz Aldrin]] (pictured) walked on the [[Moon]] with [[Neil Armstrong]], on [[Apollo 11]], July 20–21, 1969|alt=Astronaut Buzz Aldrin stands on the Moon]]

The '''Apollo program''', also known as '''Project Apollo''', was the third United States [[human spaceflight]] program carried out by the [[NASA|National Aeronautics and Space Administration]] (NASA), which accomplished landing the first humans on the [[Moon]] from 1969 to 1972. First conceived during [[Presidency of Dwight D. Eisenhower|Dwight D. Eisenhower's administration]] as a three-man spacecraft to follow the one-man [[Project Mercury]] which put the first Americans in space, Apollo was later dedicated to [[President of the United States|President]] [[John F. Kennedy]]'s national goal of "landing a man on the Moon and returning him safely to the Earth" by the end of the 1960s, which he proposed in a May 25, 1961, address to [[United States Congress|Congress]]. Project Mercury was followed by the two-man [[Project Gemini]] (1962–66). The first manned flight of Apollo was in 1968.

Kennedy's goal was accomplished on the [[Apollo 11]] mission when astronauts [[Neil Armstrong]] and [[Buzz Aldrin]] landed their [[Apollo Lunar Module|Lunar Module]] (LM) on July 20, 1969, and walked on the lunar surface, while [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]] remained in [[lunar orbit]] in the [[Apollo Command/Service Module|Command/Service Module]] (CSM), and all three landed safely on Earth on July 24. Five subsequent Apollo missions also landed [[astronaut]]s on the Moon, the last in December 1972. In these six spaceflights, [[List of Apollo astronauts#Apollo astronauts who walked on the Moon|twelve men walked on the Moon]].

Apollo ran from 1961 to 1972, and was supported by the two-man [[Project Gemini|Gemini]] program which ran concurrently with it from 1962 to 1966. Gemini missions developed some of the space travel techniques that were necessary for the success of the Apollo missions. Apollo used [[Saturn (rocket family)|Saturn family rockets]] as launch vehicles. Apollo/Saturn vehicles were also used for an [[Apollo Applications Program]], which consisted of [[Skylab]], a [[space station]] that supported three manned missions in 1973–74, and the [[Apollo–Soyuz Test Project]], a joint Earth orbit mission with the Soviet Union in 1975.

The Apollo program succeeded in achieving its goal of manned lunar landing, despite the major setback of a 1967 [[Apollo 1]] cabin fire that killed the entire crew during a prelaunch test. After the first landing, sufficient flight hardware remained for nine follow-on landings with a plan for extended lunar [[geology of the Moon|geological]] and [[astrophysics|astrophysical]] exploration. Budget cuts forced the cancellation of three of these. Five of the remaining six missions achieved successful landings, but the [[Apollo 13]] landing was prevented by an oxygen tank explosion in transit to the Moon, which disabled the command spacecraft's propulsion and life support. The crew returned to Earth safely by using the Lunar Module as a "lifeboat" for these functions.

Apollo set several major [[List of space exploration milestones, 1957–1969|human spaceflight milestones]]. It stands alone in sending manned missions beyond [[low Earth orbit]]. [[Apollo 8]] was the first manned spacecraft to orbit another celestial body, while the final [[Apollo 17]] mission marked the sixth Moon landing and the ninth manned mission beyond low Earth orbit. The program returned {{convert|842|lb|kg}} of lunar rocks and [[lunar soil|soil]] to Earth, greatly contributing to the understanding of the Moon's composition and geological history. The program laid the foundation for NASA's current human spaceflight capability, and funded construction of its [[Johnson Space Center]] and [[Kennedy Space Center]]. Apollo also spurred advances in many areas of technology incidental to rocketry and [[Human spaceflight|manned spaceflight]], including [[avionics]], telecommunications, and computers.

==Background==
The Apollo program was conceived during the [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Eisenhower]] administration in early 1960, as a follow-up to [[Project Mercury]]. While the Mercury [[space capsule|capsule]] could only support one astronaut on a limited Earth orbital mission, Apollo would carry three astronauts. Possible missions included ferrying crews to a [[space station]], [[circumlunar trajectory|circumlunar flight]]s,  and eventual manned [[Moon landing|lunar landing]]s. The program was named after the [[Apollo|Greek god of light, music, and the sun]] by NASA manager [[Abe Silverstein]], who later said that "I was naming the spacecraft like I'd name my baby."<ref>[[#Murray & Cox|Murray & Cox 1989]], p. 55</ref> Silverstein chose the name at home one evening, early in 1960, because he felt "Apollo riding his chariot across the Sun was appropriate to the grand scale of the proposed program."<ref name="pressrelease">{{cite press release |title=Release 69-36 |date=July 14, 1969 |publisher=[[Glenn Research Center|Lewis Research Center]] |url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/about/history/apollo_press_release.html |location=Cleveland, OH |accessdate=June 21, 2012}}</ref>

===Spacecraft feasibility studies===
{{Main|Apollo spacecraft feasibility study}}

In July 1960, NASA Deputy Administrator [[Hugh L. Dryden]] announced the Apollo program to industry representatives at a series of [[Space Task Group]] conferences. Preliminary specifications were laid out for a spacecraft with a ''mission module'' cabin separate from the ''command module'' (piloting and re-entry cabin), and a ''propulsion and equipment module''.  On August 30, a feasibility study competition was announced, and on October 25, three study contracts were awarded to [[Convair|General Dynamics/Convair]], [[General Electric]], and the [[Glenn L. Martin Company]].<ref name="chariots_feasibility">{{cite web|url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch1-7.html|title=Chariots For Apollo, ch1-7|publisher=}}</ref> Meanwhile, NASA performed its own in-house spacecraft design studies led by [[Maxime Faget]], to serve as a gauge to judge and monitor the three industry designs.<ref name="chariots_feasibility"/>

===Political pressure builds===
{{Main|Space Race}}

In November 1960, John F. Kennedy was elected president after a campaign that promised American superiority over the [[Soviet Union]] in the fields of [[space exploration]] and [[missile defense]]. Using aerospace technology as a symbol of national prestige, he warned of a "[[missile gap]]" between the two nations, pledging to make the US not "first but, first and, first if, but first period."<ref>[[#Beschloss|Beschloss 1997]]</ref> Despite Kennedy's rhetoric, he did not immediately come to a decision on the status of the Apollo program once he became president. He knew little about the technical details of the space program, and was put off by the massive financial commitment required by a manned Moon landing.<ref>[[#Sidey|Sidey 1963]], pp. 117–118</ref> When Kennedy's newly appointed NASA Administrator [[James E. Webb]] requested a 30 percent budget increase for his agency, Kennedy supported an acceleration of NASA's large booster program but deferred a decision on the broader issue.<ref>[[#Beschloss|Beschloss 1997]], p. 55</ref>

On April 12, 1961, Soviet [[astronaut#Russian|cosmonaut]] [[Yuri Gagarin]] became the first person to fly in space, reinforcing American fears about being left behind in a technological competition with the Soviet Union. At a meeting of the US House [[United States House Committee on Science, Space and Technology|Committee on Science and Astronautics]] one day after Gagarin's flight, many congressmen pledged their support for a crash program aimed at ensuring that America would catch up.<ref>[[#87th Congress|87th Congress 1961]]</ref> Kennedy was circumspect in his response to the news, refusing to make a commitment on America's response to the Soviets.<ref>[[#Sidey|Sidey 1963]], p. 114</ref>

[[File:Kennedy Giving Historic Speech to Congress - GPN-2000-001658.jpg|thumb|right|[[President of the United States|President]] [[John F. Kennedy|Kennedy]] delivers his proposal to put a man on the Moon before a joint session of [[United States Congress|Congress]], May 25, 1961|alt=President John F. Kennedy addresses a joint session of Congress, with Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson and House Speaker Sam Rayburn seated behind him]]
On April 20, Kennedy sent a memo to [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]] [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], asking Johnson to look into the status of America's space program, and into programs that could offer NASA the opportunity to catch up.<ref name="jfkmemo">{{cite web |url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/Asset-Viewer/6XnAYXEkkkSMLfp7ic_o-Q.aspx |title=Memorandum for Vice President |last=Kennedy |first=John F. |authorlink=John F. Kennedy |date=April 20, 1961 |work=[[White House|The White House]] |publisher=[[John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum]] |location=Boston, MA |type=Memorandum |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref><ref>{{cite book |last=Launius |first=Roger D. |title=Apollo: A Retrospective Analysis |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/cover.html |format=PDF |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=Monographs in Aerospace History Number 3 |date=July 1994 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=31825096 |chapter=President John F. Kennedy Memo for Vice President, 20 April 1961 |chapterurl=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/apollo1.pdf}} [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/docs.htm Key Apollo Source Documents].</ref> Johnson responded approximately one week later, concluding that "we are neither making maximum effort nor achieving results necessary if this country is to reach a position of leadership."<ref name="lbjmemo">{{cite web |url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/Asset-Viewer/DjiWpQJegkuIlX7WZAUCtQ.aspx |title=Memorandum for the President |last=Johnson |first=Lyndon B. |authorlink=Lyndon B. Johnson |type=Memorandum |date=April 28, 1961 |work=[[Office of the Vice President of the United States|Office of the Vice President]] |publisher=John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum |location=Boston, MA |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref><ref>{{cite book |last=Launius |first=Roger D. |title=Apollo: A Retrospective Analysis |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/cover.html |format=PDF |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=Monographs in Aerospace History Number 3 |date=July 1994 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=31825096 |chapter=Lyndon B. Johnson, Vice President, Memo for the President, 'Evaluation of Space Program,' 28 April 1961 |chapterurl=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/apollo2.pdf}} [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/Apollomon/docs.htm Key Apollo Source Documents].</ref> His memo concluded that a manned Moon landing was far enough in the future that it was likely the United States would achieve it first.<ref name="lbjmemo" />

On May 25, 1961, twenty days after the first US manned spaceflight [[Mercury-Redstone 3|Freedom 7]], Kennedy proposed the manned Moon landing in a ''Special Message to the Congress on Urgent National Needs'':
<blockquote>"Now it is time to take longer strides - time for a great new American enterprise - time for this nation to take a clearly leading role in space achievement, which in many ways may hold the key to our future on Earth.<br><br>...I believe that this nation should commit itself to achieving the goal, before this decade is out, of landing a man on the Moon and returning him safely to the Earth. No single space project in this period will be more impressive to mankind, or more important in the long-range exploration of space; and none will be so difficult or expensive to accomplish."<ref name="Special Message">{{cite AV media |people=Kennedy, John F. |date=May 25, 1961 |title=Special Message to Congress on Urgent National Needs |medium=Motion picture (excerpt) |url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/Asset-Viewer/xzw1gaeeTES6khED14P1Iw.aspx |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |publisher=John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum |location=Boston, MA |id=Accession Number: TNC:200; Digital Identifier: TNC-200-2}}</ref> {{Cws |title=Full text |link=Special Message to the Congress on Urgent National Needs|nobullet=yes}}</blockquote>

==NASA expansion==
At the time of Kennedy's proposal, only one American had flown in space—less than a month earlier—and NASA had not yet sent an astronaut into orbit. Even some NASA employees doubted whether Kennedy's ambitious goal could be met.<ref>[[#Murray & Cox|Murray & Cox 1989]], pp. 16–17</ref> By 1963, Kennedy even came close to agreeing to a joint US-USSR Moon mission, to eliminate duplication of effort.<ref>{{cite news |title=Soviets Planned to Accept JFK's Joint Lunar Mission Offer |first=Frank |last=Sietzen |url=http://www.spacedaily.com/news/russia-97h.html |agency=SpaceCast News Service |work=SpaceDaily |date=October 2, 1997 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

With the clear goal of a manned landing replacing the more nebulous goals of space stations and cislunar flights, NASA had to hit the ground running, and decided to discard the feasibility study designs of Convair, GE, and Martin, and proceed with Faget's command / service module design. The mission module was now an unnecessary luxury. They used Faget's design as the specification for another competition for spacecraft procurement bids.

Landing men on the Moon by the end of 1969 required the most sudden burst of technological creativity, and the largest commitment of resources ($24 billion) ever made by any nation in peacetime. At its peak, the Apollo program employed 400,000 people and required the support of over 20,000 industrial firms and universities.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/langley/news/factsheets/Apollo.html |title=NASA Langley Research Center's Contributions to the Apollo Program |editor-last=Allen |editor-first=Bob |work=[[Langley Research Center]] |publisher=NASA |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

NASA already had a head start on the manned landing with the July 1, 1960 establishment of the [[Marshall Space Flight Center]] in Alabama, which was working on the design of heavy lift-class [[Saturn (rocket family)|Saturn launch vehicles]] which would be required for Apollo. But two more major NASA centers had to be built to accommodate the program.

===Manned Spacecraft Center===
{{Main|Johnson Space Center}}

It became clear that managing the Apollo program would exceed the capabilities of [[Robert R. Gilruth]]'s [[Space Task Group]], which had been directing the nation's manned space program from NASA's [[Langley Research Center]]. So Gilruth was given authority to grow his organization into a new NASA center, the [[Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center|Manned Spacecraft Center]] (MSC). A site was chosen in [[Houston]], Texas, on land donated by [[Rice University]], and Administrator Webb announced the conversion on September 19, 1961.<ref name="TNO 12">{{cite book |last1=Swenson |first1=Loyd S., Jr. |first2=James M. |last2=Grimwood |first3=Charles C. |last3=Alexander |title=This New Ocean: A History of Project Mercury |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4201/toc.htm |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |origyear=Originally published 1966 |year=1989 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=569889 |id=NASA SP-4201 |chapter=Chapter 12.3: Space Task Group Gets a New Home and Name |chapterurl=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4201/ch12-3.htm}}</ref> It was also clear NASA would soon outgrow its practice of controlling missions from its [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station]] launch facilities in Florida, so a new [[Christopher C. Kraft Jr. Mission Control Center|Mission Control Center]] would be included in the MSC.

[[File:President Kennedy speech on the space effort at Rice University, September 12, 1962.ogg|thumb|right|thumbtime=17:32|President Kennedy speaks at [[Rice University]], September 12, 1962 (17 min, 47 sec)]]
In September 1962, by which time two Project Mercury astronauts had orbited the Earth, Gilruth had moved his organization to rented space in Houston, and construction of the MSC facility was under way, Kennedy visited Rice to reiterate his challenge in a [[We choose to go to the Moon|famous speech]]:
<blockquote>"But why, some say, the Moon? Why choose this as our goal? And they may well ask, why climb the highest mountain? Why, 35 years ago, fly the Atlantic? ... <br>
We choose to go to the Moon. We choose to go to the Moon in this decade and do the other things, not because they are easy, but because they are hard; because that goal will serve to organize and measure the best of our energies and skills; because that challenge is one that we are willing to accept, one we are unwilling to postpone, and one we intend to win ... .<ref name="Rice Speech">{{cite web |url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Reference+Desk/Speeches/JFK/003POF03SpaceEffort09121962.htm |title=Address at Rice University on the Nation's Space Effort |last=Kennedy |first=John F. |date=September 12, 1962 |publisher=John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum |location=Boston, MA |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20100506113709/http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Reference+Desk/Speeches/JFK/003POF03SpaceEffort09121962.htm |archivedate=May 6, 2010 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref> {{Cws |title=Full text |link=We choose to go to the moon |nobullet=yes}}</blockquote>

The MSC was completed in September 1963. It was renamed by the US Congress in honor of Lyndon Johnson soon after his death in 1973.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=4109#axzz1RbWN5hpf |title=50 – Statement About Signing a Bill Designating the Manned Spacecraft Center in Houston, Texas, as the Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center |first=Richard M. |last=Nixon |authorlink=Richard M. Nixon |date=February 19, 1973 |work=The American Presidency Project |publisher=[[University of California, Santa Barbara]] |accessdate=July 9, 2011}}</ref>

===Launch Operations Center===
{{Main|Kennedy Space Center}}

It also became clear that Apollo would outgrow the Canaveral launch facilities in Florida. The two newest launch complexes were already being built for the [[Saturn I]] and [[Saturn IB|IB]] rockets at the northernmost end: [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station Launch Complex 34|LC-34]] and [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station Space Launch Complex 37|LC-37]]. But an even bigger facility would be needed for the mammoth rocket required for the manned lunar mission, so land acquisition was started in July 1961 for a Launch Operations Center (LOC) immediately north of Canaveral at [[Merritt Island, Florida|Merritt Island]]. The design, development and construction of the center was conducted by [[Kurt H. Debus]], a member of Dr. [[Wernher von Braun]]'s original [[V-2 rocket]] engineering team. Debus was named the LOC's first Director.<ref name="NASA2">{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/kennedy/about/biographies/debus.html |title=Dr. Kurt H. Debus |date=February 1987 |work=Kennedy Biographies |publisher=NASA |accessdate=October 7, 2008}}</ref> Construction began in November 1962. Upon Kennedy's death, President Johnson issued an executive order on November 29, 1963, to rename the LOC and Cape Canaveral in honor of Kennedy.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/executive-orders/1963-johnson.html |title=Executive Orders Disposition Tables: Lyndon B. Johnson - 1963: Executive Order 11129 |work=[[Office of the Federal Register]] |publisher=[[National Archives and Records Administration]] |accessdate=April 26, 2010}}</ref>

The LOC included [[Kennedy Space Center Launch Complex 39|Launch Complex 39]], a [[Launch Control Center]], and a 130 million cubic foot (3.7 million cubic meter) [[Vehicle Assembly Building|Vertical Assembly Building]] (VAB) in which the space vehicle (launch vehicle and spacecraft) would be assembled on a [[Mobile Launcher Platform]] and then moved by a [[Crawler-transporter|transporter]] to one of several launch pads. Although at least three pads were planned, only two, designated A and B, were completed in October 1965. The LOC also included an [[Operations and Checkout Building]] (OCB) to which Gemini and Apollo spacecraft were initially received prior to being mated to their launch vehicles. The Apollo spacecraft could be tested in two [[vacuum chamber]]s capable of simulating atmospheric pressure at altitudes up to {{convert|250000|ft|km}}, which is nearly a vacuum.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://kscpartnerships.ksc.nasa.gov/techCap/altitude.htm |title=KSC Technical Capabilities: O&C Altitude Chambers |editor-last=Craig |editor-first=Kay |work=Center Planning and Development Office |publisher=NASA |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20120328084113/http://kscpartnerships.ksc.nasa.gov/techCap/altitude.htm |archivedate=March 28, 2012 |accessdate=July 29, 2011}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.luizmonteiro.com/StdAtm.aspx |title=1976 Standard Atmosphere Properties |work=luizmonteiro.com |publisher=Luizmonteiro, LLC |type=Complete [[International Standard Atmosphere]] calculator (1976 model) |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

===Organization===
Administrator Webb realized that in order to keep Apollo costs under control, he had to develop greater project management skills in his organization, so he recruited Dr. [[George Mueller (NASA)|George E. Mueller]] for a high management job. Mueller accepted, on the condition that he have a say in NASA reorganization necessary to effectively administer Apollo. Webb then worked with Associate Administrator (later Deputy Administrator) [[Robert Seamans]] to reorganize the Office of Manned Space Flight (OMSF).<ref name="SecretOfApollo">[[#Johnson|Johnson 2002]]</ref> On July 23, 1963, Webb announced Mueller's appointment as Deputy Associate Administrator for Manned Space Flight, to replace then Associate Administrator [[D. Brainerd Holmes]] on his retirement effective September 1. Under Webb's reorganization, the directors of the Manned Spacecraft Center (Gilruth) [[Marshall Space Flight Center]] (von Braun) and the Launch Operations Center (Debus) effectively reported to Mueller.<ref>[[#Bilstein|Bilstein 1996]], [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4206/p443.htm "Appendix G - NASA Organization During Apollo-Saturn"]. November 1963. p. 443</ref>

Based on his industry experience on Air Force missile projects, Mueller realized some skilled managers could be found among high-ranking officers in the [[United States Air Force]], so he got Webb's permission to recruit General [[Samuel C. Phillips]], who gained a reputation for his effective management of the [[LGM-30 Minuteman|Minuteman]] program, as OMSF program controller. Phillips' superior officer [[Bernard Adolph Schriever|Bernard A. Schriever]] agreed to loan Phillips to NASA, along with a staff of officers under him, on the condition that Phillips be made Apollo Program Director. Mueller agreed, and Phillips managed Apollo from January 1964, until it achieved the first manned landing in July 1969, after which he returned to Air Force duty.<ref>{{Cite news |title=Samuel C. Phillips, Who Directed Apollo Lunar Landing, Dies at 68 |first=Alfonso A. |last=Narvaez |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/02/01/obituaries/samuel-c-phillips-who-directed-apollo-lunar-landing-dies-at-68.html?pagewanted=1 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=February 1, 1990 |accessdate=April 14, 2010}}</ref>
<!----This probably completes this section, the intent of which is to keep the narrative flow of Webb's big 1963 reorganization. These remainders should be highlighted, probably as appropriate in later sections.
* Shea
* Christopher Kraft
* Gene Kranz
* Deke Slayton
* Rocco Petrone
---->

==Choosing a mission mode==
[[File:John Houbolt and LOR2.jpg|right|thumb|[[John Houbolt]] explaining the [[Lunar orbit rendezvous|LOR]] concept]]
{{See also|Moon landing}}

Once Kennedy had defined a goal, the Apollo mission planners were faced with the challenge of designing a spacecraft that could meet it while minimizing risk to human life, cost, and demands on technology and astronaut skill. Four possible mission modes were considered:
* '''[[Direct ascent|Direct Ascent]]:''' The spacecraft would be launched as a unit and travel directly to the Moon and land. It would return, leaving its landing stage on the Moon. This design would have required development of the extremely powerful [[Nova (rocket)|Nova]] launch vehicle.
* '''[[Earth orbit rendezvous|Earth Orbit Rendezvous]] (EOR):''' Multiple rocket launches (up to 15 in some plans) would carry parts of a Direct Ascent spacecraft and propulsion units for [[Trans-lunar injection|translunar injection]] (TLI). These would be assembled into a single spacecraft in Earth orbit.
* '''[[Lunar Orbit Rendezvous]] (LOR):''' A single [[Saturn V]] could launch a spacecraft that was composed of a [[Apollo Command/Service Module|mother ship]] which would remain in orbit around the Moon, while a smaller, two-stage [[Apollo Lunar Module|lander]] would carry two astronauts to the surface, return to dock with the mother ship, and then be discarded. Landing only a small part of the spacecraft on the Moon and returning an even smaller part to lunar orbit minimized the total mass to be launched from the Earth.
* '''Lunar Surface Rendezvous:''' Two spacecraft would be launched in succession. The first, an automated vehicle carrying propellant for the return to Earth, would land on the Moon, to be followed some time later by the manned vehicle. Propellant would have to be transferred from the automated vehicle to the manned vehicle.

[[File:Apollo Direct Ascent.png|thumb|right|Early Apollo configuration for [[Direct ascent|Direct Ascent]] and [[Earth orbit rendezvous|Earth Orbit Rendezvous]], 1961]]
In early 1961, direct ascent was generally the mission mode in favor at NASA. Many engineers feared that a rendezvous —let alone a docking— neither of which had been attempted even in [[Geocentric orbit|Earth orbit]], would be extremely difficult in lunar orbit. Dissenters including [[John Houbolt]] at Langley Research Center emphasized the important weight reductions that were offered by the LOR approach. Throughout 1960 and 1961, Houbolt campaigned for the recognition of LOR as a viable and practical option. Bypassing the NASA hierarchy, he sent a series of memos and reports on the issue to Associate Administrator Robert Seamans; while acknowledging that he spoke "somewhat as a voice in the wilderness," Houbolt pleaded that LOR should not be discounted in studies of the question.<ref>[[#Brooks, et al.|Brooks, et al. 1979]], Chapter 3.4: [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch3-4.html "Early Reaction to LOR"]. p. 71</ref>

{{anchor|Nicholas E. Golovin}}
Seamans' establishment of an ad-hoc committee headed by his special technical assistant Nicholas E. Golovin in July 1961, to recommend a [[launch vehicle]] to be used in the Apollo program, represented a turning point in NASA's mission mode decision.<ref name="hansen21">[[#Hansen|Hansen 1999]], p. 32</ref> This committee recognized that the chosen mode was an important part of the launch vehicle choice, and recommended in favor of a hybrid EOR-LOR mode. Its consideration of LOR —as well as Houbolt's ceaseless work— played an important role in publicizing the workability of the approach. In late 1961 and early 1962, members of the Manned Spacecraft Center began to come around to support LOR, including the newly hired deputy director of the Office of Manned Space Flight, [[Joseph Francis Shea|Joseph Shea]], who became a champion of LOR.<ref name="hansen24">[[#Hansen|Hansen 1999]], pp. 35-39</ref> The engineers at Marshall Space Flight Center (MSFC) took longer to become convinced of its merits, but their conversion was announced by Wernher von Braun at a briefing in June 1962.

But even after NASA reached internal agreement, it was far from smooth sailing. Kennedy's [[President's Science Advisory Committee|science advisor]] [[Jerome Wiesner]], who had expressed his opposition to manned spaceflight to Kennedy before the President took office,<ref>Levine, Anold S. (1982). [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4102/ch2.htm Managing NASA in the Apollo Era'', chapter 27, "The Lunar Landing Decision and Its Aftermath". NASA SP-4102.]</ref> and had opposed the decision to land men on the Moon, hired Golovin, who had left NASA, to chair his own "Space Vehicle Panel", ostensibly to monitor, but actually to second-guess NASA's decisions on the [[Saturn V]] launch vehicle and LOR by forcing Shea, Seamans, and even Webb to defend themselves, delaying its formal announcement to the press on July 11, 1962, and forcing Webb to still hedge the decision as "tentative".<ref>Brooks, Grimwood, and Swenson (1979). [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch3-7.html ''Chariots For Apollo'', chapter 3.7, "Casting the Die". NASA SP-4205.]</ref>

Wiesner kept up the pressure, even making the disagreement public during a two-day September visit by the President to [[Marshall Space Flight Center]]. Wiesner blurted out "No, that's no good" in front of the press, during a presentation by von Braun. Webb jumped in and defended von Braun, until Kennedy ended the squabble by stating that the matter was "still subject to final review". Webb held firm, and issued a [[request for proposal]] to candidate Lunar Excursion Module (LEM) contractors. Wiesner finally relented, unwilling to settle the dispute once and for all in Kennedy's office, because of the President's involvement with the October [[Cuban missile crisis]], and fear of Kennedy's support for Webb. NASA announced the selection of [[Grumman]] as the LEM contractor in November 1962.<ref>Brooks, Grimwood, and Swenson (1979). [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch4-4.html ''Chariots For Apollo'', chapter 4.4, "Pressures by PSAC". NASA SP-4205.]</ref>

Space historian James Hansen concludes that:
{{quote|Without NASA's adoption of this stubbornly held minority opinion in 1962, the United States may still have reached the Moon, but almost certainly it would not have been accomplished by the end of the 1960s, President Kennedy's target date.<ref>[[#Hansen|Hansen 1999]], p. 42</ref>}}

The LOR method had the advantage of allowing the lander spacecraft to be used as a "lifeboat" in the event of a failure of the command ship. Some documents prove this theory was discussed before and after the method was chosen. A 1964 MSC study concluded, "The [[Apollo Lunar Module|LM]] [as lifeboat] ... was finally dropped, because no single reasonable [[Apollo Command/Service Module|CSM]] failure could be identified that would prohibit use of the [[Apollo Command/Service Module#Service Propulsion System|SPS]]."<ref>Letterman, p. 404 (James Lovell, "Explosion on Apollo 13; April 1970: From the Earth to the Moon and Back". Lovell writes, "Naturally, I'm glad that view didn't prevail, and I'm thankful that by the time of Apollo 10, the first lunar mission carrying the LM, the LM as a lifeboat was again being discussed.").</ref> Ironically, just such a failure happened on [[Apollo 13]] when an oxygen tank explosion left the command ship without electrical power. The Lunar Module provided propulsion, electrical power and life support to get the crew home safely.<ref name="KSC-Apollo_13">{{cite web |url=http://science.ksc.nasa.gov/history/apollo/apollo-13/apollo-13.html |last=Dumoulin |first=Jim |title=Apollo-13 (29) |work=Historical Archive for Manned Missions |publisher=NASA |date=June 29, 2001 |accessdate=September 12, 2012}}</ref>

==Spacecraft==
{{Main|Apollo (spacecraft)}}

Maxime Faget's preliminary Apollo design employed a cone-shaped command module, supported by one of several service modules providing propulsion and electrical power, sized appropriately for the space station, cislunar, and lunar landing missions. Once Kennedy's Moon landing goal became official, detailed design began of a ''Command/Service Module'' (CSM) in which the crew would spend the entire direct-ascent mission and lift off from the lunar surface for the return trip, after being soft-landed by a larger landing propulsion module. The final choice of lunar orbit rendezvous changed the CSM's role to the translunar ferry used to transport the crew, along with a new spacecraft, the ''Lunar Excursion Module'' (LEM, later shortened to ''Lunar Module'', LM) which would take two men to the lunar surface and return them to the CSM.<ref name="SummaryReport" />

===Command/Service Module===
{{Main|Apollo Command/Service Module}}
[[File:Apollo CSM lunar orbit.jpg|thumb|left|[[Apollo 15]] [[Apollo Command/Service Module|CSM]] in lunar orbit|alt=The cone-shaped Command Module, attached to the cylindrical Service Module, orbits the Moon with a panel removed, exposing the Scientific Instrument Module]]

The [[Apollo Command/Service Module#Command Module (CM)|Command Module]] (CM) was the conical crew cabin, designed to carry three astronauts from launch to lunar orbit and back to an Earth ocean landing. It was the only component of the Apollo spacecraft to survive without major configuration changes as the program evolved from the early Apollo study designs. Its exterior was covered with an [[ablative heat shield]], and had its own [[reaction control system]] (RCS) engines to [[attitude control|control its attitude]] and steer its [[atmospheric entry]] path. Parachutes were carried to slow its descent to splashdown. The module was {{convert|11.42|ft|m}} tall, {{convert|12.83|ft|m}} in diameter, and weighed approximately {{convert|12250|lb|kg}}.<ref name="ABTN_LV2"/>

A cylindrical [[Apollo service module|Service Module]] (SM) supported the Command Module, with a service propulsion engine and an RCS with propellants, and a fuel cell power generation system with [[liquid hydrogen]] and [[liquid oxygen]] reactants. A high-gain [[S band|S-band]] antenna was used for long-distance communications on the lunar flights. On the extended lunar missions, an orbital scientific instrument package was carried. The Service Module was discarded just before re-entry. The module was {{convert|24.6|ft|m}} long and {{convert|12.83|ft|m}} in diameter. The initial lunar flight version weighed approximately {{convert|51300|lb|kg}} fully fueled, while a later version designed to carry a lunar orbit scientific instrument package weighed just over {{convert|54000|lb|kg}}.<ref name="ABTN_LV2"/>

[[North American Aviation]] won the contract to build the CSM, and also the second stage of the Saturn V launch vehicle for NASA. Because the CSM design was started early before the selection of lunar orbit rendezvous, the service propulsion engine was sized to lift the CSM off of the Moon, and thus was oversized to about twice the thrust required for translunar flight.<ref>[[#Wilford|Wilford 1969]], p. 167</ref> Also, there was no provision for docking with the Lunar Module. A 1964 program definition study concluded that the initial design should be continued as Block I which would be used for early testing, while Block II, the actual lunar spacecraft, would incorporate the docking equipment and take advantage of the lessons learned in Block I development.<ref name="SummaryReport">{{cite web |url=http://history.nasa.gov/apsr/Apollopt2-2.pdf |title=Apollo Program Summary Report |date=April 1975 |publisher=NASA |location=Houston, TX |pages=3-66–4-12 |format=PDF |id=JSC-09423 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

===Lunar Module===
{{Main|Apollo Lunar Module}}
[[File:Apollo16LM.jpg|thumb|[[Apollo 16]] [[Apollo Lunar Module|LM]] on the Moon]]

The Lunar Module (LM) was designed to descend from lunar orbit to land two astronauts on the Moon and take them back to orbit to rendezvous with the Command Module. Not designed to fly through the Earth's atmosphere or return to Earth, its fuselage was designed totally without aerodynamic considerations, and was of an extremely lightweight construction. It consisted of separate descent and ascent stages, each with its own engine. The descent stage contained storage for the descent propellant, surface stay consumables, and surface exploration equipment. The ascent stage contained the crew cabin, ascent propellant, and a reaction control system. The initial LM model weighed approximately {{convert|33300|lb|kg}}, and allowed surface stays up to around 34 hours. An Extended Lunar Module weighed over {{convert|36200|lb|kg}}, and allowed surface stays of over 3 days.<ref name="ABTN_LV2">[[#Orloff|Orloff 2004]], [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4029/Apollo_18-12_Launch_Vehicle-Spacecraft_Key_Facts.htm "Launch Vehicle/Spacecraft Key Facts - 2nd Table"]</ref>

The contract for design and construction of the Lunar Module was awarded to [[Grumman|Grumman Aircraft Engineering Corporation]], and the project was overseen by [[Thomas J. Kelly (aerospace engineer)|Thomas J. Kelly]].<ref>{{cite news |title=T. J. Kelly, 72, Dies; Father of Lunar Module |first=Warren E. |last=Leary |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/27/nyregion/t-j-kelly-72-dies-father-of-lunar-module.html |newspaper=The New York Times |date=March 27, 2002 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

==Launch vehicles==
[[File:Saturnsandlittlejoe2.gif|thumb|right|300px|Four Apollo rocket assemblies, drawn to scale: [[Little Joe II]], [[Saturn I]], [[Saturn IB]], and [[Saturn V]]]]

Before the Apollo program began, Wernher von Braun and his team of rocket engineers had started work on plans for very large launch vehicles, the [[Saturn (rocket family)|Saturn series]], and the even larger [[Nova (rocket)|Nova]] series. In the midst of these plans, von Braun was transferred from the Army to NASA, and made Director of the Marshall Space Flight Center. The initial direct ascent plan to send the three-man Apollo Command/Service Module directly to the lunar surface, on top of a large descent rocket stage, would require a Nova-class launcher, with a lunar payload capability of over {{convert|180000|lb|kg|abbr=out}}.<ref>[[#Bilstein|Bilstein 1996]], Chapter 2.2: [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4206/ch2.htm "Aerospace Alphabet: ABMA, ARPA, MSFC"]. p. 50</ref> The June 11, 1962, decision to use lunar orbit rendezvous enabled the Saturn V to replace the Nova, and the MSFC proceeded to develop the [[Saturn (rocket family)|Saturn rocket family]] for Apollo.<ref>[[#Bilstein|Bilstein 1996]], Chapter 3: [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4206/ch3.htm "Missions, Modes, and Manufacturing"]. p. 60</ref>

===Little Joe II===
{{Main|Little Joe II}}

Since Apollo, like Mercury, would require a [[launch escape system]] (LES) in case of a launch failure, a relatively small rocket was required for qualification flight testing of this system. A size bigger than the NAA [[Little Joe (rocket)|Little Joe]] would be required, so the [[Little Joe II]] was built by [[General Dynamics]]/[[Convair]]. After an August 1963 [[Little Joe II Qualification Test Vehicle|qualification test flight]],<ref>[[#Townsend|Townsend 1973]], p. 14</ref> four LES test flights ([[A-001]] through [[A-004|004]]) were made at the [[White Sands Missile Range]] between May 1964 and January 1966.<ref>[[#Townsend|Townsend 1973]], p. 22</ref>

===Saturn I===
<!--[[File:SA-1 launch.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.7|[[SA-1]], launched October 27, 1961.]] too big for some reason-->
{{Main|Saturn I}}

Since Apollo, like Project Mercury, used more than one launch vehicle for space missions, NASA used spacecraft-launch vehicle combination series numbers: AS-10x for Saturn I, AS-20x for Saturn IB, and AS-50x for Saturn V (compare [[Mercury-Redstone 3]], [[Mercury-Atlas 6]]) to designate and plan all missions, rather than numbering them sequentially as in Project Gemini. This was changed by the time manned flights began.<ref name="missionNumbers" />

Saturn I, the first US heavy lift launch vehicle, was initially planned to launch partially equipped CSMs in low Earth orbit tests. The [[S-I]] first stage burned [[RP-1]] with liquid oxygen (LOX) oxidizer, to produce {{convert|1500000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3}} of thrust. The [[S-IV]] second stage used six liquid hydrogen-fueled [[RL-10]] engines with {{convert|90000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3}} of thrust. A planned [[Centaur (rocket stage)|Centaur]] (S-V) third stage with two RL-10 engines, never flew on Saturn I.<ref>[[#Dawson & Bowles|Dawson & Bowles 2004]], p. 85. See footnote 61.</ref>

[[File:Apollo 7 launch2.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.7|A Saturn IB rocket launches [[Apollo 7]], 1968]]
The first four Saturn I test flights were launched from LC-34, with only live first stages, carrying dummy upper stages filled with water. The first flight with a live S-IV was launched from LC-37. This was followed by five launches of [[Boilerplate (spaceflight)|boilerplate]] CSMs (designated [[AS-101 (spacecraft)|AS-101]] through [[AS-105 (spacecraft)|AS-105]]) into orbit in 1964 and 1965. The last three of these further supported the Apollo program by also carrying [[Pegasus (satellite)|Pegasus]] satellites, which verified the safety of the translunar environment by measuring the frequency and severity of [[micrometeorite]] impacts.<ref>[[#Brooks, et al.|Brooks, et al. 1979]], Chapter 7.6: [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch7-6.html "Portents for Operations"]</ref>

In September 1962, NASA planned to launch four manned CSM flights on the Saturn I from late 1965 through 1966, concurrent with Project Gemini. The {{convert|22500|lb|kg|adj=on}} payload capacity<ref>{{cite book |url=http://www.alternatewars.com/SpaceRace/Saturn/ASD_II_Saturn_Launch_Vehicles-2-1964.pdf |title=Apollo Systems Description|date=February 1, 1964 |publisher=NASA |volume=Volume II: Saturn Launch Vehicles |page=3-3 |type=Technical Memorandum |format=PDF |id=NASA TM-X-881 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}<!----Original URL for document on NTRS server: http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19710065502_1971065502.pdf----></ref> would have severely limited the systems which could be included, so the decision was made in October 1963 to use the uprated [[Saturn IB]] for all manned Earth orbital flights.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.astronautix.com/flights/apoosa11.htm |last=Wade |first=Mark |title=Apollo SA-11 |work=Encyclopedia Astronautica |accessdate= June 21, 2012}}</ref>

===Saturn IB===
{{Main|Saturn IB}}

The Saturn IB was an upgraded version of the Saturn I. The [[S-IB]] first stage increased the thrust to {{convert|1600000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3}}, and the second stage replaced the S-IV with the [[S-IVB|S-IVB-200]], powered by a single [[Rocketdyne J-2|J-2]] engine burning liquid hydrogen fuel with LOX, to produce {{convert|200000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on|lk=on}} of thrust. A restartable version of the S-IVB was used as the third stage of the Saturn V. The Saturn IB could send over {{convert|40000|lb|kg|sigfig=3}} into low Earth orbit, sufficient for a partially fueled CSM or the LM.<ref>{{cite book |title=Saturn IB News Reference |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/58939029/Saturn-IB-News-Reference |format=PDF |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |date=December 1965 |publisher=NASA; [[Chrysler|Chrysler Corporation]]; [[Douglas Aircraft Company|McDonnell Douglas Astronautics Company]]; [[IBM|International Business Machines Corporation]]; [[Rocketdyne]] |oclc=22102803 |chapter=Saturn IB Design Features}}</ref> Saturn IB launch vehicles and flights were designated with an AS-200 series number, "AS" indicating "Apollo Saturn" and the "2" indicating the second member of the Saturn rocket family.

===Saturn V===
[[File:Ksc-69pc-442.jpg|thumb|upright=0.7|A Saturn V launches Apollo 11 in 1969]]
{{Main|Saturn V}}

The three-stage Saturn V was designed to send a fully fueled CSM and LM to the Moon. It was {{convert|33|ft|m|sigfig=3}} in diameter and stood {{convert|363|ft|m|sigfig=4}} tall with its {{convert|96800|lb|kg|sigfig=3|adj=on}} lunar payload. Its capability grew to {{convert|103600|lb|kg|sigfig=3}} for the later advanced lunar landings. The [[S-IC]] first stage burned RP-1/LOX for a rated thrust of {{convert|7500000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3}}, which was upgraded to  {{convert|7610000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3}}. The second and third stages burned liquid hydrogen, and the third stage was a modified version of the S-IVB, with thrust increased to {{convert|230000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}} and capability to restart the engine for translunar injection after reaching a [[parking orbit]].<ref name="ABTN_LV1">[[#Orloff|Orloff 2004]] [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4029/Apollo_18-11_Launch_Vehicle-Spacecraft_Key_Facts.htm Launch "Vehicle/Spacecraft Key Facts - 1st Table"]</ref>

Saturn V launch vehicles and flights were designated with an AS-500 series number, "AS" indicating "Apollo Saturn" and the "5" indicating Saturn V.

==Astronauts==
{{Main|List of Apollo astronauts}}
[[File:Apollo 1 Prime Crew - GPN-2000-001159.jpg|thumb|left|[[Apollo 1]] crew: [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White]], command pilot [[Gus Grissom]], and [[Roger B. Chaffee|Roger Chaffee]]]]

NASA's Director of Flight Crew Operations during the Apollo program was [[Deke Slayton|Donald K. "Deke" Slayton]], one of the original [[Mercury Seven]] astronauts who was medically grounded in September 1962 due to a [[heart murmur]]. Slayton was responsible for making all Gemini and Apollo crew assignments.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/slayton.html |title=Astronaut Bio: Deke Slayton 6/93 |publisher=NASA |date=June 1993 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

[[File:apollo 11.jpg|thumb|right|Apollo 11 crew, who made the first manned landing: commander [[Neil Armstrong]], [[Apollo Command/Service Module#Command Module (CM)|CM]] pilot [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]], and LM pilot [[Buzz Aldrin]]]]
Thirty-two astronauts were assigned to fly missions in the Apollo program. Twenty-four of these left Earth’s orbit and flew around the Moon between December 1968 and December 1972 (three of them twice). Half of the 24 walked on its surface, though none of them returned to the Moon after landing once. One of the moonwalkers was a trained geologist. Of the 32, [[Gus Grissom]], [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White]], and [[Roger B. Chaffee|Roger Chaffee]] were killed during a ground test in preparation for their Apollo 1 mission.<ref name="missionNumbers" />

The Apollo astronauts were chosen from the Project Mercury and Gemini veterans, plus from two later astronaut groups. All missions were commanded by Gemini or Mercury veterans. Crews on all development flights (except the Earth orbit CSM development flights) through the first two landings on Apollo 11 and [[Apollo 12]], included at least two (sometimes three) Gemini veterans. Dr. [[Harrison Schmitt]], a geologist, was the first [[NASA Astronaut Group 4|NASA scientist astronaut]] to fly in space, and landed on the Moon on the last mission, Apollo 17. Schmitt participated in the [[geology of the moon|lunar geology]] training of all of the Apollo landing crews.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/schmitt-hh.html |title=Astronaut Bio: Harrison Schmitt |publisher=NASA |date=December 1994 |accessdate=September 12, 2012}}</ref>

NASA awarded all 32 of these astronauts its highest honor, the [[NASA Distinguished Service Medal|Distinguished Service Medal]], given for "distinguished service, ability, or courage", and personal "contribution representing substantial progress to the NASA mission". The medals were awarded posthumously to Grissom, White, and Chaffee in 1969, then to the crews of all missions from [[Apollo 8]] onward. The crew that flew the first Earth orbital test mission [[Apollo 7]], [[Wally Schirra|Walter M. Schirra]], [[Donn Eisele]], and [[Walter Cunningham]], were awarded the lesser [[NASA Exceptional Service Medal]], because of discipline problems with the [[Flight controller#Flight Director (FLIGHT)|Flight Director]]'s orders during their flight. The NASA Administrator in October, 2008, decided to award them the Distinguished Service Medals, by this time posthumously to Schirra and Eisele.<ref name="Apollo Crew Honored 2008" >{{cite web |url=http://www.collectspace.com/news/news-102008a.html |title=First Apollo flight crew last to be honored |last=Pearlman |first=Robert Z. |date=October 20, 2008 |website=collectSPACE |publisher=Robert Pearlman |accessdate=June 12, 2014}}</ref>

{{See also|List of Apollo astronauts#Astronauts who flew on Apollo, listed by group|label 1=Astronauts who flew on Apollo, listed by group}}

==Lunar mission profile==
The nominal planned lunar landing mission proceeded as follows:
<gallery widths="190" heights="131">
File:apollo11-01.png|'''Launch''' The 3 Saturn V stages burn for about 11 minutes to achieve a {{convert|100|nmi|km|adj=on}} circular [[parking orbit]]. The third stage burns a small portion of its fuel to achieve orbit.
File:apollo11-02.png|'''[[Trans-lunar injection|Translunar injection]]''' After one to two orbits to verify readiness of spacecraft systems, the [[S-IVB]] third stage reignites for about 6 minutes to send the spacecraft to the Moon.
File:apollo11-03.png|'''[[Transposition, docking, and extraction|Transposition and docking]] (1)''' The [[Apollo (spacecraft)#Spacecraft Lunar Module Adapter (SLA)|Spacecraft Lunar Module Adapter]] (SLA) panels separate to free the CSM and expose the LM. The Command Module Pilot (CMP) moves the CSM out a safe distance, and turns 180°.
File:apollo11-04.png|'''Transposition and docking (2)''', The CMP docks with the LM, and pulls the combined spacecraft away from the S-IVB, which then is sent into solar orbit. The lunar voyage takes between 2 and 3 days. Midcourse corrections are made as necessary using the [[Apollo Command/Service Module#Service Module (SM)|SM]] engine.
File:apollo11-05.png|'''[[Lunar orbit]] insertion''' The spacecraft passes about {{convert|60|nmi|km}} behind the Moon, and the SM engine is fired to slow the spacecraft and put it into a {{convert|60|by|170|nmi|km|adj=on}} orbit, which is soon circularized at 60 nautical miles by a second burn.
File:apollo11-07.png|After a rest period, the Commander (CDR) and Lunar Module Pilot (LMP) move to the LM, power up its systems, and deploy the landing gear. The CSM and LM separate; the CMP visually inspects the LM, then the LM crew move a safe distance away and fire the descent engine for '''Descent orbit insertion''', which takes it to a [[perilune]] of about {{convert|50000|ft|km}}.
File:apollo11-08.png|'''[[Powered Descent Initiation|Powered descent]]''' At perilune, the descent engine fires again to start the descent. The CDR takes over manual control after pitchover for a vertical landing.
File:apollo11-09.png|The CDR and LMP perform one or more [[Extravehicular activity|EVA]]s exploring the lunar surface and collecting samples, alternating with rest periods.
File:apollo11-10.png|The [[Apollo Lunar Module#Ascent stage|ascent stage]] lifts off, using the descent stage as a launching pad.
File:apollo11-11.png|The LM rendezvouses and docks with the CSM.
File:apollo11-12.png|The CDR and LMP transfer back to the CM with their material samples, then the LM ascent stage is jettisoned, to eventually fall out of orbit and crash on the surface.
File:apollo11-13.png|'''[[Trans-Earth injection]]''' The SM engine fires to send the CSM back to Earth.
File:apollo11-14.png|The SM is jettisoned just before reentry, and the CM turns 180° to face its blunt end forward for reentry.
File:apollo11-15.png|Atmospheric drag slows the CM. Aerodynamic heating surrounds it with an envelope of ionized air which causes a communications blackout for several minutes.
File:apollo11-16.png|Parachutes are deployed, slowing the CM for a splashdown in the [[Pacific Ocean]]. The astronauts are recovered and brought to an [[aircraft carrier]].
</gallery>

<gallery widths="470" heights="295">
File:Apollo-Moon-mission-profile.png|Lunar flight profile (distances not to scale).
</gallery>

===Profile variations===
*After Apollo 12 placed the second of several [[seismometer]]s on the Moon, the S-IVBs on subsequent missions were deliberately crashed on the Moon instead of being sent to solar orbit, as an active seismic experiment to induce vibrations in the Moon.
*The first three lunar missions (Apollo 8, [[Apollo 10]], and Apollo 11) used a [[free return trajectory]], keeping a flight path coplanar with the lunar orbit, which would allow a return to Earth in case the SM engine failed to make lunar orbit insertion. Landing site lighting conditions on later missions dictated a lunar orbital plane change, which required a course change maneuver soon after TLI, and eliminated the free-return option.
*On later landing flights, the SM engine was used instead of the LM engine to begin powered descent, in order to allow a greater fuel reserve for landing.
*On Apollo 12 and later missions, the jettisoned LM ascent stages were deliberately crashed on the Moon at known locations, as another active seismic experiment. The only exceptions to this were the Apollo 13 LM which burned up in the Earth's atmosphere, and [[Apollo 16]], where a loss of [[attitude control]] after jettison prevented making a targeted impact.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/planetary/lunar/apolloloc.html |title=Apollo: Where are they now? |last=Williams |first=David R. |work=[[National Space Science Data Center]] |publisher=NASA |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}</ref>

==Development history==

===Unmanned flight tests===
<imagemap>
File:Apollo unmanned launches.png|thumb|right|250px|Apollo unmanned development mission launches. Click on a launch image to read the main article about each mission|alt=Composite image of unmanned development Apollo mission launches in chronological sequence.
rect 0 0 91 494 [[AS-201|AS-201 first unmanned CSM test]]
rect 92 0 181 494 [[AS-203|AS-203 S-IVB stage development test]]
rect 182 0 270 494 [[AS-202|AS-202 second unmanned CSM test]]
rect 271 0 340 494 [[Apollo 4|Apollo 4 first unmanned Saturn V test]]
rect 341 0 434 494 [[Apollo 5|Apollo 5 unmanned LM test]]
rect 435 0 494 494 [[Apollo 6|Apollo 6 second unmanned Saturn V test]]
</imagemap>
{{See also|List of Apollo missions}}

Two Block I CSMs were launched from LC-34 on suborbital flights in 1966 with the Saturn IB. The first, [[AS-201]] launched on February 26, reached an altitude of {{convert|265.7|nmi|km}} and splashed down {{convert|4577|nmi|km}} downrange in the Atlantic ocean.<ref>{{cite book|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/59688171/Post-Launch-Report-for-Mission-as-201-Apollo-Spacecraft-009|title=Postlaunch Report for Mission AS-201 (Apollo Spacecraft 009)|date=May 6, 1966|publisher=NASA|location=Houston, TX|format=PDF|id=MSC-A-R-66-4|accessdate=August 1, 2013}}<!----Original URL for document on NTRS server: http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19750065090_1975065090.pdf----></ref> The second, [[AS-202]] on August 25, reached {{convert|617.1|nmi|km}} altitude and was recovered {{convert|13900|nmi|km}} downrange in the Pacific ocean. These flights validated the Service Module engine and the Command Module heat shield.<ref>{{cite book|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/59690251/Post-Launch-Report-for-Mission-AS-202|title=Postlaunch Report for Mission AS-202 (Apollo Spacecraft 011)|date=October 12, 1966|publisher=NASA|location=Houston, TX|format=PDF|id=MSC-A-R-66-5|accessdate=August 1, 2013}}<!----Original URL for document on NTRS server: http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19740075039_1974075039.pdf----></ref>

A third Saturn IB test, [[AS-203]] launched from pad 37, went into orbit to support design of the S-IVB upper stage restart capability needed for the Saturn V. It carried a nosecone instead of the Apollo spacecraft, and its payload was the unburned liquid hydrogen fuel, the behavior of which engineers measured with temperature and pressure sensors, and a TV camera. This flight occurred on July 5, before AS-202, which was delayed because of problems getting the Apollo spacecraft ready for flight.<ref name=NASAreport>{{cite techreport |last=Chrysler Corp. |title= Evaluation of AS-203 Low Gravity Orbital Experiment |date=January 13, 1967 |publisher=NASA}}</ref>

===Preparation for manned flight===
Two manned orbital Block I CSM missions were planned: AS-204 and AS-205. The Block I crew positions were titled Command Pilot, Senior Pilot, and Pilot. The Senior Pilot would assume navigation duties, while the Pilot would function as a systems engineer. The astronauts would wear [[Gemini space suit#Apollo program|a modified version of the Gemini spacesuit]].

After an unmanned LM test flight AS-206, a crew would fly the first Block II CSM and LM in a dual mission known as AS-207/208, or AS-278 (each spacecraft would be launched on a separate Saturn IB.) The Block II crew positions were titled Commander (CDR) Command Module Pilot (CMP) and Lunar Module Pilot (LMP). The astronauts would begin wearing a new [[Apollo/Skylab A7L|Apollo spacesuit]], designed to accommodate lunar [[extravehicular activity]] (EVA). The traditional visor helmet was replaced with a clear "fishbowl" type for greater visibility, and the lunar surface EVA suit would include a water-cooled undergarment.

[[Deke Slayton]], the grounded [[Mercury Seven|Mercury astronaut]] who became Director of Flight Crew Operations for the Gemini and Apollo programs, selected the first Apollo crew in January 1966, with Grissom as Command Pilot, White as Senior Pilot, and rookie [[Donn F. Eisele]] as Pilot. But Eisele dislocated his shoulder twice aboard the [[reduced gravity aircraft|KC135 weightlessness training aircraft]], and had to undergo surgery on January 27. Slayton replaced him with Chaffee.<ref>{{Citation
 | last = Teitel
 | first = Amy Shira
 | author-link =
 | title = How Donn Eisele Became "Whatshisname," the Command Module Pilot of Apollo 7
 | journal = Popular Science
 | volume =
 | issue =
 | pages =
 | date = December 4, 2013
 | origyear = 2013
 | url = http://www.popsci.com/blog-network/vintage-space/how-donn-eisele-became-whatshisname-command-module-pilot-apollo-7
 | archiveurl =
 | archivedate =
 | jfm = }}</ref> NASA announced the final crew selection for AS-204 on March 21, 1966, with the backup crew consisting of Gemini veterans [[James McDivitt]] and [[David Scott]], with rookie [[Rusty Schweickart|Russell L. "Rusty" Schweickart]]. Mercury/Gemini veteran [[Wally Schirra]], Eisele, and rookie [[Walter Cunningham]] were announced on September 29 as the prime crew for AS-205.

In December 1966, the AS-205 mission was canceled, since the validation of the CSM would be accomplished on the 14-day first flight, and AS-205 would have been devoted to space experiments and contribute no new engineering knowledge about the spacecraft. Its Saturn IB was allocated to the dual mission, now redesignated AS-205/208 or AS-258, planned for August 1967. McDivitt, Scott and Schweickart were promoted to the prime AS-258 crew, and Schirra, Eisele and Cunningham were reassigned as the Apollo 1 backup crew.<ref>[[#Brooks, et al.|Brooks, et al. 1979]], Chapter 8.7: [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch8-7.html "Preparations for the First Manned Apollo Mission"]</ref>

====Program delays====
The spacecraft for the AS-202 and AS-204 missions were delivered by North American Aviation to the Kennedy Space Center with long lists of equipment problems which had to be corrected before flight; these delays caused the launch of AS-202 to slip behind AS-203, and eliminated hopes the first manned mission might be ready to launch as soon as November 1966, concurrently with the last Gemini mission. Eventually the planned AS-204 flight date was pushed to February 21, 1967.<ref name="SP4029">[[#Orloff|Orloff 2004]], [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4029/Apollo_01a_Summary.htm "Apollo 1: The Fire 27&nbsp;January 1967"]</ref>

North American Aviation was prime contractor not only for the Apollo CSM, but for the Saturn V [[S-II]] second stage as well, and delays in this stage pushed the first unmanned Saturn V flight AS-501 from late 1966 to November 1967. (The initial assembly of AS-501 had to use a dummy spacer spool in place of the stage.)<ref>{{cite book |last1=Benson |first1=Charles D. |last2=Faherty |first2=William Barnaby |title=Moonport: A History of Apollo Launch Facilities and Operations |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4204/contents.html |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20080123133438/http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4204/contents.html |archivedate=January 23, 2008 |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |year=1978 |publisher=Scientific and Technical Information Office, NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=3608505 |lccn=77029118 |id=NASA SP-4204 |chapter=Delay after Delay after Delay |chapterurl=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4204/ch19-3.html |deadurl=no}}</ref>

The problems with North American were severe enough in late 1965 to cause Manned Space Flight Administrator George Mueller to appoint program director Samuel Phillips to head a "[[tiger team]]" to investigate North American's problems and identify corrections. Phillips documented his findings in a December 19 letter to NAA president [[Lee Atwood]], with a strongly worded letter by Mueller, and also gave a presentation of the results to Mueller and Deputy Administrator Robert Seamans.<ref>NASA never volunteered the tiger team findings to the US Congress in the course of its regular oversight, but its existence was publicly disclosed as "the Phillips report" in the course of the Senate investigation into the Apollo 204 fire. {{cite web |url=http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/phillip1.html |title=The Phillips Report |publisher=NASA History Office |accessdate=April 14, 2010 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20100415050958/http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/phillip1.html |archivedate=April 15, 2010 <!--DASHBot-->| deadurl=no}}</ref>  Meanwhile, [[Grumman]] was also encountering problems with the Lunar Module, eliminating hopes it would be ready for manned flight in 1967, not long after the first manned CSM flights.<ref>[[#Brooks, et al.|Brooks, et al. 1979]], Chapter 7.4: [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch7-4.html "The LEM Test Program: A Pacing Item"]</ref>

====Disaster strikes====
{{Main|Apollo 1}}
[[File:Apollo 1 fire.jpg|thumb|right|Charred Apollo 1 cabin interior]]

Grissom, White, and Chaffee decided to name their flight Apollo 1 as a motivational focus on the first manned flight. They trained and conducted tests of their spacecraft at North American, and in the altitude chamber at the Kennedy Space Center. A "plugs-out" test was planned for January, which would simulate a launch countdown on LC-34 with the spacecraft transferring from pad-supplied to internal power. If successful, this would be followed by a more rigorous countdown simulation test closer to the February 21 launch, with both spacecraft and launch vehicle fueled.<ref name="sea4">{{cite book |first=Robert C., Jr. |last=Seamans |authorlink=Robert Seamans |publisher=NASA History Office |title=Report of Apollo 204 Review Board |chapter=Description of Test Sequence and Objectives |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/Apollo204/desc.html |date=April 5, 1967 |accessdate=October 7, 2007}}</ref>

The plugs-out test began on the morning of January 27, 1967, and immediately was plagued with problems. First the crew noticed a strange odor in their spacesuits, which delayed the sealing of the hatch. Then, communications problems frustrated the astronauts and forced a hold in the simulated countdown. During this hold, an electrical fire began in the cabin, and spread quickly in the high pressure, 100% oxygen atmosphere. Pressure rose high enough from the fire that the cabin burst and the fire erupted onto the pad area, frustrating attempts to rescue the crew. The astronauts were asphyxiated before the hatch could be opened.<ref name="sea5">{{cite book |first=Robert C., Jr. |last=Seamans |publisher=NASA History Office |title=Report of Apollo 204 Review Board |chapter=Findings, Determinations And Recommendations |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/Apollo204/find.html |date=April 5, 1967 |accessdate=October 7, 2007}}</ref>

NASA immediately convened an accident review board, overseen by both houses of Congress. While the determination of responsibility for the accident was complex, the review board concluded that "deficiencies existed in Command Module design, workmanship and quality control."<ref name="sea5" /> At the insistence of NASA Administrator Webb, North American removed [[Harrison Storms]] as Command Module program manager.<ref>[[#Gray|Gray 1994]]</ref> Webb also reassigned Apollo Spacecraft Program Office (ASPO) Manager [[Joseph Francis Shea]], replacing him with [[George Low]].<ref name="KeyPersonnelChange">[[#Ertel et al.|Ertel et al. 1978]], p. 119</ref>

[[File:Irwin i Bull testują kombinezony kosmiczne S68-15931.jpg|thumb|The Block II spacesuit in January 1968, before (left) and after changes recommended after the Apollo 1 fire]]
To remedy the causes of the fire, changes were made in the Block II spacecraft and operational procedures, the most important of which were use of a nitrogen/oxygen mixture instead of pure oxygen before and during launch, and removal of flammable cabin and space suit materials. The Block II design already called for replacement of the Block I [[plug door|plug-type]] hatch cover with a quick-release, outward opening door. NASA discontinued the manned Block I program, using the Block I spacecraft only for unmanned Saturn V flights. Crew members would also exclusively wear modified, fire-resistant Block II space suits, and would be designated by the Block II titles, regardless of whether a LM was present on the flight or not.

====Unmanned Saturn V and LM tests====
On April 24, 1967, Mueller published an official Apollo mission numbering scheme, using sequential numbers for all flights, manned or unmanned. The sequence would start with [[Apollo 4]] to cover the first three unmanned flights while retiring the Apollo 1 designation to honor the crew, per their widows' wishes.<ref name="missionNumbers">{{Cite web |title=Apollo 11 30th Anniversary: Manned Apollo Missions |publisher=NASA History Office |year=1999 |url=http://history.nasa.gov/ap11ann/missions.htm |accessdate=March 3, 2011 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20110220232013/http://history.nasa.gov/ap11ann/missions.htm |archivedate=February 20, 2011 <!--DASHBot-->|deadurl= no}}</ref><ref>[[#Ertel & al.|Ertel & al. 1978]], Part 1(H)</ref>

In September 1967, Mueller approved a [[List of Apollo mission types|sequence of mission types]] which had to be successfully accomplished in order to achieve the manned lunar landing. Each step had to be successfully accomplished before the next ones could be performed, and it was unknown how many tries of each mission would be necessary; therefore letters were used instead of numbers. The '''A''' missions were unmanned Saturn V validation; '''B''' was unmanned LM validation using the Saturn IB; '''C''' was manned CSM Earth orbit validation using the Saturn IB; '''D''' was the first manned CSM/LM flight (this replaced AS-258, using a single Saturn V launch); '''E''' would be a higher Earth orbit CSM/LM flight; '''F''' would be the first lunar mission, testing the LM in lunar orbit but without landing (a "dress rehearsal"); and '''G''' would be the first manned landing. The list of types covered follow-on lunar exploration to include '''H''' lunar landings, '''I''' for lunar orbital survey missions, and '''J''' for extended-stay lunar landings.<ref name="3Q1967">[[#Ertel et al.|Ertel et al. 1978]], p. 157</ref>

The delay in the CSM caused by the fire enabled NASA to catch up on man-rating the LM and Saturn V. Apollo 4 (AS-501) was the first unmanned flight of the Saturn V, carrying a Block I CSM on November 9, 1967. The capability of the Command Module's heat shield to survive a trans-lunar reentry was demonstrated by using the Service Module engine to ram it into the atmosphere at higher than the usual Earth-orbital reentry speed. This was followed on April 4, 1968, by [[Apollo 6]] (AS-502) which carried a CSM and a LM Test Article as ballast. The intent of this mission was to achieve trans-lunar injection, followed closely by a simulated direct-return abort, using the Service Module engine to achieve another high-speed reentry. The Saturn V experienced [[pogo oscillation]], a problem caused by non-steady engine combustion, which damaged fuel lines in the second and third stages. Two S-II engines shut down prematurely, but the remaining engines were able to compensate. The damage to the third stage engine was more severe, preventing it from restarting for trans-lunar injection. Mission controllers were able to use the Service Module engine to essentially repeat the flight profile of Apollo 4. Based on the good performance of Apollo 6 and identification of satisfactory fixes to the Apollo 6 problems, NASA declared the Saturn V ready to fly men, cancelling a third unmanned test.<ref>[[#Brooks, et al.|Brooks, et al. 1979]], Chapter 10.5: [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/ch10-5.html "Apollo 6: Saturn V's Shaky Dress Rehearsal"]</ref>

[[Apollo 5]] (AS-204) was the first unmanned test flight of LM in Earth orbit, launched from pad 37 on January 22, 1968, by the Saturn IB that would have been used for Apollo 1. The LM engines were successfully test-fired and restarted, despite a computer programming error which cut short the first descent stage firing. The ascent engine was fired in abort mode, known as a "fire-in-the-hole" test, where it was lit simultaneously with jettison of the descent stage. Although Grumman wanted a second unmanned test, George Low decided the next LM flight would be manned.<ref>{{cite book |last=Low |first=George M. |authorlink=George Low |editor-last=Cortright |editor-first=Edgar M |editor-link=Edgar Cortright |title=Apollo Expeditions to the Moon |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-350/cover.html |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |year=1975 |publisher=Scientific and Technical Information Office, NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=1623434 |lccn=75600071 |id=NASA SP-350 |chapter=Testing and Retesting To Get Ready For flight |chapterurl=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-350/ch-4-6.html}}</ref>

===Manned development missions===
<imagemap>
File:Apollo manned development missions insignia.png|thumb|right|250px|Apollo manned development mission patches. Click on a patch to read the main article about that mission|alt=Composite image of 6 manned Apollo development mission patches, from Apollo 1 to Apollo 11.
rect    0   0  595 600 [[Apollo 1|Apollo 1 unsuccessful first manned CSM test]]
rect  596   0 1376 600 [[Apollo 7|Apollo 7 first manned CSM test]]
rect 1377   0 2076 600 [[Apollo 8|Apollo 8 first manned flight to the Moon]]
rect    0 601  595 1200 [[Apollo 9|Apollo 9 manned Earth orbital LM test]]
rect  596 601 1376 1200 [[Apollo 10|Apollo 10 manned lunar orbital LM test]]
rect 1377 601 2076 1200 [[Apollo 11|Apollo 11 first manned Moon landing]]
</imagemap>

[[Apollo 7]], launched from LC-34 on October 11, 1968, was the C mission, crewed by Schirra, Eisele and Cunningham. It was an 11-day Earth-orbital flight which tested the CSM systems.

[[Apollo 8]] was planned to be the D mission in December 1968, crewed by McDivitt, Scott and Schweickart, launched on a Saturn V instead of two Saturn IBs. In the summer it had become clear that the LM would not be ready in time. Rather than waste the Saturn V on another simple Earth-orbiting mission, ASPO Manager George Low suggested the bold step of sending Apollo 8 to orbit the Moon instead, deferring the D mission to the next mission in March 1969, and eliminating the E mission. This would keep the program on track. The [[Soviet Union]] had sent animals around the Moon on September 15, 1968, aboard [[Zond 5]], and it was believed they might soon repeat the feat with human cosmonauts.<ref name="Chaikin">{{cite book |last=Chaikin |first=Andrew |authorlink=Andrew Chaikin |title=[[A Man on the Moon]]: The Voyages of the Apollo Astronauts |year=1994 |publisher=Viking |location=New York |isbn=978-0-670-81446-6 |lccn=93048680 |ref=Chaikin}}</ref><ref name="Moon Race 1968">{{cite news |title=Poised for the Leap |url=http://www.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,844661-1,00.html |accessdate=December 15, 2011 |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=December 6, 1968 |location=New York}}</ref> The decision was not announced publicly until successful completion of Apollo 7. Gemini veterans [[Frank Borman]] and [[Jim Lovell|James Lovell]], and rookie [[William Anders]] captured the world's attention by making 10 lunar orbits in 20 hours, transmitting television pictures of the lunar surface on [[Christmas Eve]], and returning safely to Earth.

The following March, LM flight, rendezvous and docking were successfully demonstrated in Earth orbit on [[Apollo 9]], and Schweickart tested the full lunar EVA suit with its [[Primary Life Support System|Portable Life Support System]] (PLSS) outside the LM.

The F mission was successfully carried out on [[Apollo 10]] in May 1969 by Gemini veterans [[Thomas P. Stafford]], [[John Young (astronaut)|John Young]] and [[Eugene Cernan]]. Stafford and Cernan took the LM to within {{convert|50000|ft|km|sigfig=2}} of the lunar surface.

[[File:Apollo 11 first step.jpg|thumb|[[Neil Armstrong]] descends the LM's ladder in preparation for the first steps on the lunar surface, as televised live on July 20, 1969]]
The G mission was achieved on [[Apollo 11]] in July 1969 by an all-Gemini veteran crew consisting of Neil Armstrong, Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin. Armstrong and Aldrin performed the first landing at the [[Mare Tranquillitatis|Sea of Tranquility]] at 20:17:40 [[UTC]] on July 20, 1969. They spent a total of 21 hours, 36 minutes on the surface, and spent 2 hours, 31 minutes outside the spacecraft, walking on the surface, taking photographs, collecting material samples, and deploying automated scientific instruments, while continuously sending black-and-white television back to Earth. The astronauts returned safely on July 24.

{{quote|text=That's one small step for [a] man, one giant leap for mankind.|sign=[[Neil Armstrong]], just after stepping onto the Moon's surface<ref name="Snopes">{{cite web |url=http://www.snopes.com/quotes/onesmall.asp |title=One Small Misstep: Neil Armstrong's First Words on the Moon |last1=Mikkelson |first1=Barbara |last2=Mikkelson |first2=David P. |date=October 2006 |work=Snopes.com |publisher=[[Snopes.Com|Urban Legends Reference Pages]] |accessdate=September 19, 2009}}</ref>}}

{{Details3|[[Neil Armstrong#First Moon walk|Neil Armstrong—First Moon walk]]}}

===Production lunar landings===
<imagemap>
File:Apollo lunar landing missions insignia.png|thumb|right|250px|Apollo production manned lunar landing mission patches. Click on a patch to read the main article about that mission|alt=Composite image of 6 production manned Apollo lunar landing mission patches, from Apollo 12 to Apollo 17.
rect    0   0  602 600 [[Apollo 12|Apollo 12 second manned Moon landing]]
rect  603   0 1205 600 [[Apollo 13|Apollo 13 unsuccessful Moon landing attempt]]
rect 1206   0 1885 600 [[Apollo 14|Apollo 14 third manned Moon landing]]
rect    0 601  602 1200 [[Apollo 15|Apollo 15 fourth manned Moon landing]]
rect  603 601 1205 1200 [[Apollo 16|Apollo 16 fifth manned Moon landing]]
rect 1206 601 1885 1200 [[Apollo 17|Apollo 17 sixth manned Moon landing]]
</imagemap>

[[File:Apollo landing sites.jpg|thumb|left|Apollo landings on the Moon, 1969–1972]]
In November 1969, Gemini veteran [[Pete Conrad|Charles "Pete" Conrad]] and rookie [[Alan Bean|Alan L. Bean]] made a precision landing on Apollo 12 within walking distance of the [[Surveyor 3]] unmanned lunar probe, which had landed in April 1967 on the [[Ocean of Storms]]. The Command Module Pilot was Gemini veteran [[Richard F. Gordon, Jr.]] Conrad and Bean carried the first lunar surface color television camera, but it was damaged when accidentally pointed into the Sun. They made two EVAs totaling 7 hours and 45 minutes. On one, they walked to the Surveyor, photographed it, and removed some parts which they returned to Earth.<ref>{{cite book |last1=Conrad |first1=Charles, Jr. |authorlink1=Pete Conrad |last2=Shepard |first2=Alan B, Jr. |authorlink2=Alan Shepard |editor-last=Cortright |editor-first=Edgar M |editor-link=Edgar Cortright |title=Apollo Expeditions to the Moon |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-350/cover.html |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |year=1975 |publisher=Scientific and Technical Information Office, NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=1623434 |lccn=75600071 |id=NASA SP-350 |chapter=Tan Dust On Surveyor |chapterurl=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-350/ch-12-3.html}}</ref>

The contracted batch of 15 Saturn Vs were enough for lunar landing missions through Apollo 20. NASA publicized a preliminary list of eight more planned landing sites, with plans to increase the mass of the CSM and LM for the last five missions, along with the payload capacity of the Saturn V. These final missions would combine the I and J types in the 1967 list, allowing the CMP to operate a package of lunar orbital sensors and cameras while his companions were on the surface, and allowing them to stay on the Moon for over three days. These missions would also carry the [[Lunar Roving Vehicle]] (LRV) increasing the exploration area and allowing televised liftoff of the LM. Also, the Block II spacesuit was [[Apollo/Skylab A7L#A7LB Spacesuit (Apollo, Skylab and ASTP)|revised for the extended missions]] to allow greater flexibility and visibility for driving the LRV.

The success of the first two landings allowed the remaining missions to be crewed with a single veteran as Commander, with two rookies. Apollo 13 launched Lovell, [[Jack Swigert]], and [[Fred Haise]] in April 1970, headed for the [[Fra Mauro formation]]. But two days out, a liquid oxygen tank exploded, disabling the Service Module and forcing the crew to use the LM as a "life boat" to return to Earth. Another NASA review board was convened to determine the cause, which turned out to be a combination of damage of the tank in the factory, and a subcontractor not making a tank component according to updated design specifications.<ref name="KSC-Apollo_13" /> Apollo was grounded again, for the remainder of 1970 while the oxygen tank was redesigned and an extra one was added.

====Mission cutbacks====
{{Main|Canceled Apollo missions}}

About the time of the first landing in 1969, it was decided to use an existing Saturn V to launch the Skylab orbital laboratory pre-built on the ground, replacing the original plan to construct it in orbit from several Saturn IB launches; this eliminated Apollo 20. NASA's yearly budget also began to shrink in light of the successful landing, and NASA also had to make funds available for the development of the upcoming [[Space Shuttle]]. By 1971, the decision was made to also cancel missions 18 and 19. The two unused Saturn Vs became museum exhibits at the [[John F. Kennedy Space Center]] on Merritt Island, Florida, [[Marshall Space Flight Center|George C. Marshall Space Center]] in [[Huntsville, Alabama|Huntsville]], Alabama, [[Michoud Assembly Facility]] in [[New Orleans]], Louisiana, and [[Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center]] in Houston, Texas.

The cutbacks forced mission planners to reassess the original planned landing sites in order to achieve the most effective geological sample and data collection from the remaining four missions. [[Apollo 15]] had been planned to be the last of the H series missions, but since there would be only two subsequent missions left, it was changed to the first of three J missions.

Apollo 13's Fra Mauro mission was reassigned to [[Apollo 14]], commanded in February 1971 by Mercury veteran [[Alan Shepard]], with [[Stuart Roosa]] and [[Edgar Mitchell]]. This time the mission was successful. Shepard and Mitchell spent 1 day, 9½ hours on the surface, with two EVAs totalling 9 hours 22½ minutes.

In August 1971, just after conclusion of the Apollo 15 mission, president [[Richard Nixon]] proposed canceling the two remaining lunar landing missions, Apollo 16 and 17. [[Office of Management and Budget]] Deputy Director [[Caspar Weinberger]] was opposed to this, and persuaded Nixon to keep the remaining missions.<ref>"MEMORANDUM FOR THE PRESIDENT" by Caspar Weinberger (via George Schultz), Aug 12, 1971, Page32(of 39) [http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/aeronautics-and-astronautics/16-885j-aircraft-systems-engineering-fall-2005/video-lectures/logsdn_lec_notes.pdf]</ref>

====Extended missions====
[[File:Apollo 15 Lunar Rover and Irwin.jpg|thumb|left|[[Lunar Roving Vehicle]] used on Apollos 15–17]]
[[File:Apollo17 plaque.jpg|thumb|right|Plaque left on the Moon by [[Apollo 17]]]]

Apollo 15 was launched on July 26, 1971, with David Scott, [[Alfred Worden]] and [[James Irwin]]. Scott and Irwin landed on July 30 near [[Mons Hadley|Hadley Rille]], and spent just under 2 days, 19 hours on the surface. In over 18 hours of EVA, they collected about {{convert|77|kg|lb}} of lunar material.

Apollo 16 landed in the [[Descartes Highlands]] in April 1972. The crew was commanded by John Young, with [[Ken Mattingly]] and [[Charles Duke]]. Young and Duke spent just under 3 days on the surface, with a total of over 20 hours EVA.

Apollo 17 was the last of the Apollo program, landing in the [[Taurus-Littrow]] region in December 1972. Eugene Cernan commanded [[Ronald Evans (astronaut)|Ronald E. Evans]] and NASA's first scientist-astronaut, geologist Dr. [[Harrison Schmitt|Harrison H. Schmitt]]. Schmitt was originally scheduled for Apollo 18, but the lunar geological community lobbied for his inclusion on the final lunar landing. Cernan and Schmitt stayed on the surface for just under 3 days, 3 hours and spent just over 23 hours of total EVA.
{{clear}}

==Mission summary==
{{main|List of Apollo missions}}
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Designation  !! Date !! Launch<br>Vehicle !! CSM !! LM !! Crew !! Summary
|-
| [[AS-201]] ||width=120px| Feb. 26, 1966|| AS-201 ||width=60px| CSM-009|| None||width=130px| None|| First flight of Saturn IB and Block I CSM; suborbital to Atlantic ocean; qualified heat shield to orbital reentry speed
|-
| [[AS-203]] || July 5, 1966|| AS-203 || None|| None|| None|| No spacecraft; observations of liquid hydrogen fuel behavior in orbit, to support design of S-IVB restart capability
|-
| [[AS-202]] || Aug. 25, 1966|| AS-202 || CSM-011|| None|| None|| Suborbital flight of CSM to Pacific ocean
|-
| [[Apollo 1]] || Feb 21, 1967|| AS-204 || CSM-012|| None||[[Gus Grissom]] [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White]] [[Roger B. Chaffee]] || Not flown; all crew members perished in fire on launch pad on January 27, 1967
|-
| [[Apollo 4]] || Nov. 9, 1967|| AS-501 || CSM-017|| None|| None|| First test flight of Saturn V, placed a CSM in a high Earth orbit; demonstrated S-IVB restart; qualified CM heat shield to lunar reentry speed
|-
| [[Apollo 5]] || Jan. 22–23, 1968|| AS-204 || None|| LM-1|| None|| Earth orbital flight test of LM, launched on Saturn IB; demonstrated ascent and descent propulsion; man-rated the LM
|-
| [[Apollo 6]] || April 4, 1968|| AS-502 || CM-020<br>SM-014|| None|| None|| Unmanned, attempted demonstration of trans-lunar injection, and direct-return abort using SM engine; three engine failures, including failure of S-IVB restart. Flight controllers used SM engine to repeat Apollo 4's flight profile. Man-rated the Saturn V.
|-
| [[Apollo 7]] || Oct. 11–22, 1968|| AS-205 || CSM-101|| None||[[Wally Schirra]]<br>[[Walter Cunningham|Walt Cunningham]]<br>[[Donn F. Eisele|Donn Eisele]]|| First manned Earth orbital demonstration of Block II CSM, launched on Saturn IB. First live television publicly broadcast from a manned mission
|-
| [[Apollo 8]] || Dec. 21–27, 1968|| AS-503 || CSM-103|| None||[[Frank Borman]]<br>[[Jim Lovell|James Lovell]]<br>[[William Anders]]|| First manned flight to Moon; CSM made 10 lunar orbits in 20 hours.
|-
| [[Apollo 9]] || Mar. 3–13, 1969|| AS-504 || CSM-104 ''Gumdrop''|| LM-3<br>''Spider''||[[James McDivitt]]<br>[[David Scott]]<br>[[Rusty Schweickart|Russell Schweickart]]|| First manned flight of CSM and LM in Earth orbit; demonstrated Portable Life Support System to be used on the lunar surface
|-
| [[Apollo 10]] || May 18–26, 1969|| AS-505 || CSM-106 ''Charlie Brown''|| LM-4<br>''Snoopy||[[Thomas P. Stafford|Thomas Stafford]]<br>[[John Young (astronaut)|John Young]]<br>[[Eugene Cernan]]|| Dress rehearsal for first lunar landing; flew LM down to {{convert|50000|ft|km}} from lunar surface
|-
| [[Apollo 11]] || July 16–24, 1969|| AS-506 ||CSM-107 ''Columbia''|| LM-5 ''Eagle''||[[Neil Armstrong]]<br>[[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]]<br>[[Buzz Aldrin]]|| First manned landing, in Sea of Tranquility. Surface EVA time: 2:31 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|47.51|lb|kg}}
|-
| [[Apollo 12]] || Nov. 14–24, 1969|| AS-507 ||CSM-108 ''Yankee Clipper''|| LM-6<br>''Intrepid''||[[Pete Conrad|C. "Pete" Conrad]]<br>[[Richard F. Gordon, Jr.|Richard Gordon]]<br>[[Alan Bean]]|| Second landing, in Ocean of Storms near Surveyor 3 . Surface EVA time: 7:45 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|75.62|lb|kg}}
|-
| [[Apollo 13]] || April 11–17, 1970|| AS-508 || CSM-109 ''Odyssey''|| LM-7<br>''Aquarius''||[[Jim Lovell|James Lovell]]<br>[[Jack Swigert]]<br>[[Fred Haise]]|| Third landing attempt aborted near the Moon, due to SM failure. Crew used LM as "life boat" to return to Earth.
|-
| [[Apollo 14]] || Jan. 31–Feb. 9, 1971|| AS-509 || CSM-110 ''Kitty Hawk''|| LM-8<br>''Antares''||[[Alan Shepard]]<br>[[Stuart Roosa]]<br>[[Edgar Mitchell]]|| Third landing, in Fra Mauro. Surface EVA time: 9:21 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|94.35|lb|kg}}.
|-
| [[Apollo 15]] || July 26–Aug. 7, 1971|| AS-510 || CSM-112 ''Endeavour''|| LM-10<br>''Falcon''||[[David Scott]]<br> [[Alfred Worden]]<br> [[James Irwin]]|| First Extended LM and rover, landed in Hadley-Apennine. Surface EVA time:18:33 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|169.10|lb|kg}}.
|-
| [[Apollo 16]] || April 16–27, 1972|| AS-511 || CSM-113 ''Casper''|| LM-11<br>''Orion''||[[John Young (astronaut)|John Young]]<br>[[Ken Mattingly|T. Kenneth Mattingly]]<br>[[Charles Duke]]|| Landed in Plain of Descartes. Surface EVA time: 20:14 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|207.89|lb|kg}}.
|-
| [[Apollo 17]] || Dec. 7–19, 1972|| AS-512 || CSM-114 ''America''|| LM-12<br>''Challenger''||[[Eugene Cernan]]<br>[[Ronald Evans (astronaut)|Ronald Evans]]<br>[[Harrison Schmitt]]|| Only Saturn V night launch. Landed in Taurus-Littrow. First geologist on the Moon. Final manned Moon landing. Surface EVA time: 22:02 hr. Samples returned: {{convert|243.40|lb|kg}}.
|}
Source for surface times and sample amounts: ''Apollo by the Numbers: A Statistical Reference'' (Orloff 2004).<ref name="Orloff-EVA">[[#Orloff|Orloff 2004]], [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4029/Apollo_18-30_Extravehicular_Activity.htm "Extravehicular Activity"]</ref>

==Samples returned==
{{Main|Moon rock}}
{{multiple image
|align=right
|image1=Apollo 15 Genesis Rock.jpg
|width1=150
|caption1=The most famous of the Moon rocks recovered, the [[Genesis Rock]], returned from Apollo&nbsp;15.
|image2=Lunar Ferroan Anorthosite 60025.jpg
|width2=132
|caption2=Ferroan [[Anorthosite]] Moon rock, returned from Apollo&nbsp;16.}}

The Apollo program returned {{convert|837.87|lb|kg}} of lunar rocks and [[lunar soil|soil]] to the [[Lunar Receiving Laboratory]] in Houston.<ref name="Orloff-EVA"/> Today, most of the samples are stored at the [[Lunar Sample Laboratory Facility]] built in 1979.

The rocks collected from the Moon are extremely old compared to rocks found on Earth, as measured by [[radiometric dating]] techniques. They range in age from about 3.2 billion years for the [[basalt]]ic samples derived from the [[lunar mare|lunar maria]], to about 4.6 billion years for samples derived from the [[Lunar highlands|highlands]] crust.<ref>[[#Papike et al.|Papike et al. 1998]], pp. 5-001 – 5-234</ref> As such, they represent samples from a very early period in the development of the [[Solar System]], that are largely absent on Earth. One important rock found during the Apollo Program is dubbed the [[Genesis Rock]], retrieved by astronauts David Scott and James Irwin during the Apollo 15 mission. This [[anorthosite]] rock is composed almost exclusively of the calcium-rich feldspar mineral [[anorthite]], and is believed to be representative of the highland crust. A geochemical component called [[KREEP]] was discovered, which has no known terrestrial counterpart. KREEP and the anorthositic samples have been used to infer that the outer portion of the Moon was once completely molten (see [[lunar magma ocean]]).

Almost all the rocks show evidence of impact process effects. Many samples appear to be pitted with [[micrometeoroid]] impact craters, which is never seen on Earth rocks, due to the thick atmosphere. Many show signs of being subjected to high pressure shock waves that are generated during impact events. Some of the returned samples are of ''impact melt'' (materials melted near an impact crater.) All samples returned from the Moon are highly [[breccia]]ted as a result of being subjected to multiple impact events.

Analysis of composition of the lunar samples supports the [[giant impact hypothesis]], that the Moon was created through impact of a large astronomical body with the Earth.<ref>[[#Burrows|Burrows 1999]], p. 431</ref>

==Costs==
When President Kennedy first chartered the Moon landing program, a preliminary cost estimate of $7 billion was generated, but this proved an extremely unrealistic guess of what could not possibly be determined precisely, and James Webb used his judgment as administrator to change the estimate to $20 billion before giving it to Vice President Johnson.<ref name=Butts>{{cite web |last1=Butts |first1=Glenn |last2=Linton |first2=Kent |title=The Joint Confidence Level Paradox: A History of Denial |work=2009 NASA Cost Symposium |publisher=Cost Analysis Division |date=April 28, 2009 |pages=25–26 |url=http://science.ksc.nasa.gov/shuttle/nexgen/Nexgen_Downloads/Butts_NASA's_Joint_Cost-Schedule_Paradox_-_A_History_of_Denial.pdf |postscript= <!--None--> }}</ref>

When Kennedy made his 1962 speech at Rice University, the annual space budget was $5.4 billion, and he described this cost as 40 cents per person per week, "somewhat less than we pay for cigarettes and cigars every year", but that the Moon program would soon raise this to "more than 50 cents a week for every man, woman and child in the United States".<ref name="Rice Speech"/>

Webb's estimate shocked many at the time (including the President) but ultimately proved to be reasonably accurate. In January 1969, NASA prepared an itemized estimate of the run-out cost of the Apollo program. The total came to $23.9 billion, itemized as follows:<ref>[[#Wilford|Wilford 1969]], p. 67</ref>
*Apollo spacecraft: $7,945.0 million
*Saturn I launch vehicles: $767.1 million
*Saturn IB launch vehicles: $1,131.2 million
*Saturn V launch vehicles: $6,871.1 million
*Launch vehicle engine development: $854.2 million
*Mission support: $1,432.3 million
*Tracking and data acquisition: $664.1 million
*Ground facilities: $1,830.3 million
*Operation of installations: $2,420.6 million

The final cost of Apollo was reported to Congress as $25.4 billion in 1973.<ref>[[#93rd Congress|93rd Congress 1973]], p. 1271</ref>  It took up the majority of NASA's budget while it was being developed. For example, in 1966 it accounted for about 60 percent of NASA's total $5.2 billion budget.<ref>{{cite book |last1=Skolnikoff |first1=Eugene B. |last2=Hoagland |first2=John H. |title=The World-wide Spread of Space Technology |series=69-5 |year=1968 |publisher=[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology School of Science#MIT Kavli Institute for Astrophysics & Space Research|MIT Center for Space Research]] |location=Cambridge, MA |oclc=14154430 |ref=Skolnikoff & Hoagland}}</ref> A single Saturn V launch in 1969 cost up to $375 million, compared to the [[National Science Foundation]]'s fiscal year 1970 budget of $440 million.<ref>[[#Heppenheimer|Heppenheimer 1999]], Chapter 2: [http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4221/ch2.htm "NASA's Uncertain Future"], p. 73</ref>

In 2009, NASA held a symposium on project costs which presented an estimate of the Apollo program costs in 2005 dollars as roughly $170 billion. This included all [[research and development]] costs; the procurement of 15 Saturn V rockets, 16 Command/Service Modules, 12 Lunar Modules, plus program support and management costs; construction expenses for facilities and their upgrading, and costs for flight operations. This was based on a [[Congressional Budget Office]] report, ''A Budgetary Analysis of NASA's New Vision for Space'', September 2004.<ref name=Butts/> ''The Space Review'' estimated in 2010 the cost of Apollo from 1959 to 1973 as $20.4 billion, or $109 billion in 2010 dollars.<ref name="lafleur20100308">{{cite news |title=Costs of US piloted programs |first=Claude |last=Lafleur |url=http://www.thespacereview.com/article/1579/1 |work=[[The Space Review]] |date=March 8, 2010 |accessdate=February 18, 2012}}</ref>

==Apollo Applications Program==
{{Main|Apollo Applications Program}}

Looking beyond the manned lunar landings, NASA investigated several post-lunar applications for Apollo hardware. The Apollo Extension Series (''Apollo X'',) proposed up to 30 flights to Earth orbit, using the space in the [[Apollo (spacecraft)#Spacecraft Lunar Module Adapter (SLA)|Spacecraft Lunar Module Adapter]] (SLA) to house a small orbital laboratory (workshop). Astronauts would continue to use the CSM as a ferry to the station. This study was followed by design of a larger orbital workshop to be built in orbit from an empty S-IVB Saturn upper stage, and grew into the Apollo Applications Program (AAP). The workshop was to be supplemented by Apollo Telescope Missions, which would replace the LM's descent stage equipment and engine with a solar telescope observatory. The most ambitious plan called for using an empty S-IVB as an interplanetary spacecraft for a [[Manned Venus Flyby|Venus fly-by mission]].

The S-IVB orbital workshop was the only one of these plans to make it off the drawing board. Dubbed [[Skylab]], it was constructed complete on the ground rather than in space, and launched in 1973 using the two lower stages of a Saturn V. It was equipped with an [[Apollo Telescope Mount]], the solar telescope that would have been used on the Apollo Telescope Missions. Skylab's last crew departed the station on February 8, 1974, and the station itself re-entered the atmosphere in 1979, by which time it had become the oldest operational Apollo-Saturn component.

==Recent observations==
[[File:Lroc apollo11 landing site 20091109 zoom.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.15|“There the [Apollo 11] lunar module sits, parked just where it landed 40 years ago, as if it still really were 40 years ago and all the time since merely imaginary.” –''The New York Times''<ref name="nyt_lro_lm_img">{{cite news |title=The Human Moon |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/17/opinion/17tue4.html |work=The New York Times |date=November 16, 2009 |accessdate=November 19, 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091119041921/http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/17/opinion/17tue4.html| archivedate=November 19, 2009 <!--DASHBot-->| deadurl=no}}</ref>]]

In September 2007, the [[X Prize Foundation|X PRIZE Foundation]] and [[Google]] announced the [[Google Lunar X Prize]], to be awarded for a robotic lunar landing mission which transmits close-up images of the Apollo Lunar Modules and [[List of artificial objects on the Moon|other artificial objects on the surface]].<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.googlelunarxprize.org/prize-details/rules-overview |title=Rules Overview |work=[[Google Lunar X Prize]] |publisher=[[X Prize Foundation|X PRIZE Foundation]] |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

In 2008, [[Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency]]'s [[SELENE]] probe observed evidence of the halo surrounding the Apollo 15 Lunar Module blast crater while orbiting above the lunar surface.<ref>{{cite press release |title=The 'halo' area around Apollo 15 landing site observed by Terrain Camera on SELENE(KAGUYA) |date=May 20, 2008 |publisher=[[Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency]] |location=Chōfu, Tokyo |url=http://www.jaxa.jp/press/2008/05/20080520_kaguya_e.html |accessdate=November 19, 2009 |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091212114843/http://www.jaxa.jp/press/2008/05/20080520_kaguya_e.html |archivedate=December 12, 2009 <!--DASHBot-->| deadurl=no}}</ref> In 2009, NASA's [[robotic spacecraft|robotic]] [[Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter]], while orbiting {{convert|50|km|mi|sigfig=2|sp=us}} above the Moon, photographed the remnants of the Apollo program left on the lunar surface, and photographed each site where manned Apollo flights landed.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/LRO/multimedia/lroimages/apollosites.html |title=LRO Sees Apollo Landing Sites |last1=Hautaluoma |first1=Grey |last2=Freeberg |first2=Andy |editor-last=Garner |editor-first=Robert|date=July 17, 2009 |publisher=NASA |accessdate=November 19, 2009 |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091116012309/http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/LRO/multimedia/lroimages/apollosites.html| archivedate= November 16, 2009 <!--DASHBot-->| deadurl= no}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/revisited/index.html |editor-last=Townsend |editor-first=Jason |title=Apollo Landing Sites Revisited |publisher=NASA |accessdate=November 19, 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091113094613/http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/revisited/index.html| archivedate= November 13, 2009 <!--DASHBot-->| deadurl= no}}</ref> All of the U. S. flags left on the Moon during the Apollo missions were found to still be standing, with the exception of the one left during the Apollo 11 mission, which was blown over during that mission's lift-off from the lunar surface and return to the mission Command Module in lunar orbit; the degree to which these flags retain their original colors remains unknown.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://lroc.sese.asu.edu/news/index.php?/archives/620-Question-Answered!.html |title=Question Answered! |last=Robinson |first=Mark |date=July 27, 2012 |work=LROC News System |publisher=[[Arizona State University]] |accessdate=October 28, 2012}}</ref>

In a November 16, 2009 editorial, ''[[The New York Times]]'' opined:
{{quote|[T]here's something terribly wistful about these photographs of the Apollo landing sites. The detail is such that if Neil Armstrong were walking there now, we could make him out, make out his footsteps even, like the astronaut footpath clearly visible in the photos of the Apollo 14 site. Perhaps the wistfulness is caused by the sense of simple grandeur in those Apollo missions. Perhaps, too, it’s a reminder of the risk we all felt after the Eagle had landed – the possibility that it might be unable to lift off again and the astronauts would be stranded on the Moon. But it may also be that a photograph like this one is as close as we’re able to come to looking directly back into the human past.<ref name="nyt_lro_lm_img"/>}}

==Legacy==

===Science and engineering===
{{further|NASA spin-off technologies}}

The Apollo program has been called the greatest technological achievement in human history.<ref>{{Cite web |title=Apollo 11 30th Anniversary: Introduction |publisher=NASA History Office |year=1999 |url=http://history.nasa.gov/ap11ann/introduction.htm |accessdate=April 26, 2013}}</ref><ref>{{cite news |title=The Moon Landing |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/special_report/1999/07/99/the_Moon_landing/396037.stm |work=[[BBC News]] |publisher=[[BBC]] |location=London |date=July 23, 1999 |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20021002030438/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/special_report/1999/07/99/the_moon_landing/396037.stm |archivedate=October 2, 2002}}</ref> Apollo stimulated many areas of technology, leading to over 1,800 spinoff products as of 2015.<ref>{{cite web|last=NASA Spinoff Database|url=http://spinoff.nasa.gov/spinoff/database|publisher=National Aeronautics and Space Administration|title=NASA Spinoff Database|date=April 8, 2016}}</ref> The [[Apollo Guidance Computer|flight computer]] design used in both the Lunar and Command Modules was, along with the [[LGM-30 Minuteman|Minuteman Missile System]], the driving force behind early research into [[integrated circuit]]s.<ref>{{cite book |last=Mindell |first=David A. |title=Digital Apollo: Human and Machine in Spaceflight |year=2008 |publisher=The MIT Press |isbn=978-0-262-13497-2}}</ref> [[Numerical control|Computer-controlled machining]] was first used in the fabrication of Apollo structural components.

===Cultural impact===
[[File:NASA-Apollo8-Dec24-Earthrise.jpg|thumb|left|"Everything that I ever knew – my life, my loved ones, the Navy – everything, the whole world was behind my thumb." –[[Jim Lovell|James Lovell]] |alt=The Earth over the lunar horizon, photographed by the Apollo 8 crew]]

The crew of Apollo 8 sent the first live televised pictures of the Earth and the Moon back to Earth, and read from the creation story in the [[Book of Genesis]], on Christmas Eve, 1968. An estimated one-quarter of the population of the world saw—either live or delayed—the Christmas Eve transmission during the ninth orbit of the Moon.<ref> [[#Chaikin|Chaikin 1994]], p. 120</ref> The mission and Christmas provided an inspiring end to 1968, which had been a troubled year for the US, marked by [[Vietnam War]] protests, race riots, and the assassinations of civil rights leader [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]], and Senator [[Robert F. Kennedy]].

An estimated one-fifth of the population of the world watched the live transmission of the Apollo 11 moonwalk.<ref>[[#Burrows|Burrows 1999]], p. 429</ref>

[[File:The Earth seen from Apollo 17.jpg|thumb|right|[[The Blue Marble]] photograph taken on December 7, 1972 during Apollo 17. "We went to explore the Moon, and in fact discovered the Earth." –[[Eugene Cernan]] ]]
An effect of the Apollo program is the view of Earth as a fragile, small planet, captured in photographs taken by the astronauts during the lunar missions. The most famous, taken by the Apollo 17 astronauts, is [[The Blue Marble]].

Many astronauts and cosmonauts have commented on the profound effects that seeing Earth from space has had on them;<ref>{{cite book |last=White |first=Frank |title=The Overview Effect: Space Exploration and Human Evolution |edition=2nd |year=1998 |publisher=[[American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics]] |location=Reston, VA |isbn=1-56347-260-0 |oclc=39001291 |lccn=98023507 |ref=White}}</ref> the [[List of Apollo astronauts|24 astronauts who traveled to the Moon]] are the only humans to have observed Earth from beyond low Earth orbit, and have traveled farther from Earth than anyone else to date.

According to ''[[The Economist]]'', Apollo succeeded in accomplishing President Kennedy's goal of taking on the Soviet Union in the [[Space Race]], and beat it by accomplishing a singular and significant achievement, and thereby showcased the superiority of the capitalistic, free-market system as represented by the US. The publication noted the irony that in order to achieve the goal, the program required the organization of tremendous public resources within a vast, centralized government bureaucracy.<ref>{{cite news |title=Apollo plus 50 |editor-last=Lexington |url=http://www.economist.com/node/18712369 |work=[[The Economist]] |publisher=[[Economist Group|The Economist Newspaper Limited]] |location=London |date=May 21, 2011 |page=36 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

There are those who, despite evidence to the contrary, deny that the moon landings took place. The Apollo [[Moon landing conspiracy theories|moon landing hoax]] claims helped propel [[List of conspiracy theories|conspiracy theories]] into a quasi-political narrative.<ref>[http://theweek.com/articles/459843/brief-history-conspiracy-theories]</ref>

==Apollo 11 broadcast data restoration project==
{{see also|Apollo 11 missing tapes}}

As part of Apollo 11's 40th anniversary in 2009, NASA spearheaded an effort to digitally restore the existing videotapes of the mission's live televised moonwalk.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/40th/ |title=Apollo 40th Anniversary |publisher=NASA |date= |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20120609022513/http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/40th/ |archivedate=June 9, 2012 |accessdate=June 21, 2012}}</ref> After an exhaustive three-year search for missing tapes of the original video of the Apollo 11 moonwalk, NASA concluded the data tapes had more than likely been accidentally erased.<ref name=NPR_tapes>{{cite web |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=106637066 |title=Houston, We Erased The Apollo 11 Tapes |last=Greenfieldboyce |first=Nell |authorlink=Nell Greenfieldboyce |date=July 16, 2009 |work=[[NPR]] |publisher=National Public Radio, Inc. |location=Washington, D.C. |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref>

{{quote|We're all saddened that they're not there. We all wish we had 20-20 hindsight. I don't think anyone in the NASA organization did anything wrong, I think it slipped through the cracks, and nobody's happy about it.|Dick Nafzger, TV Specialist, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center<ref name=NPR_tapes/>}}

The Moon landing data was recorded by a special [[Apollo TV camera]] which recorded in a format incompatible with broadcast TV. This resulted in lunar footage that had to be converted for the live television broadcast and stored on magnetic telemetry tapes. During the following years, a magnetic tape shortage prompted NASA to remove massive numbers of magnetic tapes from the [[National Archives and Records Administration]] to be recorded over with newer satellite data. Stan Lebar, who led the team that designed and built the lunar television camera at [[Westinghouse Electric (1886)|Westinghouse Electric Corporation]], also worked with Nafzger to try to locate the missing tapes.<ref name=NPR_tapes/>

{{quote|So I don't believe that the tapes exist today at all. It was a hard thing to accept. But there was just an overwhelming amount of evidence that led us to believe that they just don't exist anymore. And you have to accept reality.|Stan Lebar, lunar television camera designer, Westinghouse Electric Corporation<ref name=NPR_tapes/>}}

With a budget of $230,000, the surviving original lunar broadcast data from Apollo 11 was compiled by Nafzger and assigned to [[Lowry Digital]] for restoration. The video was processed to remove random noise and camera shake without destroying historical legitimacy.<ref name="Moon footage restore">{{cite news |url=http://www.usnews.com/science/articles/2009/07/17/nasa-lost-moon-footage-but-hollywood-restores-it |title=NASA lost moon footage, but Hollywood restores it |date=July 17, 2009 |first=Seth |last=Borenstein |agency=Associated Press |newspaper=[[U.S. News & World Report]] |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}</ref> The images were from tapes in [[Australia]], the [[CBS News]] archive, and [[kinescope]] recordings made at Johnson Space Center. The restored video, remaining in black and white, contains conservative digital enhancements and did not include sound quality improvements.<ref name="Moon footage restore"/>

==Depictions on film==

===Documentaries===
Numerous documentary films cover the Apollo program and the Space Race, including:
* ''[[Moonwalk One]]'' (1970)
* ''[[For All Mankind]]'' (1989)
* "Moon" from the BBC miniseries ''[[The Planets (TV miniseries)|The Planets]]'' (1999)
* ''[[Magnificent Desolation: Walking on the Moon 3D]]'' (2005)
* ''[[The Wonder of It All (2007 film)|The Wonder of It All]]'' (2007)
* ''[[In the Shadow of the Moon (film)|In the Shadow of the Moon]]'' (2007)
* ''[[When We Left Earth: The NASA Missions]]'' (miniseries) (2008)
* ''[[Moon Machines]]'' (miniseries) (2008)
* ''[[James May on the Moon]]'' (documentary commemorating 40 years since the landings) (2009)
* ''[[NASA's Story]]'' (documentary series) (2009)
* ''[http://moonscapemovie.blogspot.ch/p/watch-latest-release-of-moonscape.html Moonscape]'' (freely downloadable Apollo 11 documentary) (2012)

===Docudramas===
The Apollo program, or certain missions, have been [[docudrama|dramatized]] in ''[[Apollo 13 (film)|Apollo 13]]'' (1995), ''[[Apollo 11 (film)|Apollo 11]]'' (1996), ''[[From the Earth to the Moon (TV miniseries)|From the Earth to the Moon]]'' (1998), ''[[Space Race (TV series)|Space Race]]'' (2005), and ''[[Moonshot (film)|Moonshot]]'' (2009).

==See also==
{{Portal|Spaceflight|Moon}}
* [[commons:Apollo 11 flight|Apollo 11 flight to the Moon]]
* [[Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package]]
* [[Apollo TV camera]]
* [[Exploration of the Moon]]
* [[List of man-made objects on the Moon]]
* [[List of megaprojects]]
* [[Lockheed Propulsion Company]]
* [[Moon landing]]
* [[Moon landing conspiracy theories]]
* [[Soviet manned lunar programs]]
* [[Space policy of the United States]]
* [[Splashdown (spacecraft landing)]]
* [[Stolen and missing moon rocks]]

==References==
{{NASA}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin|colwidth=30em}}
* {{cite book |last=Beschloss |first=Michael R. |authorlink=Michael Beschloss |editor1-last=Launius |editor1-first=Roger D. |editor2-last=McCurdy |editor2-first=Howard E. |title=Spaceflight and the Myth of Presidential Leadership |year=1997 |publisher=University of Illinois Press |location=Champaign, IL |isbn=0-252-06632-4 |lccn=96051213 |chapter=Kennedy and the Decision to Go to the Moon |ref=Beschloss}}
* {{cite book |last=Bilstein |first=Roger E. |others=Foreword by [[William R. Lucas]] |title=Stages to Saturn: A Technological History of the Apollo/Saturn Launch Vehicles |url=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4206/contents.htm |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |origyear=Originally published 1980 |year=1996 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington D.C. |oclc=36332191 |id=NASA SP-4206 |ref=Bilstein}}
* {{cite book |last1=Brooks |first1=Courtney G. |last2=Grimwood |first2=James M. |last3=Swenson |first3=Loyd S., Jr. |others=Foreword by [[Samuel C. Phillips]] |title=Chariots for Apollo: A History of Manned Lunar Spacecraft |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/SP-4205/cover.html |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |year=1979 |publisher=Scientific and Technical Information Branch, NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-0-486-46756-6 |oclc=4664449 |lccn=79001042 |id=NASA SP-4205 |ref=Brooks, et al.}}
* {{cite book |last=Burrows |first=William E. |title=This New Ocean: The Story of the First Space Age |year=1999 |publisher=Modern Library |isbn=0-375-75485-7 |oclc=42136309 |ref=Burrows}}
* {{cite book |last=Chaikin |first=Andrew |authorlink=Andrew Chaikin |title=[[A Man on the Moon]] |year=1994 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=New York |isbn=0-14-027201-1 |oclc=38918860 |ref=Chaikin}} Chaikin interviewed all the surviving astronauts and others who worked with the program.
* {{cite book |author=[[United States Congress|Congress]], [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]], [[United States House Committee on Science, Space and Technology|Committee on Science and Astronautics]] |title=Discussion of Soviet Man-in-space Shot |type=Hearing |date=April 13, 1961 |publisher=[[87th United States Congress|87th Congress]], first session |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=4052829 |lccn=61061306 |ref=87th Congress}}
* {{cite book |author=Congress, House of Representatives, Committee on Science and Astronautics |title=1974 NASA Authorization Hearings |type=Hearing on H.R. 4567 |year=1973 |publisher=[[93rd United States Congress|93rd Congress]], first session |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=23229007 |ref=93rd Congress}}
* {{cite book |last1=Dawson |first1=Virginia P. |last2=Bowles |first2=Mark D. |title=Taming Liquid Hydrogen: The Centaur Upper Stage Rocket 1958-2002 |url=http://www.history.nasa.gov/SP-4230.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=September 12, 2012 |series=The NASA History Series |year=2004 |publisher=NASA |id=NASA SP-2400-4320 |oclc=51518552 |ref=Dawson & Bowles}}
* {{cite book |last1=Ertel |first1=Ivan D. |last2=Newkirk |first2=Roland W. |last3=Brooks |first3=Courtney G. |others=Foreword by Kenneth S. Kleinknecht |title=The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology |url=http://www.lpi.usra.edu/lunar/documents/NTRS/collection3/NASA_SP_4009-4.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |volume=IV |year=1978 |publisher=Scientific and Technical Information Office, NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |id=NASA SP-4009 |oclc=23818 |lccn=69060008 |display-authors=2 |ref=Ertel et al.}}
* {{cite book |last=Gray |first=Mike |authorlink=Mike Gray |title=Angle of Attack: Harrison Storms and the Race to the Moon |origyear=First published [[W. W. Norton & Company]] 1992 |year=1994 |publisher=[[Penguin Books]] |location=New York |isbn=0-14-023280-X |oclc=30520885 |ref=Gray}}
* {{cite book |last=Hansen |first=James R. |title=Enchanted Rendezvous: John C. Houbolt and the Genesis of the Lunar-Orbit Rendezvous Concept |url=http://history.nasa.gov/monograph4.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=May 3, 2012 |series=Monographs in Aerospace History Number 4 |year=1999 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=69343822 |ref=Hansen}}
* {{cite book |last=Heppenheimer |first=T.A. |title=The Space Shuttle Decision: NASA's Search for a Reusable Space Vehicle |url=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4221/sp4221.htm |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |year=1999 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=40305626 |id=NASA SP-4221 |ref=Heppenheimer}}
* {{cite book |last=Johnson |first=Stephen B. |title=The Secret of Apollo: Systems Management in American and European Space Programs |series=New series in NASA history |year=2002 |publisher=[[Johns Hopkins University Press]] |location=Baltimore |isbn=0-8018-6898-X |oclc=48003131 |lccn=2001005688 |ref=Johnson}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Launius |editor1-first=Roger D. |editor2-last=McCurdy |editor2-first=Howard E. |title=Spaceflight and the Myth of Presidential Leadership |year=1997 |publisher=University of Illinois Press |isbn=0-252-06632-4 |lccn=96051213 |location=Champaign, IL |ref=Launius & McCurdy}}
* {{cite book |last=Launius |first=Roger D. |title=Apollo: A Retrospective Analysis |url=https://archive.org/details/nasa_techdoc_20040084534 |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |edition=Reprint |series=Monographs in Aerospace History Number 3 |origyear=Originally published July 1994 |date=July 2004 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |ref=Launius}}
* {{cite book
 | last = Letterman
 | first = John B.
 | authorlink =
 | title = Survivors: True Tales of Endurance: 500 Years of the Greatest Eyewitness Accounts
 | publisher = Simon & Schuster
 | year = 2003
 | location = New York
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Yqo44On1tVAC&pg=PA404&lpg=PA404&dq=lm+lifeboat&source=bl&ots=xZpCZ1zZB9&sig=_O3R2Ew_cd9OK93IyH1Z378HN5U&hl=en&sa=X&ei=dAdlVM_TF4uYyAS0hIKwDw&ved=0CC0Q6AEwBQ#v=onepage&q=lm%20lifeboat&f=false
 | isbn = 0-7432-4547-4
 | jfm = }}
* {{cite book |last1=Murray |first1=Charles |authorlink1=Charles Murray (political scientist) |last2=Cox |first2=Catherine Bly |title=Apollo: The Race to the Moon |year=1989 |publisher=Simon & Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-671-61101-1 |oclc=19589707 |lccn=89006333 |ref=Murray & Cox}}
* {{cite book |last=Orloff |first=Richard W. |title=Apollo by the Numbers: A Statistical Reference |url=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4029/SP-4029.htm |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |series=The NASA History Series |origyear=First published 2000 |date=September 2004 |work=NASA History Division, Office of Policy and Plans |publisher=[[NASA]] |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=0-16-050631-X |lccn=00061677 |id=NASA SP-2000-4029 |ref=Orloff}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Papike |first1=James J. |last2=Ryder |first2=Graham |last3=Shearer |first3=Charles K. |date=January 1998 |title=Planetary Materials: Lunar Samples |journal=[[Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry]] |volume= 36 |issue=1 |pages=5-001–5-234 |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=[[Mineralogical Society of America]] |isbn=0-939950-46-4 |lccn=99474392 |issn=0275-0279 |ref=Papike et al.}}
* {{cite book |last=Sidey |first=Hugh |authorlink=Hugh Sidey |title=John F. Kennedy, President |year =1963 |publisher=Atheneum |edition=1st |location=New York |url=https://archive.org/details/johnfkennedypres000540mbp |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |lccn=63007800 |ref=Sidey}}
* {{Citation |last=Townsend |first=Neil A. |date=March 1973 |title=Apollo Experience Report: Launch Escape Propulsion Subsystem |publisher=NASA |place=Washington, D.C. |id=NASA TN D-7083 |url=http://klabs.org/history/apollo_experience_reports/tn-d7083_apollo_launch_escape_propulsion.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=September 12, 2012 |ref=Townsend}}
* {{cite book |last=Wilford |first=John Noble |authorlink=John Noble Wilford |title=We Reach the Moon: The New York Times Story of Man's Greatest Adventure |year=1969 |publisher=Bantam Paperbacks |location=New York |oclc=29123 |ref=Wilford}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|45em}}
* {{PDFlink|[http://www.hq.nasa.gov/alsj/APSR-JSC-09423.pdf ''Apollo Program Summary Report'']|46.3&nbsp;MB}} NASA Report JSC-09423, April 1975
* {{cite book |last=Collins |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Collins (astronaut) |others=Foreword by [[Charles Lindbergh]] |title=Carrying the Fire: An Astronaut's Journeys |origyear=Originally published 1974; New York: [[Farrar, Straus and Giroux]] |year=2001 |publisher=Cooper Square Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8154-1028-7 |lccn=2001017080 |ref=Collins}} Astronaut Mike Collins autobiography of his experiences as an astronaut, including his flight aboard Apollo 11.
* {{cite book |last=Cooper |first=Henry S.F., Jr. |title=Thirteen: The Apollo Flight That Failed |origyear=Originally published 1972; New York: Dial Press |year=1995 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |location=Baltimore |isbn=0-8018-5097-5 |oclc=31375285 |lccn=94039726 |ref=Cooper}} Although this book focuses on Apollo 13, it provides a wealth of background information on Apollo technology and procedures.
* {{cite book |last1=French |first1=Francis |authorlink1=Francis French |last2=Burgess |first2=Colin |authorlink2=Colin Burgess (author) |others=Foreword by [[Walter Cunningham]] |title=[[In the Shadow of the Moon (book)|In the Shadow of the Moon]]: A Challenging Journey to Tranquility, 1965–1969 |year=2007 |publisher=University of Nebraska Press |location=Lincoln |isbn=978-0-8032-1128-5 |oclc=182559769 |lccn=2006103047 |ref=French & Burgess}} History of the Apollo program from Apollos 1–11, including many interviews with the Apollo astronauts.
* {{cite book |last=Kranz |first=Gene |authorlink=Gene Kranz |title=Failure is Not an Option: Mission Control from Mercury to Apollo 13 and Beyond |year=2000 |publisher=Simon & Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-7432-0079-9 |oclc=43590801 |lccn=00027720 |ref=Kranz}} Factual, from the standpoint of a flight controller during the [[Project Mercury|Mercury]], [[Project Gemini|Gemini]], and Apollo space programs.
* {{cite book |last1=Lovell |first1=Jim |authorlink1=Jim Lovell |last2=Kluger |first2=Jeffrey |authorlink2=Jeffrey Kluger |title=[[Lost Moon|Apollo 13]] |origyear=Previously published 1994 as ''[[Lost Moon]]'' |year=2000 |publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|Houghton Mifflin Company]] |location=Boston |isbn=0-618-05665-3 |oclc=43118301 |lccn=99089647 |ref=Lovell & Kluger}} Details the flight of Apollo 13.
* {{cite book |last1=Pellegrino |first1=Charles R. |authorlink1=Charles R. Pellegrino |last2=Stoff |first2=Joshua |title=Chariots for Apollo: The Untold Story Behind the Race to the Moon |year=1999 |publisher=Avon Books |location=New York |isbn=0-380-80261-9 |oclc=41579174 |ref=Pellegrino & Stoff}} Tells [[Grumman]]'s story of building the Lunar Modules.
* {{Cite book |last1=Scott |first1=David |authorlink1=David Scott |last2=Leonov |first2=Alexei |authorlink2=Alexei Leonov |last3=Toomey |first3=Christine |others=Foreword by [[Neil Armstrong]]; introduction by [[Tom Hanks]] |title=Two Sides of the Moon: Our Story of the Cold War Space Race |edition=1st U.S. |year=2004 |publisher=[[Thomas Dunne Books]] |location=New York |isbn=0-312-30865-5 |oclc=56587777 |lccn=2004059381 |ref=Scott & Leonov}}
* {{cite book |last=Seamans |first=Robert C., Jr. |title=Project Apollo: The Tough Decisions |series=Monographs in Aerospace History Number 37 |year=2005 |publisher=NASA |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=0-16-074954-9 |oclc=64271009 |lccn=2005003682 |id=NASA SP-4537 |ref=Seamans}} History of the manned space program from September 1, 1960, to January 5, 1968.
* {{cite book |last1=Slayton |first1=Donald K. |authorlink1=Deke Slayton |last2=Cassutt |first2=Michael |authorlink2=Michael Cassutt |title=Deke!: An Autobiography |year=1995 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |location=New York |isbn=0-312-85918-X |ref=Slayton & Cassutt}} Account of Deke Slayton's life as an astronaut and of his work as chief of the astronaut office, including selection of Apollo crews.
* {{PDFlink|[http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19690022643_1969022643.pdf ''The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology''. Volume 1:]|131.2&nbsp;MB}} From origin to November 7, 1962
* {{PDFlink|[http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19740004394_1974004394.pdf ''The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology''. Volume 2:]|13.4&nbsp;MB}} November 8, 1962 – September 30, 1964
* {{PDFlink|[http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19760014180_1976014180.pdf ''The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology''. Volume 3:]|57.7&nbsp;MB}} October 1, 1964 – January 20, 1966
* {{PDFlink|[http://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19800011953_1980011953.pdf ''The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology''. Volume 4:]|24.2&nbsp;MB}} January 21, 1966 – July 13, 1974
* {{cite book |last=Wilhelms |first=Don E. |authorlink=Donald Wilhelms |title=To a Rocky Moon: A Geologist's History of Lunar Exploration |year=1993 |publisher=University of Arizona Press |location=Tucson |isbn=0-8165-1065-2 |oclc=26720457 |lccn=92033228 |ref=Wilhelms}} The history of lunar exploration from a geologist's point of view.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Apollo missions}}
{{Wikinewscat}}
{{Library resources box|onlinebooks=yes}}
* [http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/history/apollo/index.html Apollo program history] at NASA's Human Space Flight (HSF) website
* [http://history.nasa.gov/apollo.html The Apollo Program] at the NASA History Program Office
* [http://www.sti.nasa.gov/tto/apollo.htm Apollo Spinoffs] at the NASA Spinoff website
* [http://airandspace.si.edu/explore-and-learn/topics/apollo/ The Apollo Program] at the [[National Air and Space Museum]]
* [http://www.nasa.gov/externalflash/apollo11/index1.html Apollo 35th Anniversary Interactive Feature] at NASA (in [[Adobe Flash|Flash]])
* [http://www.lpi.usra.edu/expmoon/apollo_landings.html Lunar Mission Timeline] at the [[Lunar and Planetary Institute]]

'''NASA reports'''
* [http://history.nasa.gov/apsr/apsr.htm Apollo Program Summary Report] (PDF), NASA, JSC-09423, April 1975
* [http://history.nasa.gov/series95.html NASA History Series Publications]
* [http://history.nasa.gov/diagrams/apollo.html Project Apollo Drawings and Technical Diagrams] at the NASA History Program Office
* [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/alsj/frame.html The Apollo Lunar Surface Journal] edited by Eric M. Jones and Ken Glover
* [http://history.nasa.gov/afj/ The Apollo Flight Journal] by W. David Woods, ''et al''.

'''Multimedia'''
* [http://apollo.sese.asu.edu/ Apollo Image Archive] at [[Arizona State University]]
* [http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/images/apollo/index.html Apollo Gallery] at NASA's Human Space Flight (includes videos/animations)
* [http://whitehousetapes.net/clips/1962_1121_apollo/ Audio recording and transcript of President John F. Kennedy, NASA administrator James Webb, ''et al.'', discussing the Apollo agenda] (White House Cabinet Room, November 21, 1962)
* [http://www.apolloarchive.com/ The Project Apollo Archive] by Kipp Teague is a large repository of Apollo images, videos, and audio recordings
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/projectapolloarchive/  The Project Apollo Archive on Flickr]
* [http://www.lpi.usra.edu/resources/apollo/ Apollo Image Atlas] – almost 25,000 lunar images, Lunar and Planetary Institute
* {{Internet Archive short film|id=gov.ntis.ava03129vnb1|name="Time of Apollo (1975)"}}	
* {{YouTube| GNJpoP642wc | "The Journeys of Apollo - NASA Documentary" }}

{{Apollo program}}
{{People who have walked on the Moon}}
{{US manned space programs|before=[[Project Gemini|Gemini]]|after=[[Skylab]]}}
{{NASA planetary exploration programs}}
{{NASA navbox|state=collapsed}}
{{The Moon}}
{{Lunar rovers}}
{{Moon spacecraft}}
{{Spaceflight}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Use American English|date=January 2014}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Apollo Program}}
[[Category:Human spaceflight programs]]
[[Category:Apollo program| ]]
[[Category:Exploration of the Moon]]
[[Category:Engineering projects]]
[[Category:1960s in the United States]]
[[Category:1970s in the United States]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
</text>
</page>
<page>
<title>Neil Armstrong</title>
<text>
{{Other people}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox astronaut
| name = Neil Armstrong
| othername=Neil Alden Armstrong
| image = Neil Armstrong pose.jpg
| alt = Photo of Neil Armstrong, July 1969, in space suit with the helmet off
| caption = Armstrong in July 1969<br />[[File:Neil Armstrong Signature.svg|100px]]
| type =  [[Man in Space Soonest|USAF]] / [[NASA]] [[astronaut]]
| nationality = American
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1930|08|5}}
| birth_place = {{nowrap|[[Wapakoneta, Ohio|Wapakoneta]], [[Ohio]], [[United States|U.S.]]}}
| death_date = {{Death date and age|2012|08|25|1930|08|05|mf=yes}}
| death_place = {{nowrap|[[Cincinnati]], [[Ohio]], U.S.}}
| previous_occupation = [[Naval aviation|Naval aviator]], [[test pilot]]
| alma_mater = [[Purdue University]], B.S. 1955<br>[[University of Southern California]], M.S. 1970
| rank = 
| selection = [[List of astronauts by year of selection#1958|1958 USAF Man In Space Soonest]]<br />[[List of astronauts by year of selection#1960|1960 USAF Dyna-Soar]]<br>[[NASA Astronaut Group 2|1962 NASA Group 2]]
| eva1 = 1
| eva2 = 2 hours 31 minutes
| time = 8 days, 14 hours, 12 minutes, and 30 seconds
| mission = [[Gemini 8]], [[Apollo 11]]
| insignia = [[File:Ge08Patch orig.png|40px]] [[File:Apollo 11 insignia.png|40px]]
| awards = [[File:En-NavAstro.jpg|55px|link=astronaut badge|United States Naval Aviator/Astronaut Insignia]] [[File:Nasa civilian astronaut.jpg|55px|link=astronaut badge|NASA Civilian Astronaut Wings]] {{Presidential Medal of Freedom}} {{CS Medal of Honor}}
}}
'''Neil Alden Armstrong''' (August 5, 1930 – August 25, 2012) was an American [[astronaut]] and the [[Apollo 11#Lunar surface operations|first person to walk on the Moon]]. He was also an [[aerospace engineering|aerospace engineer]], [[United States Naval Aviator|naval aviator]], [[test pilot]], and [[university professor]]. Before becoming an astronaut, Armstrong was an [[Officer (armed forces)|officer]] in the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] and served in the [[Korean War]]. After the war, he earned his bachelor's degree at [[Purdue University]] and served as a test pilot at the [[National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics]] (NACA) [[Dryden Flight Research Center|High-Speed Flight Station]], where he logged over 900 flights. He later completed graduate studies at the [[University of Southern California]].

A participant in the [[United States Air Force|U.S. Air Force]]'s [[Man in Space Soonest]] and [[Boeing X-20 Dyna-Soar|X-20 Dyna-Soar]] [[human spaceflight]] programs, Armstrong joined the [[NASA Astronaut Corps]] in 1962. He made his first space flight as command pilot of [[Gemini 8]] in March 1966, becoming NASA's first civilian astronaut to fly in space. He performed the first [[Spacecraft docking and berthing mechanisms|docking]] of two [[spacecraft]], with pilot [[David Scott]].<ref name="Gemini 1965–1966">{{cite web |title=Gemini 1965–1966 |publisher=Spacecollection.info |url=http://www.spacecollection.info/us_gemini/gemini.html |accessdate=May 14, 2011}}</ref> This mission was aborted after Armstrong used some of his reentry control fuel to prevent a dangerous spin caused by a stuck thruster, in the first in-flight space emergency.

Armstrong's second and last spaceflight was as commander of [[Apollo 11]], the first manned [[Moon landing]] mission in July 1969. Armstrong and [[Apollo Lunar Module|Lunar Module]] pilot [[Buzz Aldrin]] descended to the lunar surface and spent two and a half hours outside the spacecraft, while [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]] remained in lunar orbit in the [[Apollo Command/Service Module|Command/Service Module]]. Along with Collins and Aldrin, Armstrong was awarded the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]] by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Richard Nixon]]. President [[Jimmy Carter]] presented Armstrong the [[Congressional Space Medal of Honor]] in 1978. Armstrong and his former crewmates received the [[Congressional Gold Medal]] in 2009.

Armstrong died in [[Cincinnati]], [[Ohio]], on August 25, 2012, at the age of 82, after complications from [[coronary artery bypass surgery]].<ref>{{cite journal |title=Neil Armstrong's Death—a Medical Perspective |work=Scientific American |url=http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/molecules-to-medicine/2012/09/03/neil-armstrongs-deatha-medical-perspective/ |accessdate=December 30, 2012}}</ref><ref name=CNN-Armstrong-Death>{{cite news |title=Space legend Neil Armstrong dies |work=CNN |url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/08/25/us/neil-armstrong-obit/index.html |accessdate=December 30, 2012 }}</ref>

==Early years==
Neil Armstrong was born on August 5, 1930, to Stephen Koenig Armstrong and Viola Louise Engel in [[Auglaize County, Ohio|Auglaize County]], near [[Wapakoneta, Ohio]]<!-- Was Engel her surname before marriage, during marriage, or both? -->.<ref>{{cite web |title=History of Wapakoneta (or is it Wapaghkonnetta?) |work=City of Wapakoneta, Ohio |url=http://www.wapakoneta.net/history |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref><ref name=Hansen49>Hansen 2005, pp. 49–50.</ref> He was of [[Scottish American|Scottish]], [[Irish American|Irish]], and [[German American|German]] ancestry,<ref>{{cite web |first=Patrick |last=Counihan |title=Distant Irish relatives mourn moonwalker Neil Armstrong |date=August 27, 2012 |url=http://www.irishcentral.com/news/distant-irish-relatives-mourn-moonwalker-neil-armstrong-167530445-237525201.html# |accessdate=March 26, 2015}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |first=Angelique |last=Chrisafis |title=Ulster Scots' Eagle fails to take off |date=May 28, 2004 |url=http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2004/may/28/arts.northernireland |accessdate=March 26, 2015}}</ref> and had two younger siblings, June and Dean. Stephen Armstrong worked as an [[audit]]or<ref>{{Cite news |title=Neil Armstrong grants rare interview to accountants organization |work=CBC News |date=May 24, 2012 |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/story/2012/05/24/f-neil-armstrong-interview-accountants.html |accessdate=May 24, 2012}}</ref> for the Ohio state government; the family moved around the state repeatedly after Armstrong's birth, living in 20 towns. Neil's love for flying grew during this time, having gotten off to an early start when his father took his two-year-old son to the [[National Air Races|Cleveland Air Races]]. When he was five, he experienced his first airplane flight in [[Warren, Ohio]] on July 20, 1936 when he and his father took a ride in a [[Ford Trimotor]], also known as the "Tin Goose".<ref>{{cite web |title=Project Apollo: Astronaut Biographies |work=NASA |url=http://history.nasa.gov/ap11ann/astrobios.htm#Armstrong |accessdate=May 12, 2011}}</ref>

His father's last move was in 1944, back to Neil's birthplace, Wapakoneta, in Auglaize County. Armstrong attended [[Blume High School]] and took flying lessons at the grassy Wapakoneta airfield.<ref name=Hansen49/> He earned a student flight certificate on his 16th birthday, then [[First solo flight|soloed]] later in August; all before he had a driver's license.<ref>{{cite book |last=Koestler-Grack |first=Rachel A. |title=Neil Armstrong |page=14 |publisher=Gareth Stevens |date=2009 |isbn=1-4339-2147-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BnYzJKdNOM0C&pg=PA14 }}</ref> Armstrong was active in the [[Scouting in Ohio|Boy Scouts]] and earned the rank of [[Eagle Scout (Boy Scouts of America)|Eagle Scout]]. As an adult, he was recognized by the [[Boy Scouts of America]] with its [[Distinguished Eagle Scout Award]] and [[Silver Buffalo Award]].<ref name="desalista">{{cite web |title=Distinguished Eagle Scouts |publisher=Boy Scouts of America |url=http://www.scouting.org/filestore/pdf/02-529.pdf |accessdate=November 4, 2010}}</ref> On July 18, 1969, while flying towards the [[Moon]] inside the ''Columbia'', Armstrong greeted the Scouts: "I'd like to say hello to all my fellow Scouts and Scouters at [[Farragut State Park]] in [[Idaho]] having a [[National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)|National Jamboree]] there this week; and Apollo&nbsp;11 would like to send them best wishes".  Houston replied: "Thank you, Apollo&nbsp;11. I'm sure that, if they didn't hear that, they'll get the word through the news. Certainly appreciate that."<ref>{{cite web |title=Apollo 11 - Day 3, part 2: Entering Eagle - Transcript |publisher=NASA |date=April 11, 2010 |url=http://history.nasa.gov/ap11fj/09day3-entering-eagle.htm |accessdate=February 10, 2011 }}</ref> Among the very few personal items that Neil Armstrong carried with him to the Moon and back was a World Scout Badge.<ref>{{cite web |title=World Scouting salutes Neil Armstrong |publisher=World Organization of the Scout Movement |url=http://oldsite.scout.org/en/information_events/news/world_scouting_salutes_neil_armstrong|accessdate=July 27, 2015}}</ref>

In 1947, at age 17, Armstrong began studying [[Aerospace engineering|aeronautical engineering]] at [[Purdue University]]. He was the second person in his family to attend college. He was also accepted to the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] (MIT). The only engineer he knew (who had attended MIT) dissuaded him from attending, telling Armstrong that it was not necessary to go all the way to [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], for a good education.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 55–56.</ref>

His college tuition was paid for under the [[James L. Holloway, Jr.#Holloway Plan|Holloway Plan]]. Successful applicants committed to two years of study, followed by two years of flight training and one year of service in the U.S. Navy as an aviator, then completion of the final two years of their bachelor's degree. Candidates had to promise to not marry until graduation, signed the "Aviation Guarantee" to serve on Active Duty for at least four years, and would not receive a promotion to Ensign until two years after they received their Midshipman's warrant.

==Navy service==
Armstrong's call-up from the Navy arrived on January 26, 1949, requiring him to report to [[Naval Air Station Pensacola]] for flight training at age 18. This lasted almost 18 months, during which he qualified for [[Aircraft carrier|carrier]] landing aboard {{USS|Cabot|CVL-28|6}} and {{USS|Wright|CVL-49|6}}. On August 16, 1950, two weeks after his 20th birthday, Armstrong was informed by letter that he was a fully qualified [[United States Naval Aviator|Naval Aviator]].<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 68–78.</ref><!--all good-->

His first assignment was to Fleet Aircraft Service Squadron&nbsp;7 at [[Naval Air Station North Island|NAS San Diego]] (now known as NAS North Island). Two months later he was assigned to [[VF-51|Fighter Squadron 51]] (VF-51), an all-jet squadron, and made his first flight in a jet, an [[Grumman F9F Panther|F9F-2B Panther]], on January 5, 1951. In June, he made his first jet carrier landing on {{USS|Essex|CV-9|6}} and was promoted the same week from [[Midshipman]] to [[Ensign (rank)|Ensign]]. By the end of the month, ''Essex'' had set sail with VF-51 aboard, bound for Korea, where its VF-51 would act as [[ground-attack aircraft]].<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 79–85.</ref><!--all good-->

[[File:F9F-2 Panthers VF-51 over Korea 1951.jpg|thumb|left|F9F-2 Panthers over Korea, with Armstrong piloting S-116 (left).]]
Armstrong first saw action in the [[Korean War]] on August 29, 1951, as an escort for a photo [[reconnaissance]] plane over [[Kimchaek|Songjin]].<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 90.</ref> Five days later on September 3, he flew armed reconnaissance over the primary transportation and storage facilities south of the village of Majon-ni, west of [[Wonsan]]. While making a low bombing run at about {{convert|350|mph|-1|abbr=on}}, Armstrong's F9F Panther was hit by [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft fire]]. While trying to regain control, he collided with a pole at a height of about {{convert|20|ft|0}}, which sliced off about three feet (1 m) of the Panther's right wing.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 92–93.</ref> Armstrong flew the plane back to friendly territory, but due to the loss of the [[aileron]], [[Ejection seat|ejection]] was his only safe option. He planned to eject over water and await rescue by Navy helicopters, and therefore flew to an airfield near [[Pohang]], but his ejection seat was blown back over land.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 95.</ref> A jeep driven by a roommate from flight school picked Armstrong up; it is unknown what happened to the wreckage of No. 125122 F9F-2.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 96.</ref>

Armstrong flew 78 missions over Korea for a total of 121 hours in the air, most of which were in January 1952. He received the [[Air Medal]] for 20 combat missions, a [[5/16 inch star|Gold Star]] for the next 20, and the [[Korean Service Medal]] and Engagement Star.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 112.</ref> Armstrong left the Navy at age 22 on August 23, 1952, and became a [[Lieutenant (junior grade)|Lieutenant, Junior Grade]], in the [[United States Navy Reserve|U.S. Naval Reserve]]. He remained in the reserve for eight years, then resigned his commission on October 21, 1960.<ref name="Hansen, p. 118">Hansen 2005, p. 118.</ref><!--all good-->

==College years==
After his service with the Navy, Armstrong returned to Purdue, where his best grades came in the four semesters following his return from Korea. He had previously earned average marks, but his final [[Grade (education)|GPA]] was 4.8 out of 6.0.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 62.</ref> He pledged the [[Phi Delta Theta]] [[Fraternities and sororities in North America|fraternity]]<ref>{{cite web |title=The Beginning |publisher=Phi Delta Theta international site |url=http://www.phideltatheta.org/index.php?option=com_content&task=view&id=15&Itemid=118 |accessdate=May 3, 2011}}</ref> after his return and he wrote and co-directed its musical as part of the all-student revue; he was also a member of [[Kappa Kappa Psi]]<ref>{{cite web |title=Prominent Members of Kappa Kappa Psi |work=Kappa Kappa Psi |url=http://www.kkpsi.org/prominentmembers.asp |accessdate=May 3, 2011}}</ref> National Honorary Band Fraternity and a [[baritone horn|baritone]] player in the [[Purdue All-American Marching Band]]. Armstrong graduated in 1955 with a [[Bachelor of Science]] degree in [[Aeronautical Engineering]].<ref name="Hansen, p. 118"/>

After returning to Purdue, he met Janet Elizabeth Shearon, who was majoring in [[Family and consumer science|home economics]]. According to the couple, there was no real courtship, and neither could remember the exact circumstances of their engagement, except that it occurred while Armstrong was working at the NACA's [[Glenn Research Center|Lewis Flight Propulsion Laboratory]]. They were married on January 28, 1956, at the Congregational Church in [[Wilmette, Illinois]]. When he moved to [[Edwards Air Force Base]], he lived in the bachelor quarters of the base, while Janet lived in the [[Westwood, Los Angeles|Westwood]] district of [[Los Angeles]]. After one semester, they moved into a house in [[Antelope Valley]]. Janet never finished her degree, a fact she regretted later in life.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 124–127.</ref>

The couple had three children together: Eric, Karen, and Mark.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 128.</ref> In June 1961, daughter Karen was diagnosed with a [[malignant]] [[tumor]] of the middle part of her [[Brainstem|brain stem]]; X-ray treatment slowed its growth, but her health deteriorated to the point where she could no longer walk or talk. Two-year-old Karen died of [[pneumonia]], related to her weakened health, on January 28, 1962.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 161–164.</ref><!--all good-->

Armstrong later completed his [[Master of Science]] degree in [[Aerospace Engineering]] at the [[University of Southern California]] in 1970.<ref name=NASA-bio>{{cite web |title=Biographical Data: Neil A. Armstrong |date=August 2012 |publisher=NASA |url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/armstrong-na.html }}</ref>  He would eventually be awarded [[honorary doctorate]]s by several universities.<ref name=glenn-bio>{{cite web |title=Biography: Neil A. Armstrong |publisher=NASA ([[Glenn Research Center|John H. Glenn Research Center]]) |date=March 2008|url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/glenn/about/bios/neilabio.html |accessdate=May 16, 2011}}</ref>

==Test pilot==
[[File:Neil Armstrong 1956 portrait.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=A black-and-white photo of Armstrong|Armstrong, 26, <!--taken November 20, 1956,--> as a test pilot at the [[National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics|NACA]] High-Speed Flight Station at [[Edwards Air Force Base|Edwards AFB]], California.]]
Following his graduation from Purdue, Armstrong decided to become an experimental research test pilot. He applied at the [[National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics]] (NACA) High-Speed Flight Station at  [[Edwards Air Force Base]]. Although the committee had no open positions, it forwarded his application to the [[Glenn Research Center|Lewis Flight Propulsion Laboratory]] in [[Cleveland]], where Armstrong began working in March 1955.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 119–120.</ref><!--All good--> Armstrong's stint at Cleveland lasted a couple of months, and by July 1955 he had returned to Edwards AFB for a new job.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 122.</ref>

On his first day at Edwards, Armstrong was tasked his first assignments, which were to pilot [[chase plane]]s during releases of experimental aircraft from modified bombers. He also flew the modified bombers, and on one of these missions had his first flight incident at Edwards. On March 22, 1956, Armstrong was in a [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress]],<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 134.</ref><!--All good--> which was to air-drop a [[Douglas D-558-2 Skyrocket]]. He sat in the right-hand pilot seat while the left-hand seat commander, Stan Butchart, flew the B-29.<ref name="Early NASA Years">{{cite web |last=Creech |first=Gray |title=From the Mojave to the Moon: Neil Armstrong's Early NASA Years |publisher=NASA |date=July 15, 2004 |url=http://www.nasa.gov/missions/research/neil_armstrong.html |accessdate=May 17, 2011}}</ref>

As they ascended to {{convert|30000|ft|km}}, the number-four engine stopped and the [[Propeller (aircraft)|propeller]] began [[wikt:windmill|windmilling]] (rotating freely) in the airstream. Hitting the switch that would stop the propeller's spinning, Butchart found the propeller slowed but then started spinning again, this time even faster than the other engines; if it spun too fast, it would break apart. Their aircraft needed to hold an airspeed of {{convert|210|mph|0|abbr=on}} to launch its Skyrocket payload, and the B-29 could not land with the Skyrocket attached to its belly. Armstrong and Butchart brought the aircraft into a nose-down alignment to increase speed, then launched the Skyrocket. At the instant of launch, the number-four engine propeller disintegrated. Pieces of it damaged the number-three engine and hit the number-two engine. Butchart and Armstrong were forced to shut down the number-three engine, due to damage, and the number-one engine, due to the [[torque]] it created. They made a slow, circling descent from {{convert|30000|ft|m|-3|abbr=on}} using only the number-two engine, and landed safely.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 134–136.</ref><!--All good-->

As a research pilot, Armstrong served as project pilot on the [[North American F-100 Super Sabre|F-100 Super Sabre]] A and C variants, [[McDonnell F-101 Voodoo|F-101 Voodoo]], and the [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]] [[Lockheed F-104 Starfighter|F-104A Starfighter]]. He also flew the [[Bell X-1]]B, [[Bell X-5]], [[North American X-15]], [[Republic F-105 Thunderchief|F-105 Thunderchief]], [[Convair F-106 Delta Dart|F-106 Delta Dart]], [[Boeing B-47 Stratojet|B-47 Stratojet]], [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135 Stratotanker]], and was one of eight elite pilots involved in the [[NASA Paresev|paraglider research vehicle program (Paresev)]].

Armstrong's first flight in a rocket plane was on August 15, 1957, in the [[Bell X-1]]B, to an altitude of {{convert|11.4|mi|km|1}}. The [[Landing gear|nose landing gear]] broke on landing, which had happened on about a dozen previous flights of the Bell X-1B due to the aircraft's design.<ref name="Hansen, p. 145">Hansen 2005, p. 145.</ref><!--All good--> He later flew the [[North American X-15]] seven times; his penultimate flight reached an altitude of {{Convert|207,500|ft|km}}.<ref name="Hansen, p. 145"/>

Armstrong was involved in several incidents that went down in Edwards folklore and/or were chronicled in the memoirs of colleagues. The first occurred during his sixth X-15 flight on April 20, 1962, while Armstrong tested a self-adjusting control system. He flew to a height of over {{convert|207,000|ft|km}}, (the highest he flew before Gemini 8), but the aircraft nose was held up too long during descent and the X-15 bounced off the atmosphere back up to {{convert|140,000|ft|km|0}}. At that altitude, the air is so thin that aerodynamic surfaces have almost no effect. He flew past the landing field at [[Mach number|Mach]]&nbsp;3 ({{convert|2000|mph|-2|abbr=on}}) at over {{convert|100000|ft|km}} in altitude, and ended up {{convert|40|mi|km}} south of Edwards. After sufficient descent, he turned back toward the landing area, and barely managed to land without striking [[Yucca brevifolia|Joshua trees]] at the south end. It was the longest X-15 flight in both time and distance from the ground track.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 178–184.</ref><!--All good-->

Four days later, Armstrong was involved in a second incident, when he flew for the only time with [[Chuck Yeager]]. Their job, flying a [[Lockheed T-33 Shooting Star]], was to evaluate Smith Ranch Dry Lake for use as an emergency landing site for the X-15. In his autobiography, Yeager wrote that he knew the lake bed was unsuitable for landings after recent rains, but Armstrong insisted on flying out anyway. As they attempted a [[Touch-and-go landing|touch-and-go]], the wheels became stuck and they had to wait for rescue. Armstrong tells a different version of events, where Yeager never tried to talk him out of it and they made a first successful landing on the east side of the lake. Then Yeager told him to try again, this time a bit slower. On the second landing, they became stuck and according to Armstrong, Yeager was in fits of laughter.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 184–189.</ref><!--All good-->

[[File:Pilot Neil Armstrong and X-15 -1 - GPN-2000-000121.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A black-and-white photo of Armstrong smiling outside of an X-15|Armstrong, 30, and [[North American X-15|X-15]] #1<br>after a research flight in 1960.]]
Many of the test pilots at Edwards praised Armstrong's engineering ability. [[Milton Orville Thompson|Milt Thompson]] said he was "the most technically capable of the early X-15 pilots." [[Bill Dana (pilot)|Bill Dana]] said Armstrong "had a mind that absorbed things like a sponge." Those who flew for the Air Force tended to have a different opinion, especially people like Yeager and [[William J. Knight|Pete Knight]], who did not have engineering degrees. Knight said that pilot-engineers flew in a way that was "more mechanical than it is flying," and gave this as the reason why some pilot-engineers got into trouble: their flying skills did not come naturally.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 138–139.</ref><!--All good-->

A few weeks later on May 21, 1962, Armstrong was involved in what Edwards' folklore called the "Nellis Affair." He was sent in a [[Lockheed F-104 Starfighter]] to inspect [[Delamar Dry Lake]] in southern [[Nevada]], again for emergency landings. He misjudged his altitude, and also did not realize that the landing gear had not fully extended. As he touched down, the landing gear began to retract; Armstrong applied full power to abort the landing, but the ventral fin and landing gear door struck the ground, damaging the radio and releasing [[hydraulic fluid]]. Without radio communication, Armstrong flew south to [[Nellis Air Force Base]], past the control tower, and waggled his wings, the signal for a no-radio approach. The loss of hydraulic fluid caused the [[Tailhook|tail-hook]] to release, and upon landing, he caught the arresting wire attached to an anchor chain, and dragged the chain along the runway.<ref name="Hansen 2005, pp. 189–192">Hansen 2005, pp. 189–192.</ref>

It took thirty minutes to clear the runway and rig an arresting cable and Armstrong telephoned Edwards and asked for someone to collect him. Milt Thompson was sent in an F-104B, the only two-seater available, but a plane Thompson had never flown. With great difficulty, Thompson made it to Nellis, but a strong crosswind caused a hard landing and the left main tire suffered a blowout. The runway was again closed to clear it, and [[Bill Dana (pilot)|Bill Dana]] was sent to Nellis in a T-33 Shooting Star, but he almost landed long—and the Nellis base operations office decided that to avoid any further problems, it would be best to find the three NASA pilots ground transport back to Edwards.<ref name="Hansen 2005, pp. 189–192"/><!--All good-->

Armstrong made seven [[List of X-15 flights|flights in the X-15]] from November 1960 to July 1962. He reached a top altitude of {{convert|207,500|ft|km|1}} in the X-15-3,<ref name="Hansen, p. 178">Hansen 2005, p. 178.</ref> and a top speed of [[Mach number|Mach]]&nbsp;5.74 ({{convert|3989|mph|0|abbr=on}}) in the X-15-1; he left the Dryden Flight Research Center with a total of 2,400 flying hours.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 210.</ref> Over his career, he flew more than 200 different models of aircraft.<ref name=NASA-bio/>

==Astronaut career==
[[File:Neil Armstrong in Gemini G-2C training suit.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Photo|Armstrong in an early<br>[[Project Gemini|Gemini]] spacesuit]]
In 1958, Armstrong had been selected for the U.S. Air Force's [[Man In Space Soonest]] program. In November 1960, he was chosen as part of the pilot consultant group for the [[Boeing X-20 Dyna-Soar|X-20 Dyna-Soar]], a military space plane under development by Boeing for the U.S. Air Force, and on March 15, 1962, he was selected by the U.S. Air Force as one of seven pilot-engineers who would fly the space plane when it got off the design board.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 173.</ref><!--All good-->

In the months after the announcement that applications were being sought for the second group of NASA astronauts, Armstrong became more and more excited about the prospects of both the [[Apollo program]] and of investigating a new aeronautical environment. Armstrong's astronaut application arrived about a week past the June 1, 1962, deadline. Dick Day, with whom Armstrong had worked closely at Edwards, saw the late arrival of the application and slipped it into the pile before anyone noticed.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 195.</ref><!--All good--> At [[Brooks Air Force Base]] at the end of June, Armstrong underwent a medical exam that many of the applicants described as painful and at times seemingly pointless.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 195–204.</ref><!--All good-->

[[Deke Slayton]] called Armstrong on September 13, 1962, and asked whether he would be interested in joining the NASA Astronaut Corps as part of what the press dubbed "the [[NASA Astronaut Group 2|New Nine]]"; without hesitation, Armstrong said yes. The selections were kept secret until three days later, although newspaper reports had been circulating since earlier that year that he would be selected as the "first civilian astronaut."<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 201–202.</ref> Armstrong was one of two civilian pilots selected for the second group; the other was [[Elliot See]], also a former naval aviator.<ref name=USastronaut>{{cite web |title=Elliot M. See, Jr. |work=NASA |url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/see-em.html |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref> See was scheduled to command ''[[Gemini 9]]'', but died in a [[1966 NASA T-38 crash|T-38 crash in 1966]] that also took the life of crewmate [[Charles Bassett]]. Armstrong was the first American civilian in space, but the first civilian was [[Valentina Tereshkova]] of the [[Soviet Union]], nearly three years earlier. A textile worker and amateur parachutist, she was aboard [[Vostok 6]] when it launched on June 16, 1963.<ref>{{cite web |title=Valentina Vladimirovna Tereshkova (Born March 6, 1937) |publisher=Adm.yar.ru |url=http://www.yarregion.ru/eng/Pages/famous_people_Valentina_Vladimirovna_Tereshkova.aspx|accessdate=July 27, 2015}}</ref>

===Gemini program===

====''Gemini 8''====
{{Main|Gemini 8}}
[[File:GEMINI-TITAN-8 - PRELAUNCH ACTIVITY.jpg|thumb|left|Armstrong, 35, suiting up<br>for ''[[Gemini 8]]'' in March 1966]]
The crew assignments for ''Gemini&nbsp;8'' were announced on September 20, 1965, with Armstrong as Command Pilot and [[David Scott]] as Pilot. Scott was the first member of the third group of astronauts to receive a prime crew assignment. The mission launched on March 16, 1966; it was to be the most complex yet, with a rendezvous and docking with the unmanned [[Agena target vehicle]], the second American [[extra-vehicular activity]] (EVA) by Scott. In total, the mission was planned to last 75 hours and 55 orbits. After the Agena lifted off at 10&nbsp;a.m. [[Eastern Time Zone|EST]], the [[Titan II GLV|Titan II]] carrying Armstrong and Scott ignited at 11:41:02&nbsp;am EST, putting them into an orbit from where they would chase the Agena.<ref>Hansen 2005, ch. 19.</ref>

The rendezvous and first-ever docking between two spacecraft was successfully completed after 6.5 hours in orbit.<ref name="Gemini 1965–1966"/> Contact with the crew was intermittent due to the lack of tracking stations covering their entire orbits. Out of contact with the ground, the docked spacecraft began to roll, and Armstrong attempted to correct this with the [[Orbital Maneuvering System|Orbital Attitude and Maneuvering System]] (OAMS) of the Gemini spacecraft. Following the earlier advice of Mission Control, they undocked, but found that the roll increased dramatically to the point where they were turning about once per second, which meant the problem was in their Gemini's attitude control. Armstrong decided the only course of action was to engage the Reentry Control System (RCS) and turn off the OAMS. Mission rules dictated that once this system was turned on, the spacecraft would have to reenter at the next possible opportunity. It was later thought that damaged wiring made one of the thrusters become stuck in the on position.<ref>{{cite web |last=Merritt |first=Larry |title=The abbreviated flight of Gemini 8 |publisher=Boeing |url=http://bts.boeing.com/news/frontiers/archive/2006/march/i_history.html |date=March 2006 |accessdate=May 14, 2011 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110812222659/http://bts.boeing.com/news/frontiers/archive/2006/march/i_history.html |archivedate=August 12, 2011}}</ref>

[[File:Armstrong and Scott with Hatches Open - GPN-2000-001413.jpg|thumb|alt=Photo of Armstrong and Scott in the Gemini capsule, in the water. They are being assisted by some recovery crew| Recovery of ''[[Gemini 8]]'' from<br>the western Pacific Ocean;<br>Armstrong sitting to the right.]]

Throughout the astronaut office there were a few people, most notably [[Walter Cunningham]], who publicly stated that Armstrong and Scott had ignored the malfunction procedures for such an incident, and that Armstrong could have salvaged the mission if he had turned on only one of the two RCS rings, saving the other for mission objectives. These criticisms were unfounded; no malfunction procedures were written and it was possible to turn on only both RCS rings, not just one or the other. [[Gene Kranz]] wrote, "the crew reacted as they were trained, and they reacted wrong because we trained them wrong." The mission planners and controllers had failed to realize that when two spacecraft are docked together, they must be considered to be one spacecraft.<ref>Kranz, p. 174.</ref>

Armstrong himself was depressed<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 274.</ref><!--All good--> that the mission had been cut short, canceling most mission objectives and robbing Scott of his [[Extra-vehicular activity|EVA]].

====''Gemini 11''====
{{Main|Gemini 11}}
The last assignment for Armstrong in the [[Project Gemini|Gemini]] program was as the back-up Command Pilot for ''[[Gemini 11]]'', announced two days after the landing of ''Gemini 8''. Having trained for two flights, Armstrong was quite knowledgeable about the systems and was more in a teaching role<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 292–293.</ref> for the rookie backup Pilot, [[William Anders]]. The launch was on September 12, 1966,<ref>{{cite web |title=Gemini-XI |work=NASA (Kennedy Space Center) |url=http://science.ksc.nasa.gov/history/gemini/gemini-xi/gemini-xi.html |accessdate=July 24, 2010}}</ref> with [[Pete Conrad]] and [[Richard F. Gordon, Jr.|Dick Gordon]] on board, who successfully completed the mission objectives, while Armstrong served as [[Capsule communicator#Capsule Communicator (CAPCOM)|CAPCOM]].

Following the flight, President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] asked Armstrong and his wife to take part in a 24-day goodwill tour of South America.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 296–297.</ref> Also on the tour, which took in 11 countries and 14 major cities, were Dick Gordon, [[George Low]], their wives, and other government officials. In [[Paraguay]], Armstrong impressed dignitaries by greeting them in their local language, [[Guarani language|Guarani]];<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 298.</ref> in Brazil he talked about the exploits of the Brazilian-born [[Alberto Santos-Dumont]], who was regarded as having beaten the [[Wright brothers]] with the [[Early flying machines|first flying machine]] with his [[Santos-Dumont 14-bis|14-bis]].<ref>{{cite web |title=Santos Dumont In France 1906–1916 |publisher=Earlyaviators.com |url=http://www.earlyaviators.com/edumonb.htm |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref>

===Apollo program===
On January 27, 1967, the date of the ''[[Apollo 1]]'' fire, Armstrong was in Washington, D.C., with [[Gordon Cooper]], [[Richard F. Gordon, Jr.|Dick Gordon]], [[Jim Lovell]] and [[Scott Carpenter]] for the signing of the United Nations [[Outer Space Treaty]]. The astronauts chatted with the assembled dignitaries until 6:45&nbsp;p.m. when Carpenter went to the airport, and the others returned to the Georgetown Inn, where they each found messages to phone the [[Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center|Manned Spacecraft Center]]. During these telephone calls, they learned of the deaths of [[Gus Grissom]], [[Edward Higgins White|Ed White]] and [[Roger B. Chaffee|Roger Chaffee]]. Armstrong and the group spent the rest of the night drinking scotch and discussing what had happened.<ref>{{cite book |last1=Lovell |first1=Jim |authorlink1=Jim Lovell |last2=Kluger |first2=Jeffrey |authorlink2=Jeffrey Kluger |title=Apollo 13 |date=2000 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin |isbn=0-618-05665-3 |pages=24–25 }}</ref>

On April 5, 1967, the same day the ''Apollo&nbsp;1'' investigation released its report on the fire, Armstrong assembled with 17 other astronauts for a meeting with Deke Slayton. The first thing Slayton said was, "The guys who are going to fly the first lunar missions are the guys in this room."<ref>{{cite book |first1=Eugene |last1=Cernan |authorlink1=Eugene Cernan |first2=Don |last2=Davis |title=The Last Man on the Moon |date=1999 |publisher=St Martin's Griffin |location=New York |isbn=0-312-26351-1 |page=165}}</ref> According to [[Eugene Cernan]], Armstrong showed no reaction to the statement. To Armstrong it came as no surprise—the room was full of veterans of Project Gemini, the only people who could fly the lunar missions. Slayton talked about the planned missions and named Armstrong to the backup crew for ''[[Apollo 9]]'', which at that stage was planned to be a [[medium Earth orbit]] test of the [[Apollo Lunar Module|Lunar Module]]-[[Apollo Command/Service Module|Command/Service Module]] combination. After design and manufacturing delays in the Lunar Module (LM), ''Apollo&nbsp;9'' and ''Apollo&nbsp;8'' swapped crews. Based on the normal crew rotation scheme, Armstrong would command ''Apollo&nbsp;11''.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 312–313.</ref>

[[File:Apollo 11 LLRV 1.jpg|thumb|Armstrong floats to the ground after ejecting from LLRV 1.]]
To give the astronauts experience with how the LM would fly on its final landing descent, NASA commissioned [[Bell Aircraft]] to build two [[Lunar Landing Research Vehicle]]s, later augmented with three Lunar Landing Training Vehicles (LLTV). Nicknamed the "Flying Bedsteads", they simulated the Moon's one-sixth of Earth's gravity by using a [[turbofan]] engine to support the remaining five-sixths of the craft's weight. On May 6, 1968, about 100&nbsp;feet (30&nbsp;m) above the ground, Armstrong's controls started to degrade and the LLTV began banking.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 330.</ref> He ejected safely (later analysis suggested that if he had ejected half a second later, his parachute would not have opened in time). His only injury was from biting his tongue. Even though he was nearly killed, Armstrong maintained that without the LLRV and LLTV, the lunar landings would not have been successful, as they gave commanders valuable experience in the behavior of lunar landing craft.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 334.</ref><!--All good-->

====Apollo 11====
{{Main|Apollo 11}}

After Armstrong served as backup commander for ''[[Apollo 8]]'', Slayton offered him the post of commander of ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' on December 23, 1968, as ''Apollo 8'' orbited the Moon.<ref>{{harvnb|Nelson|2009|p=17}}</ref> In a meeting that was not made public until the publication of Armstrong's biography in 2005, Slayton told him that although the planned crew was Armstrong as commander, lunar module pilot Buzz Aldrin and command module pilot Michael Collins, he was offering the chance to replace Aldrin with Jim Lovell. After thinking it over for a day, Armstrong told Slayton he would stick with Aldrin, as he had no difficulty working with him and thought Lovell deserved his own command. Replacing Aldrin with Lovell would have made Lovell the Lunar Module Pilot, unofficially the lowest ranked member, and Armstrong could not justify placing Lovell, the commander of ''[[Gemini 12]]'', in the number&nbsp;3 position of the crew.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 338</ref><!--All good-->
[[File:Ap11-s69-31740.jpg|thumb|alt=Photo|The ''[[Apollo 11]]'' crew portrait. Left to right are Armstrong, [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]], and [[Buzz Aldrin]].]]

A March 1969 meeting between Slayton, George Low, [[Robert R. Gilruth|Bob Gilruth]], and [[Christopher C. Kraft, Jr.|Chris Kraft]] determined that Armstrong would be the first person on the Moon, in some part because NASA management saw Armstrong as a person who did not have a large ego.<ref name="Hansen, ch. 25.">Hansen 2005, ch. 25.</ref> A press conference held on April 14, 1969, gave the design of the LM cabin as the reason for Armstrong's being first; the hatch opened inwards and to the right, making it difficult for the lunar module pilot, on the right-hand side, to exit first. Slayton added, "Secondly, just on a pure protocol basis, I figured the commander ought to be the first guy out&nbsp;... I changed it as soon as I found they had the time line that showed that. Bob Gilruth approved my decision."<ref>Expeditions to the Moon, chapter 8, p. 160.</ref> At the time of their meeting, the four men did not know about the hatch consideration. The first knowledge of the meeting outside the small group came when Kraft wrote his 2001 autobiography.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 373.</ref>

On July 16, 1969, Armstrong received a crescent Moon carved out of [[Polystyrene|Styrofoam]] from the pad leader, [[Guenter Wendt]], who described it as a key to the Moon. In return, Armstrong gave Wendt a ticket for a "space taxi" "good between two planets".<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 407</ref>

=====Voyage to the Moon=====
During the ''Apollo 11'' launch, Armstrong's heart reached a top rate of 110 beats per minute.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 410</ref> He found the first stage to be the loudest—much noisier than the ''Gemini 8'' Titan II launch—and the Apollo CSM was relatively roomy compared to the Gemini capsule. This ability to move around was suspected to be the reason why none of the ''Apollo 11'' crew suffered from [[Space adaptation syndrome|space sickness]], while members of previous crews did. Armstrong was especially happy, as he had been prone to [[motion sickness]] as a child and could experience [[nausea]] after doing long periods of [[aerobatics]].<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 411–412.</ref>
[[File:Neil Armstrong.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Photo of Armstrong smiling in his spacesuit| Aldrin took this photo of Armstrong in the cabin after the completion of the [[Extra-vehicular activity|EVA]] on July 21, 1969.]]

The objective of ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' was to land safely rather than to touch down with precision on a particular spot. Three minutes into the lunar descent burn, Armstrong noted that craters were passing about two seconds too early, which meant the ''Eagle'' would probably touch down beyond the planned landing zone by several miles.<ref>{{cite book |last=Smith |first=Andrew |title=Moon Dust |publisher=[[Bloomsbury]] |date=2006 |isbn=0-7475-6369-1 |page=11}}</ref> As the ''Eagle'''s landing [[radar]] acquired the surface, several computer error alarms appeared. The first was a code [[Jack Garman#1202|1202]] alarm, and even with their extensive training, neither Armstrong nor Aldrin was aware of what this code meant. They promptly received word from [[capsule communicator|CAPCOM]] [[Charles Duke]] in Houston that the alarms were not a concern; the 1202 and 1201 alarms were caused by an [[Computer multitasking|executive overflow]] in the [[Apollo Guidance Computer|lunar module computer]]. As described by Buzz Aldrin in the documentary ''[[In the Shadow of the Moon (film)|In the Shadow of the Moon]]'', the overflow condition was caused by his own counter-checklist choice of leaving the docking radar on during the landing process, so the computer had to process unnecessary radar data and did not have enough time to execute all tasks, dropping lower-priority ones. Aldrin stated that he did so with the objective of facilitating re-docking with the CM should an abort become necessary, not realizing that it would cause the overflow condition.

When Armstrong noticed they were heading towards a landing area which he believed was unsafe, he took over manual control of the LM, and attempted to find an area which seemed safer, taking longer than expected, and longer than most simulations had taken.<ref>Chaikin 1995, p. 199.</ref> For this reason, there was concern from mission control that the LM was running low on fuel.<ref>Chaikin 1995, p. 198.</ref> Upon landing, Aldrin and Armstrong believed they had about 40&nbsp;seconds worth of fuel left, including the 20&nbsp;seconds worth of fuel which had to be saved in the event of an abort.<ref name="Chaikin 1995, p. 200.">Chaikin 1995, p. 200</ref> During training, Armstrong had landed the LLTV with less than 15&nbsp;seconds left on several occasions, and he was also confident the LM could survive a straight-down fall from {{convert|50|ft|m}} if needed. Analysis after the mission showed that at touchdown there were 45 to 50 seconds of propellant burn time left.<ref>{{cite book |title=Apollo 11 Mission Report |chapter=9.8.3 Gaging System Performance |date=November 1969 |publisher=NASA |url=http://history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/A11_MissionReport.pdf}}</ref>

The landing on the surface of the Moon occurred several seconds after 20:17:40 [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]] on July 20, 1969,<ref>{{cite web |last=Jones |first=Eric M. |title=The First Lunar Landing, time 109:45:40 |url=http://www.history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11.landing.html }} That was the time of probe contact; the exact time of landing is difficult to determine, because Armstrong said the landing was "very gentle" and "It was hard to tell when we were on."</ref> at which time one of three {{convert|67|in|m|adj=on}}-long probes attached to three of the Lunar Module's four legs made contact with the surface, a panel light inside the LM lit up, and Aldrin called out, "Contact light." Armstrong shut the engine off and said, "shutdown." As the LM settled onto the surface, Aldrin said, "Okay. Engine stop", then they both called out some post-landing checklist items. After a ten-second pause, Duke acknowledged the landing with, "We copy you down, ''Eagle''." Armstrong announced the landing to Mission Control and the world with the words, "Houston, [[Tranquility Base]] here. The ''Eagle'' has landed." Aldrin and Armstrong celebrated with a brisk handshake and pat on the back before quickly returning to the checklist of tasks needed to ready the lunar module for liftoff from the Moon should an emergency unfold during the first moments on the lunar surface.<ref>{{cite web |last=Jones |title=The First Lunar Landing, time 1:02:45 |url=http://www.history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11.landing.html |accessdate=November 30, 2007}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |title=Mission Transcripts, Apollo 11 AS11 PA0.pdf |url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/history/mission_trans/apollo11.htm |accessdate=November 30, 2007}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |title=Apollo 11 Mission Commentary 7-20-69 CDT 15:15 - GET 102:43 - TAPE 307/1 |url=http://history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11transcript_pao.htm }}</ref> After Armstrong had confirmed touch-down, Duke re-acknowledged, and expressed the flight controllers' anxiety: "Roger,&nbsp;... Tranquility. We copy you on the ground. You got a bunch of guys about to turn blue. We're breathing again. Thanks a lot.".''<ref name="Chaikin 1995, p. 200." />

=====First Moon walk=====
{{See also|Apollo 11#Lunar surface operations|l1=Apollo 11—Lunar surface operations}}
{{Listen|filename=Frase de Neil Armstrong.ogg|title="That's one small step for [a] man, one giant leap for mankind"|description=|format=[[Ogg]]}}

Although the official NASA flight plan called for a crew rest period before [[extra-vehicular activity]], Armstrong requested that the EVA be moved to earlier in the evening, [[Central Time Zone (North America)|Houston time]]. Once Armstrong and Aldrin were ready to go outside, [[Apollo Lunar Module|''Eagle'']] was depressurized, the hatch was opened and Armstrong made his way down the ladder first.

At the bottom of the ladder Armstrong said, "I'm going to step off the LEM now" (referring to the [[Apollo Lunar Module]]). He then turned and set his left boot on the lunar surface at 2:56 [[UTC]] July 21, 1969,<ref>{{cite book |last=Harland |first=David |title=Exploring the Moon: The Apollo Expeditions |date=1999 |isbn=1-85233-099-6}}</ref> then spoke the famous words, "That's one small step for [a] man, one giant leap for mankind."<ref name="Snopes">{{cite web |last=Mikkelson |first=Barbara |author2=David Mikkelson |title=One Small Misstep: Neil Armstrong's First Words on the Moon |date=October 2006 |work=Snopes.com |url=http://www.snopes.com/quotes/onesmall.asp |accessdate=September 19, 2009}}</ref>

[[File:Apollo 11 Landing - first steps on the moon.ogv|thumb|left|Armstrong describes<br>the lunar surface.]]

Armstrong prepared his famous [[epigram]] on his own.<ref name="Plimpton" /> In a post-flight press conference, he said that he decided on the words "just prior to leaving the LM [lunar module]."<ref>{{cite web|title=Apollo 11 Post Flight Press Conference, 16 September 1969|url=http://history.nasa.gov/ap11ann/FirstLunarLanding/ch-7.html|accessdate=24 July 2015|quote=Yes, I did think about it. It was not extemporaneous, neither was it planned. It evolved during the conduct of the flight and I decided what the words would be while we were on the lunar surface just prior to leaving the LM.}}</ref> In a 1983 interview in ''[[Esquire Magazine]]'', Armstrong explained to [[George Plimpton]]: "I always knew there was a good chance of being able to return to Earth, but I thought the chances of a successful touchdown on the moon surface were about even money—fifty–fifty&nbsp;... Most people don't realize how difficult the mission was. So it didn't seem to me there was much point in thinking of something to say if we'd have to abort landing."<ref name="Plimpton">{{cite news |last=Plimpton |first=George |title=Neil Armstrong's Famous First Words |work=Esquire |date=December 1983 |pages=113–118}}</ref>  In 2012, brother Dean Armstrong claimed that Neil had shown him a note with a draft of the line months before the launch,<ref>{{cite news|last1=Gray|first1=Richard|title=Neil Armstrong's family reveal origins of 'one small step' line|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/science/space/9770712/Neil-Armstrongs-family-reveal-origins-of-one-small-step-line.html|accessdate=24 July 2015|work=The Telegraph|date=30 December 2012}}</ref> although historian [[Andrew Chaikin]], who had interviewed the astronaut in 1988 for his book ''[[A Man on the Moon]]'', disputed that he had ever claimed coming up with the line spontaneously during the mission.<ref>{{cite web|last1=Chaikin|first1=Andrew|title=Neil Armstrong Didn't Lie About 'One Small Step' Moon Speech, Historian Says|url=http://www.space.com/19136-neil-armstrong-moon-speech-truth.html|website=Space.com|accessdate=24 July 2015|date=4 January 2013}}</ref>

Recordings of Armstrong's transmission do not evidence the indefinite article "a" before "man", though  NASA and Armstrong insisted for years that static had obscured it. Armstrong stated he would never make such a mistake, but after repeated listenings to recordings, he eventually admitted he must have dropped the "a".<ref name="Snopes" /> He later said he "would hope that history would grant me leeway for dropping the syllable and understand that it was certainly intended, even if it was not said—although it might actually have been".<ref>{{Cite book |last=Nickell |first=Duane S. |title=Guidebook for the scientific traveler: visiting astronomy and space |publisher=Rutgers University Press |date=2008 |page=175 |isbn=978-0-8135-4374-1}}</ref>

[[File:As11-40-5886.jpg|thumb|right|Armstrong on the Moon]]
It has since been claimed that acoustic analysis of the recording reveals the presence of the missing "a";<ref name="Snopes" /><ref>{{cite news |last=Goddard |first=Jacqui |title=One small word is one giant sigh of relief for Armstrong |work=[[The Times]] |location=London |date=October 2, 2006 |url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/news/world/americas/article2000645.ece |accessdate=December 31, 2012}}</ref> Peter Shann Ford, an Australia-based computer programmer, conducted a digital audio analysis and claims that Armstrong did, in fact, say "a man", but the "a" was inaudible due to the limitations of communications technology of the time.<ref name="Snopes" /><ref>{{cite web |last=Ford |first=Peter Shann |title=Electronic Evidence and Physiological Reasoning Identifying the Elusive Vowel "a" in Neil Armstrong's Statement on First Stepping onto the Lunar Surface |work=CollectSpace.com |date=September 17, 2006 |url=http://www.collectspace.com/news/news-100306a.html |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref><ref>{{cite news |title=Software Finds Missing 'a' in Armstrong's Moon Quote |work=[[CNN]].com |agency=Associated Press |date=October 1, 2006 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/09/30/moon.quote.ap/index.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061004151135/http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/09/30/moon.quote.ap/index.html |archivedate=October 4, 2006}}</ref> Ford and James R. Hansen, Armstrong's authorized biographer, presented these findings to Armstrong and NASA representatives, who conducted their own analysis.<ref>{{cite news |last=Smith |first=Veronica |title=Armstrong's Moon landing speech rewritten |work=[[Cosmos Magazine]] |agency=Agence France-Presse |date=October 2, 2006 |url=http://www.cosmosmagazine.com/node/717 |accessdate=August 29, 2007}}</ref> Armstrong found Ford's analysis "persuasive."<ref>{{cite news |last=Carreau |first=Mark |title=High-tech analysis may rewrite space history |work=[[Houston Chronicle]] |date=September 29, 2006 |url=http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/front/4225505.html |accessdate=September 30, 2006}}</ref> However, the article by Ford was published on Ford's own web site rather than in a [[Peer review|peer-reviewed]] [[scientific journal]], and linguists David Beaver and [[Mark Liberman]] wrote of their skepticism of Ford's claims on the blog [[Language Log]].<ref>
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |authorlink=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/%7Emyl/languagelog/archives/003630.html |title=One small step backwards}} (including audio)
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/%7Emyl/languagelog/archives/003632.html |title=One 75-millisecond step before a "man"}}
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/003634.html |title=Armstrong's abbreviated article: the smoking gun?}}
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/%7Emyl/languagelog/archives/003635.html |title=Armstrong's abbreviated article: notes from the expert}}
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/003639.html |title=First Korean on the moon!}}
* {{cite web |author=Language Log |url=http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/003645.html |title=What Neil Armstrong said}}
</ref> Thus, NASA's transcript continues to show the "a" in parentheses.<ref>{{cite web |last=Jones |title=One Small Step, time 109:24:23 |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/alsj/a11/a11.step.html |accessdate=December 18, 2012}}</ref>

When Armstrong made his proclamation, [[Voice of America]] was rebroadcast live via the [[BBC]] and many other stations worldwide. The estimated global audience at that moment was 450&nbsp;million listeners,<ref>{{cite book |last=Heil |first=Alan L. |title=Voice of America: A History |date=2003 |isbn=0-231-12674-3}}</ref> out of a then estimated world population of 3.631&nbsp;billion people.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.infoplease.com/year/1969.html |title=Information Please world statistics |accessdate=October 2, 2007}}</ref>

[[File:Apollo 11 first step.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A low-quality photo of a television monitor showing Armstrong on the lunar module's ladder|Armstrong, one or two minutes before taking the first step onto the Moon.]]

About 20&nbsp;minutes after the first step, Aldrin joined Armstrong on the surface and became the second human to set foot on the Moon, and the duo began their tasks of investigating how easily a person could operate on the lunar surface. Early on, they unveiled a plaque commemorating their flight, and also planted the [[Lunar Flag Assembly|flag of the United States]]. The flag used on this mission had a metal rod to hold it horizontal from its pole. Since the rod did not fully extend, and the flag was tightly folded and packed during the journey, the flag ended up with a slightly wavy appearance, as if there were a breeze.<ref>{{cite web |last=Greene |first=Nick |title=A Lunar Odyssey |work=Apollo 11 Mission |publisher=[[About.com]] |page=3 |url=http://space.about.com/cs/missions/a/apollo11_3.htm |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref> Shortly after their flag planting, President [[Richard Nixon]] spoke to them by a telephone call from his office. The President spoke for about a minute, after which Armstrong responded for about thirty seconds.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 505–506.</ref>

In the entire ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' photographic record, there are only five images of Armstrong partly shown or reflected. The mission was planned to the minute, with the majority of photographic tasks to be performed by Armstrong with a single [[Hasselblad]] camera.<ref name="AS11-40-5886">"[http://next.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11.5886.html AS11-40-5886]" ''Apollo Lunar Surface Journal''. March 2, 2010. Retrieved May 13, 2011.</ref>

After helping to set up the [[Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package|Early Apollo Scientific Experiment Package]], Armstrong went for a walk to what is now known as East Crater, {{convert|65|yd|m}} east of the LM, the greatest distance traveled from the LM on the mission. Armstrong's final task was to remind Aldrin to leave a small package of memorial items to deceased Soviet [[List of cosmonauts|cosmonauts]] [[Yuri Gagarin]] and [[Vladimir Komarov]], and ''[[Apollo 1|Apollo&nbsp;1]]'' astronauts [[Gus Grissom]], [[Edward Higgins White|Ed White]] and [[Roger B. Chaffee]].<ref>{{cite web |last1=Jones |first1=Eric M. |last2=Glover |first2=Ken |title=EASEP Deployment and Closeout |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11.clsout.html |work=Apollo Lunar Surface Journal |publisher=NASA |accessdate=March 28, 2014 |at=111:36:38 |date=1995}}</ref> The time spent on EVA during ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' was about two and a half hours, the shortest of any of the six Apollo lunar landing missions;<ref name=ApolloSum/> each of the subsequent five landings were allotted gradually longer periods for EVA activities—the crew of ''[[Apollo 17|Apollo&nbsp;17]]'', by comparison, spent over 22&nbsp;hours exploring the lunar surface.<ref name=ApolloSum>{{cite web |title=Summary Data on Apollo Missions |publisher=NASA |url=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4214/app5.html |accessdate=May 20, 2011}}</ref>

In a 2010 interview, Armstrong explained that NASA limited his Moon walk to two hours because they were unsure how the spacesuits would handle the extreme temperature of the Moon.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.space.com/10469-neil-armstrong-explains-famous-apollo-11-moonwalk.html |title=Neil Armstrong Explains His Famous Apollo 11 Moonwalk |publisher=Space.com |accessdate=October 14, 2013}}</ref>

In 2013, [[Popular Science]]'s photo gallery included a photo that Armstrong took of Aldrin but his own image is visible on Aldrin's helmet as one of the best [[astronaut selfie]]s.<ref>{{cite web |title=Best Astronaut Selfies |url=http://www.popsci.com/gallery/best-astronaut-selfies |publisher=Popular Science Magazine |accessdate=December 27, 2013}}</ref>

=====Return to Earth=====
[[File:TheShahNeilArmstrong.png|thumb|left|260px|Neil Armstrong shaking hands with [[Shah]] [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]] of [[Iran]] during [[Apollo 11]] astronauts' visit to [[Tehran]] from October 28–31, 1969]]
[[File:President Nixon welcomes the Apollo 11 astronauts aboard the U.S.S. Hornet.jpg|thumb|alt=Photo of the three crew members smiling at the [[President of the United States|President]] through the glass window of their quarantine chamber. President Nixon is standing at a microphone, also smiling.|The ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' crew and President [[Richard Nixon|Nixon]] during the post-mission quarantine period.]]

After they re-entered the LM, the hatch was closed and sealed. While preparing for the liftoff from the lunar surface, Armstrong and Aldrin discovered that, in their bulky spacesuits, they had broken the ignition switch for the ascent engine; using part of a pen, they pushed the circuit breaker in to activate the launch sequence.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 489–490</ref> The lunar module then continued to its rendezvous and docked with ''Columbia'', the command and service module. The three astronauts returned to Earth and splashed down in the [[Pacific Ocean]], to be picked up by the {{USS|Hornet|CV-12|6}}.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/nmc/spacecraftDisplay.do?id=1969-059A |title=Apollo 11 Command and Service Module (CSM) |publisher=NASA |accessdate=August 26, 2012}}</ref>

After being released from an 18-day quarantine to ensure that they had not picked up any infections or diseases from the Moon, the crew were feted across the United States and around the world as part of a 45-day "Giant Leap" tour. Armstrong then took part in [[Bob Hope]]'s 1969 [[United Service Organizations|USO]] show, primarily to Vietnam.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 580.</ref>

Later from October 29–31, 1969 he and the rest of the [[Apollo 11]] astronauts visited the city of [[Tehran]], capital of [[Iran]], where he met [[Shah]] [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]] and the rest of the nation's royal family.

In May 1970, Armstrong traveled to the Soviet Union to present a talk at the 13th annual conference of the International Committee on Space Research; after arriving in [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]] from Poland, he traveled to Moscow where he met [[Premier of the Soviet Union|Premier]] [[Alexei Kosygin]]. He was the first westerner to see the supersonic [[Tupolev Tu-144]] and was given a tour of the [[Yuri Gagarin Cosmonaut Training Center]], which Armstrong described as "a bit Victorian in nature".<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 583.</ref> At the end of the day, he was surprised to view delayed video of the launch of [[Soyuz 9]]—it had not occurred to Armstrong that the mission was taking place, even though [[Valentina Tereshkova]] had been his host and her husband, [[Andriyan Nikolayev]], was on board.<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 582–584.</ref>

==Life after Apollo==

===Teaching===
[[File:Neil Armstrong Hall of Engineering.png|thumb|left|200px|alt=Photo of a statue of Neil Armstrong sitting on a ledge. The words "Neil Armstrong Hall of Engineering" are visible on the building in the background.|Neil Armstrong Hall of Engineering<br>at [[Purdue University]]]]

Armstrong announced shortly after the ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' flight that he did not plan to fly in space again.<ref>{{cite web |last=Riley |first=Christopher |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2009/jul/09/apollo-astronauts-walking-moon |title=The Moon Walkers: Twelve Men Who Have Visited Another World |publisher=Guardian.co.uk |date=July 10, 2009 |accessdate=May 3, 2011}}</ref> He was appointed Deputy Associate Administrator for aeronautics for the Office of Advanced Research and Technology, Advanced Research Projects Agency ([[DARPA|ARPA]]), but served in this position for only a year, and resigned from it and NASA as a whole in 1971.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 584.</ref>

He accepted a teaching position in the Department of Aerospace Engineering at the [[University of Cincinnati]],<ref>{{Cite web|title = Neil Armstrong Remembered|url = http://ceas.uc.edu/about/neil-armstrong-remembered.html|website = University of Cincinnati|accessdate = 2015-11-28|language = en-US}}</ref> having decided on Cincinnati over other universities, including his ''alma mater'', Purdue, because it had a small aerospace department; he hoped that the faculty members would not be annoyed that he came straight into a professorship with only the USC master's degree.<ref name="a11 crew">{{cite web |title=Apollo 11 Crew Information |work=Apollo 11 Lunar Surface Journal |publisher=NASA |date=November 1, 2005 |url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11.crew.html |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref> He began the work while stationed at Edwards years before, and finally completed it after ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' by presenting a report on various aspects of Apollo, instead of a thesis on the simulation of hypersonic flight. The official job title he received at Cincinnati was University Professor of Aerospace Engineering. After teaching for eight years, he resigned in 1979 without explaining his reason for leaving.<ref>Hansen, pp. 590–594.</ref>

===NASA accident investigations===
Armstrong served on two spaceflight accident investigations. The first was in 1970, after ''[[Apollo 13]]'', where as part of [[Edgar Cortright]]'s panel, he produced a detailed chronology of the flight. Armstrong opposed the report's recommendation to re-design the service module's oxygen tanks, the source of the explosion.<ref>Hansen, pp. 600–603.</ref> In 1986, President Ronald Reagan appointed him to the [[Rogers Commission Report|Rogers Commission]] which investigated the Space-shuttle ''Challenger'' disaster of that year. As vice-chairman, Armstrong was in charge of the operational side of the commission.<ref>Hansen, pp. 610–616.</ref>

===Business activities===
[[File:NASALegendsUSO.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Neil Armstrong (second from right in the middle row) visits with U.S. Air Force members during a March 2010 [[USO]] stop in [[Southwest Asia]]. Seated next to him on the left are astronauts [[Jim Lovell]] and [[Gene Cernan]].]]
After Armstrong retired from NASA in 1971, he acted as a spokesman for several businesses. The first company to successfully approach him was [[Chrysler]], for whom he appeared in advertising starting in January 1979. Armstrong thought they had a strong engineering division, plus they were in financial difficulty. He later acted as a spokesman for other companies, including [[General Time Corporation]] and the [[Bankers Association of America]]. He acted as a spokesman for U.S. businesses only.<ref>Hansen, p. 595.</ref>

Along with spokesman duties, he also served on the board of directors of several companies, including Marathon Oil, Learjet, Cinergy (Cincinnati Gas & Electric Company), Taft Broadcasting, United Airlines, Eaton Corporation, AIL Systems and Thiokol.<ref>Hansen, pp. 596–598.</ref> He joined Thiokol's board after he served on the Rogers Commission; the [[Space Shuttle]] ''Challenger'' was destroyed due to a problem with the Thiokol-manufactured solid rocket boosters. He retired as chairman of the board of EDO Corporation in 2002.<ref>{{cite press release |title=EDO Corporation CEO James M. Smith to become Chairman upon retirement of Neil A. Armstrong |publisher=EDO Corporation |date=February 8, 2000 |url=http://www.edocorp.com/pr2002/02r0208.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061017094755/http://www.edocorp.com/pr2002/02r0208.htm |archivedate=October 17, 2006 |accessdate=July 1, 2006}}</ref>

===Voice actor===
In 2010, he voiced the character of Dr. Jack Morrow<ref name=IMDb>{{IMDb name|id=0035842}}</ref> in ''[[Quantum Quest: A Cassini Space Odyssey]]'', a 2010 animated educational sci-fi adventure film initiated by JPL/NASA through a grant from Jet Propulsion Lab.<ref name=J9P>{{cite web |title=Quantum Quest |publisher=jupiter9productions.com  |url=http://jupiter9productions.com/news.aspx  |accessdate=October 8, 2012}}</ref>

==Personal life==
[[File:Neil Armstrong at 50th anniversary of John Glenn's first spaceflight.jpg|thumb|250px|Armstrong speaks on the 50th anniversary of [[John Glenn]]'s first spaceflight in February 2012.]]

Unlike former astronauts who actively sought political careers after leaving NASA (such as [[United States Senate|U.S. Senators]] [[John Glenn]] [[Democratic Party (United States)|(D-OH, 1974–1999)]] and [[Harrison Schmitt]] [[Republican Party (United States)|(R-NM, 1977-1983)]]), Armstrong was approached by political groups from both parties, but declined all offers. He described his political leanings as favoring [[states' rights]] and opposing the United States acting as the "world's policeman".<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 600–601.</ref><!--All good-->

In the late 1950s, Armstrong applied at a local Methodist church to lead a Boy Scout troop. When asked for his religious affiliation, he labeled himself as a [[Deism|deist]].<ref>{{cite book |last=Hansen |first=James R. |title=First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong |date=2005 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |isbn=978-0-7432-8171-3 |page=33 |quote=It is clear that by the time Armstrong returned from Korea in 1952 he had become a type of deist, a person whose belief in God was founded on reason rather than on revelation, and on an understanding of God's natural laws rather than on the authority of any particular creed or church doctrine. While working as a test pilot in Southern California in the late 1950s, Armstrong applied at a local Methodist church to lead a Boy Scout troop. Where the form asked for his religious affiliation, Neil wrote the word "Deist."}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://sydney.edu.au/research/spacenet/news-events/20150402.shtml|title=Sydney SpaceNet Events|work=sydney.edu.au}}</ref> His mother later said that Armstrong's religious views caused her grief and distress in later life as she was more religious.<ref>{{cite book |last=Hansen |first=James R. |title=First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong |date=2005 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |isbn=978-0-7432-8171-3 |page=35 |quote=[Neil Armstrong's mother] wrote on October 27, 1969, to a Methodist minister in Iowa&nbsp;..."but when he was a senior in high school, and even more in college, he began wondering about the truth of Jesus Christ. I felt sure he was praying less&nbsp;... [Today] he is not teaching his own two fine sons about Jesus Christ. This fact causes a million swords to be pierced through my heart constantly."}}</ref> His [[First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong|official biography]] also describes him as a deist.

In 1972, Armstrong was welcomed into the town of [[Langholm]], [[Scotland]], the traditional seat of [[Clan Armstrong]]; he was made the first freeman of the [[burgh]], and happily declared the town his home.<ref>{{cite news |last=Johnston |first=Willie |title=Recalling Moon man's 'muckle' leap |work=BBC News |date=July 20, 2009 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/8158762.stm |accessdate=July 20, 2009}}</ref> The ''Justice of the Peace'' read from an unrepealed 400-year-old law that required him to hang any Armstrong found in the town.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 13.</ref><!--All good-->

In the fall of 1979, Armstrong was working at his farm near [[Lebanon, Ohio]]. As he jumped off of the back of his grain truck, his wedding ring caught in the wheel, tearing off the tip of his ring finger. He collected the severed digit and packed it in ice, and surgeons reattached it at the Jewish Hospital in Louisville, Kentucky.<ref>{{cite news |last=Sawyer |first=Kathy |title=Armstrong's Code |work=[[The Washington Post]] Magazine |date=July 11, 1999 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/space/armstrong1.htm |accessdate=August 29, 2007}}</ref> In February 1991, a year after his father had died, and nine months after the death of his mother, he suffered a mild heart attack while skiing with friends at [[Aspen, Colorado]].<ref>Hansen 2005, pp. 639–640.</ref><!--All good-->

Armstrong married his first wife Janet Shearon on January 28, 1956. Their first son Eric was born in 1957, followed by daughter, Karen, in 1959. Karen died of a brain tumor in January 1962, and the couple's second son Mark was born in 1963.<ref>{{cite news  |title=Neil Armstrong, First Man on Moon, Dies at 82 |work=A+E Networks|url=http://www.biography.com/people/neil-armstrong-9188943 |accessdate=August 28, 2012}}</ref>  Armstrong's first wife, Janet, divorced him in 1994, after 38 years of marriage.<ref>{{cite news |last=Schorn |first=Daniel |title=Being The First Man On The Moon |work=60 Minutes |publisher=CBS News |date=July 2, 2006 |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/11/03/60minutes/main1008288_page3.shtml|accessdate=January 9, 2011}}</ref> He had met his second wife, Carol Held Knight (b. 1945),<ref>{{cite news |last=Cain |first=Pat |title=Carol Held Knight: Neil Armstrong's Wife, Family Survive (Photos) |date=August 25, 2012 |url=http://www.rightentertainment.com/?p=6272 |accessdate=September 16, 2012}}</ref> in 1992 at a golf tournament, where they were seated together at the breakfast table. She said little to Armstrong, but two weeks later she received a call from him asking what she was doing—she replied she was cutting down a cherry tree; 35 minutes later Armstrong was at her house to help out. They were married on June 12, 1994, in Ohio, and then had a second ceremony, at San Ysidro Ranch, in California. He lived in [[Indian Hill, Ohio]].<ref>{{cite news |last=Johnston |first=John |last2=Amrhein |first2=Saundra |last3=Thompson |first3=Richelle |title=Neil Armstrong, Reluctant Hero |date=July 18, 1999 |work=The Cincinnati Enquirer |url=http://www.enquirer.com/editions/1999/07/18/loc_neil_armstrong_the.html}}</ref>

Armstrong is generally referred to as a "reluctant" American Hero. John Glenn, the first American to orbit Earth, recalled Armstrong's legendary humility. "He didn't feel that he should be out huckstering himself," the former Ohio senator told CNN.<ref>{{cite web |title=Birjees S Hussain: One final leap for Neil&nbsp;... |publisher=gulftoday.ae |date=August 31, 2012 |url=http://gulftoday.ae/portal/506ecc20-6263-4750-a26d-4abffc2f8428.aspx |accessdate=November 27, 2012}}</ref> "He was a humble person, and that's the way he remained after his lunar flight, as well as before." [[File:Quincy Jones, John Glenn, and Neil Armstrong during NASA's 50th anniversary gala.jpg|thumb|left|250px|alt=Photo|[[Quincy Jones]] presents platinum copies of "[[Fly Me to the Moon]]" to [[John Glenn]] (''left'') and Armstrong, September 24, 2008.]]After 1994, Armstrong refused all requests for autographs because he found that his signed items were selling for large amounts of money and that many forgeries were in circulation; any requests that were sent to him received a [[form letter]] in reply, saying that he had stopped signing. Although his no-autograph policy was well known, author [[Andrew Smith (author)|Andrew Smith]] observed people at the 2002 Reno Air Races still trying to get signatures, with one person even claiming, "If you shove something close enough in front of his face, he'll sign."<ref>Smith 2005, p. 134.</ref> He also stopped sending out congratulatory letters to new Eagle Scouts, because he believed these letters should come from people who know the Scouts personally.<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 623.</ref><!--All good-->

Use of Armstrong's name, image, and famous quote caused him problems over the years. [[MTV]] wanted to use his quote for its now-famous identity depicting the ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' landing when it launched in 1981, but he refused.<ref name=VanityFair>{{cite news |last=Anson |first=Robert Sam |title=Birth of an MTV Nation |work=Vanity Fair |date=November 2000 |location=New York  Sam |url=http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2000/11/mtv200011?printable=true&currentPage=allPittman }}</ref> Armstrong sued [[Hallmark Cards]] in 1994 after they used his name and a recording of the "one small step" quote in a Christmas ornament without permission. The lawsuit was settled out of court<ref>Hansen 2005, p. 628.</ref><!--All good--> for an undisclosed amount of money which Armstrong donated to Purdue.<ref>{{Cite news |title=Neil Armstrong, Hallmark Settle |work=Chicago Tribune |date=December 2, 1995 |url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1995-12-02/business/9512020040_1_neil-armstrong-hallmark-cards-ornament |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref>

In May 2005, Armstrong became involved in an unusual legal dispute with his barber of 20 years, Mark Sizemore.<ref>{{Cite web|title = One Small Snip Of Hair...|url = http://www.thesmokinggun.com/file/one-small-snip-hair|website = The Smoking Gun|accessdate = 2015-07-20}}</ref> After cutting Armstrong's hair, Sizemore sold some of it to a collector for $3,000 without Armstrong's knowledge or permission.<ref>{{Cite news |title=Armstrong, barber in fight over locks |work=Dayton Daily News |location=Ohio |date=June 1, 2005 |url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-11945915.html |accessdate=May 17, 2011}}</ref> Armstrong threatened legal action against Sizemore unless he returned the hair or donated the proceeds to a charity of Armstrong's choosing. Sizemore, unable to retrieve the hair, decided to donate the proceeds to the charity of Armstrong's choice.<ref>{{cite web |last=Rosenberg |first=Jennifer |title=Barber Sold Neil Armstrong's Hair |work=About.com |date=June 5, 2005 |url=http://history1900s.about.com/b/2005/06/05/barber-sold-neil-armstrongs-hair.htm |accessdate=August 29, 2007}}</ref>

Since the early 1980s, Armstrong has been the subject of a hoax saying that he converted to Islam after hearing the ''[[adhan]]'', the Muslim call to prayer, while walking on the Moon. The [[Indonesia]]n singer Suhaemi wrote a song called "''Gema Suara Adzan di Bulan''" ("The Resonant Sound of the Call to Prayer on the Moon") which described Armstrong's conversion; the song was discussed widely in various [[Jakarta]] news outlets in 1983.<ref>{{cite book |first=Glenda |last=Abramson |title=Religious Perspectives in Modern Muslim and Jewish Literatures |publisher=Psychology Press |date=2005 |isbn=0-415-35021-2 |volume=8 |page=93 |series=RoutledgeCurzon Studies in Arabic and Middle-Eastern Literatures|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8uB6G2AVhcAC&pg=PA93}}</ref> Other similar hoax stories were seen in Egypt and Malaysia. In March 1983, the [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]] responded by issuing a global message to Muslims saying that Armstrong "has not converted to Islam".<ref name=Hansen631>Hansen 2005, pp. 630–631.</ref> However, the hoax was not completely quieted; it surfaced occasionally for the next three decades. A part of the confusion stems from the similarity between Armstrong's American residence in [[Lebanon, Ohio]], and the country [[Lebanon]] which has a majority population of Muslims.<ref name=Hansen631/><ref>{{cite web |title=Neil Armstrong never converted to Islam! |date=August 25, 2012 |publisher=The Arab Digest |url=http://www.thearabdigest.com/2012/08/neil-armstrong-never-converted-to-islam.html  |accessdate=October 13, 2012}}</ref>

==Illness and death==
[[File:Neil Armstrong family memorial service (201208310014HQ).jpg|thumb|Photograph of Armstrong as a boy at his family memorial service in [[Indian Hill, Ohio]] near Cincinnati on August 31, 2012.]]
Armstrong underwent [[vascular bypass]] surgery on August 7, 2012, to relieve [[Coronary disease|blocked coronary arteries]].<ref>{{cite web |title=Armstrong, First Man on the Moon, Recovering From Heart Surgery |publisher=Reuters |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/08/08/us-usa-people-armstrong-idUSBRE8771KU20120808 |accessdate=August 8, 2012}}</ref> Although he was reportedly recovering well,<ref>{{cite news |first=Thomas |last=H. Maugh II |title=Neil Armstrong recovering well after cardiac bypass surgery |date=August 9, 2012 |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |publisher=[[Tribune Company]] |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2012/aug/09/science/la-sci-sn-armstrong-heart-surgery-20120809 |accessdate=January 5, 2014}}</ref> he developed complications in the hospital and died on August 25, in Cincinnati, Ohio.<ref name=CNN-Armstrong-Death /> After his death, Armstrong was described, in a statement released by the [[White House]], as "among the greatest of American heroes—not just of his time, but of all time".<ref>{{cite web |title=President Obama's Statement on Neil Armstrong's Death |publisher=Wall Street Journal |date=August 25, 2012|url=http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2012/08/25/president-obamas-statement-on-neil-armstrongs-death/ |accessdate=August 26, 2012 }}</ref><ref name="AP-death">{{cite news |title=Neil Armstrong, First Man on Moon, Dies at 82 |date=August 25, 2012 |work=The New York Times |agency=Associated Press |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/26/science/space/neil-armstrong-dies-first-man-on-moon.html |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref> The statement further said that Armstrong had carried the aspirations of the United States' citizens and that he had delivered "a moment of human achievement that will never be forgotten."<ref>{{cite web |title=Statement by the President on the Passing of Neil Armstrong |publisher=The White House, Office of the Press Secretary|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2012/08/25/statement-president-passing-neil-armstrong  |accessdate=August 26, 2012}}</ref>

His family released a statement describing Armstrong as a "reluctant American hero [who had] served his nation proudly, as a navy fighter pilot, test pilot, and astronaut&nbsp;... While we mourn the loss of a very good man, we also celebrate his remarkable life and hope that it serves as an example to young people around the world to work hard to make their dreams come true, to be willing to explore and push the limits, and to selflessly serve a cause greater than themselves. For those who may ask what they can do to honor Neil, we have a simple request. Honor his example of service, accomplishment and modesty, and the next time you walk outside on a clear night and see the moon smiling down at you, think of Neil Armstrong and give him a wink."<ref name="NASA FAMILY">{{cite web |title=Family Statement Regarding the Death of Neil Armstrong |date=August 25, 2012 |publisher=NASA |url=http://www.nasa.gov/home/hqnews/2012/aug/HQ_12_600_armstrong_family.html |accessdate=August 26, 2012}}</ref> This prompted many responses, including the [[Twitter]] [[hashtag]] "#WinkAtTheMoon".<ref name="NASA FAMILY TRIBUTE Twitter HashTag">{{cite web |title=Twitter #WinkAtTheMoon |date=August 25, 2012 |url=https://twitter.com/search/?q=%23WinkAtTheMoon |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref>

Armstrong's colleague on the ''Apollo 11'' mission, Buzz Aldrin, said that he was "deeply saddened by the passing. I know I am joined by millions of others in mourning the passing of a true American hero and the best pilot I ever knew. I had truly hoped that on July 20th, 2019, Neil, Mike and I would be standing together to commemorate the 50th Anniversary of our moon landing&nbsp;... Regrettably, this is not to be."<ref name="ALDRIN Twitter 25 AUGUST 2012">{{cite web |title=Buzz Aldrin on Twitter about passing of Neil Armstrong |publisher=twitter.com |date=August 25, 2012 |url=https://twitter.com/TheRealBuzz/status/239488144288927744 |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref><ref name="ALDRIN Official Statement 25 AUGUST 2012">{{cite web |title=Buzz Aldrin's Official Statement on the Passing of Neil Armstrong |date=August 25, 2012  |url=http://buzzaldrin.com/buzz-aldrins-official-statement-on-the-passing-of-neil-armstrong/ |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref> ''Apollo 11'' [[Apollo Command/Service Module|Command Module]] pilot Michael Collins said, of Armstrong, "He was the best, and I will miss him terribly."<ref name="NASA Obituary">{{cite web |title=Neil Armstrong: 1930–2012 |publisher=NASA |date=August 25, 2012 |url=http://www.nasa.gov/topics/people/features/armstrong_obit.html |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref><ref name="Collins WashPost 20120912">{{cite web |last=Collins |first=Michael  |title=The Neil Armstrong I knew—and flew with |publisher=Washington Post |date=September 12, 2012 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/michael-collins-the-neil-armstrong-i-knew--and-flew-with/2012/09/12/b3f7556c-fb7c-11e1-8adc-499661afe377_story.html |accessdate=September 13, 2012}}</ref> NASA Administrator [[Charles F. Bolden, Jr.|Charles Bolden]] said that: "As long as there are history books, Neil Armstrong will be included in them, remembered for taking humankind's first small step on a world beyond our own".<ref name="BOLDIN 25 AUGUST 2012">{{cite web |title=NASA Administrator Statement on Neil Armstrong's Death |publisher=NASA |date=August 25, 2012 |url=http://www.nasa.gov/home/hqnews/2012/aug/HQ_12-601_Bolden_Statement.html |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |title=US space pioneer Neil Armstrong dies at 82 - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/americas/2012/08/201282519933640323.html |accessdate=August 26, 2012}}</ref>

[[File:Neil Armstrong burial at sea (201209140008HQ).jpg|thumb|left|Armstrong's [[burial at sea]] on September 14, 2012]]
A tribute was held in Armstrong's honor on September 13 at [[Washington National Cathedral]], whose Space Window depicts the ''Apollo 11'' mission and holds a sliver of Moon rock amid its stained-glass panels.<ref name="aljazeu"/> In attendance were Armstrong's Apollo 11 crewmates, Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin; Eugene A. Cernan, the ''Apollo 17'' mission commander and last man to walk on the Moon; and former Senator and astronaut John Glenn, the first American to orbit the Earth. In a eulogy, Charles Bolden said, "Neil will always be remembered for taking humankind's first small step on a world beyond our own, but it was the courage, grace, and humility he displayed throughout this life that lifted him above the stars." Eugene Cernan recalled Armstrong's low-fuel approach to the Moon: "When the gauge says empty we all know there's a gallon or two left in the tank!" [[Diana Krall]] sang the song "[[Fly Me to the Moon]]". Michael Collins led prayers. Aldrin and Collins left immediately after the event. The ''[[Apollo 15]]'' commander, [[David Scott]], spoke to the press; he recalled the ''[[Gemini 8]]'' mission with Armstrong when he spoke, possibly for the first time, about an incident in which glue spilled on his harness and prevented it from locking correctly minutes before the hatch had to be sealed or the mission aborted. Armstrong then called on back-up pilot [[Pete Conrad]] to solve the problem, which he did, to continue the mission without stopping the countdown clock. "That happened because Neil Armstrong was a team player, he always worked on behalf of the team."<ref name="aljazeu">{{cite web |last=Terrett |first=John |title=Above the stars now |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=September 15, 2012 |url=http://blogs.aljazeera.com/blog/americas/above-stars-now |accessdate=September 26, 2012}}</ref>

On September 14, Armstrong's cremated remains were scattered in the [[Atlantic Ocean]] during a [[Burial at sea|burial-at-sea]] ceremony aboard the {{USS|Philippine Sea|CG-58|6}}.<ref>{{cite web |title=Neil Armstrong Laid to Rest in Atlantic |publisher=NASA |url=http://www.nasa.gov/topics/people/features/armstrong_cathedral_memorial.html |accessdate=September 14, 2012}}</ref> Flags were flown at [[half-mast|half-staff]] on the day of Armstrong's funeral.<ref>{{cite web |title=Obama orders flags at half-staff for Neil Armstrong |publisher=USA Today |date=August 27, 2012 |url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/theoval/post/2012/08/obama-orders-flags-at-half-staff-for-armstrong/1#.UPMU3InjlU5/ |accessdate=January 13, 2013 }}</ref>

==Legacy==
[[File:RIAN archive 837790 Valentina Tereshkova and Neil Armstrong.jpg|thumb|180px|First woman in space, [[Valentina Tereshkova]], presents Armstrong with a badge at his visit to the [[Yuri Gagarin Cosmonaut Training Center|Yuri Gagarin Cosmonaut Training Center in Star City]], June 1, 1970]]
[[File:Stevan Kragujevic, Neil Armstrong in Belgrade, 1969.JPG|thumb|180px|Neil Armstrong in [[Belgrade]], [[SFRY|SFR Yugoslavia]], 1969.]]
{| style="margin: 1em auto;"
|colspan=3 style="text-align: center;"|[[File:En-NavAstro.jpg|200px]]
|-
|colspan=3 style="text-align: center;"|{{ribbon devices|number=2|type=award-star|ribbon=Air Medal ribbon.svg|width=103}} {{ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Ribbon of the US Navy Presidential Unit Citation.svg|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Presidential Medal of Freedom with Distinction (ribbon).PNG|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=CongSpaceRib.png|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=NasaDisRib.gif|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=National Defense Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=service-star|ribbon=Korean Service Medal - Ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=ResMedRib.svg|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Korean Presidential Unit Citation.png|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=United Nations Service Medal for Korea Ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Korean War Service Medal ribbon.png|width=103}}
|}

{| class="wikitable" style="margin: 1em auto; text-align: center;"
|-
|colspan=3 |[[Astronaut Badge|Naval Aviator Astronaut badge]]
|-
|colspan=3 |[[Air Medal]] with two [[5/16 inch star|stars]] | [[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|Presidential Unit Citation]]
|-
|[[Presidential Medal of Freedom|Presidential Medal of Freedom<br>with Distinction]]
|[[Congressional Space Medal of Honor]]
|[[NASA Distinguished Service Medal]]
|-
|[[National Defense Service Medal]]
|[[Korean Service Medal]]<br>with one [[Service star|star]]
|[[Armed Forces Reserve Medal]]
|-
|[[Republic of Korea Presidential Unit Citation|Presidential Unit Citation<br>(Korea)]]
|[[United Nations Korea Medal]]
|[[Korean War Service Medal]]
|}

Armstrong received many honors and awards, including the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]], the [[Congressional Space Medal of Honor]], the Robert H. Goddard Memorial Trophy, the Sylvanus Thayer Award, the [[Collier Trophy]] from the National Aeronautics Association, and the [[Congressional Gold Medal]]. The lunar crater [[Armstrong (crater)|Armstrong]], 31&nbsp;mi (50&nbsp;km) from the ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' landing site, and [[asteroid]] [[6469 Armstrong]]<ref>{{cite web |title=Discovery Circumstances: Numbered Minor Planets (5001)-(10000) |url=http://www.minorplanetcenter.net/iau/lists/NumberedMPs005001.html |accessdate=November 27, 2015}}</ref> are named in his honor. Armstrong was also inducted into the [[Aerospace Walk of Honor]], the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]], and the [[United States Astronaut Hall of Fame]].<ref>{{cite web |title=Honorees |publisher=City of Lancaster |url=http://www.cityoflancasterca.org/index.aspx?page=193 |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |title=Neil A. Armstrong |publisher=Astronaut Scholarship Foundation |url=http://www.astronautscholarship.org/armstrong.html |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref> Armstrong and his Apollo 11 crewmates were the 1999 recipients of the [[Langley Gold Medal]] from the Smithsonian Institution.

Throughout the United States, there are more than a dozen elementary, middle and high schools named in his honor,<ref>{{cite web |url=http://nces.ed.gov/ccd/schoolsearch/school_list.asp?Search=1&InstName=neil+armstrong&SchoolID=&Address=&City=&State=&Zip=&Miles=&County=&PhoneAreaCode=&Phone=&DistrictName=&DistrictID=&SchoolType=1&SchoolType=2&SchoolType=3&SchoolType=4&SpecificSchlTypes=all&IncGrade=-1&LoGrade=-1&HiGrade=-1 |title=Search for Public School |accessdate=July 10, 2007 }}</ref> and many places around the world have streets, buildings, schools, and other places named for Armstrong and/or Apollo.<ref>{{cite news |title=Ireland: What's in a name? Cold, hard cash |work=The Times |location=London |date=December 22, 2002 |url=http://property.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/property/article804378.ece |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref> In 1969, folk songwriter and singer [[John Stewart (musician)|John Stewart]] recorded "Armstrong", a tribute to Armstrong and his first steps on the Moon. Purdue University announced in October 2004 that its new engineering building would be named ''[[Purdue University College of Engineering|Neil Armstrong Hall of Engineering]]'' in his honor;<ref name="holsapple">{{cite news |last=Holsapple |first=Matt |title=Purdue launching Neil Armstrong Hall for engineering's future |work=Purdue University News |date=October 16, 2004 |url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/html3month/2004/041016.Jischke.Armstrong.html |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref> the building cost $53.2&nbsp;million and was dedicated on October 27, 2007, during a ceremony at which Armstrong was joined by fourteen other Purdue Astronauts.<ref name="venere">{{cite news |last=Venere |first=Emil |title=Neil Armstrong Hall is new home to Purdue engineering |work=Purdue University News |date=October 27, 2007 |url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2007b/071027CelArmstrongDedication.html |accessdate=January 5, 2008}}</ref> In 1971, Armstrong was awarded the [[Sylvanus Thayer Award]] by the United States Military Academy at West Point for his service to the country.<ref>{{cite web |title=Sylvanus Thayer Award |publisher=Sylvanus-thayer-award.co.tv |url=http://sylvanus-thayer-award.co.tv/ |accessdate=May 19, 2011}}</ref> The [[Armstrong Air and Space Museum]], in Armstong's hometown of [[Wapakoneta, Ohio]], and the airport in [[New Knoxville, Ohio|New Knoxville]], where he took his first flying lessons when he was fifteen, were named after him.<ref>{{cite book |last=Woods |first=Mary B.  |last2=Woods |first2=Michael |title=Space Disasters |publisher=Lerner Publications |page=57 |date=January 1, 2008 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0OOhCNTNHuEC&pg=PA57}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |last=Knight |first=Andy  |title=To the moon: Armstrong space museum offers history lessons on space travel |publisher=Cincinnati.Com |date=Winter 2000 |url=http://www.cincinnati.com/visitorsguide/stories/012800_moon.html |accessdate=August 28, 2007}}</ref><ref>{{cite book |last=Goodman |first=Rebecca |last2=Brunsman |first2=Barrett J. |title=This Day in Ohio History |publisher=Clerisy Press |date=2005}}</ref>

[[File:Apollo 11 - Crew at the White House.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=Photo of four men wearing suits, with the curtain drawn behind them, admitting light.|Michael Collins, [[President of the United States|President]] [[George W. Bush]], Neil Armstrong, and Buzz Aldrin during celebrations of the 35th anniversary of the ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' flight, July 21, 2004]]
Armstrong's authorized biography, ''[[First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong]]'', was published in 2005. For many years, Armstrong turned down biography offers from authors such as Stephen Ambrose and James A. Michener, but agreed to work with James R. Hansen after reading one of Hansen's other biographies.<ref>{{cite news |last=McGauley |first=John |title=Discovering the Man Behind 'First Man' |date=October 14, 2005 |publisher=collectSPACE.com |url=http://www.collectspace.com/news/news-013003b.html#100305}}</ref>

In a 2010 ''Space Foundation'' survey, Armstrong was ranked as the #1 most popular space hero,<ref>{{cite press release |title=Space Foundation Survey Reveals Broad Range of Space Heroes |publisher=Space Foundation |date=October 27, 2010 |accessdate=May 13, 2011 |url=http://www.spacefoundation.org/news/story.php?id=1038 }}</ref> and in 2013, ''Flying'' magazine ranked him at #1 on its list of the "51 Heroes of Aviation".<ref>{{cite journal |title=51 Heroes of Aviation |work=Flying |url=http://www.flyingmag.com/photo-gallery/photos/51-heroes-aviation?pnid=41853}}</ref>

The press often asked Armstrong for his views on the future of spaceflight. In 2005, Armstrong said that a [[manned mission to Mars]] will be easier than the [[Apollo program|lunar challenge]] of the 1960s: "I suspect that even though the various questions are difficult and many, they are not as difficult and many as those we faced when we started the Apollo [space program] in 1961." In 2010, he made a rare public criticism of the decision to cancel the ''[[Ares I|Ares&nbsp;1]]'' launch vehicle and the [[Constellation program|Constellation Moon landing program]].<ref>{{cite news |last=Kaplan |first=Jeremy A. |title=Star Wars: Neil Armstrong, Obama Spar Over NASA's Future |date=April 14, 2010 |work=Fox News |url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2010/04/14/obama-vs-neil-armstrong-nasa-constellation/?test=latestnews}}</ref>
In an open public letter also signed by Apollo veterans [[Jim Lovell]] and [[Eugene Cernan|Gene Cernan]], he noted, "For The United States, the leading space faring nation for nearly half a century, to be without carriage to low Earth orbit and with no human exploration capability to go beyond Earth orbit for an indeterminate time into the future, destines our nation to become one of second or even third rate stature".<ref>{{cite news |last=Armstrong |first=Neil |last2=Lovell |first2=James |last3=Cernan |first3=Eugene |title=Armstrong: Obama NASA plan 'devastating' |date=April 14, 2010 |work=NBC Nightly News |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/36470363}}</ref> Armstrong had also publicly recalled his initial concerns about the ''Apollo&nbsp;11'' mission, when he had believed there was only a 50 percent chance of landing on the Moon. "I was elated, ecstatic and extremely surprised that we were successful", he later said.<ref>{{cite news  |first=Sean |last=Yoong|title=Neil Armstrong: Manned Mars mission 20 years away |work=USA Today |location=Washington DC |date=September 6, 2005 |url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/science/space/2005-09-06-mars-armstrong_x.htm |accessdate=May 3, 2011}}</ref>

On November 18, 2010, at age 80, Armstrong said in a speech during the ''[[Meet the Future, Science & Technology Summit 2010|Science & Technology Summit]]'' in The Hague, Netherlands, that he would offer his services as commander on a mission to Mars if he were asked.<ref>{{cite web |title=Neil Armstrong wil nog best naar Mars |trans-title=Neil Armstrong still wants to go to Mars |work=NU.nl |language=nl |date=November 18, 2010 |url=http://www.nu.nl/wetenschap/2382331/neil-armstrong-wil-nog-best-mars.html}}</ref>

In September 2012, the US Navy announced that the first {{sclass|Armstrong|oceanographic research ship}} is named [[RV Neil Armstrong (AGOR-27)|RV ''Neil Armstrong'']]. The ship, christened on March 28, 2014, was launched on March 29, 2014, passed sea trials August 7, 2015 and delivered to the Navy on September 23, 2015.  It is a modern oceanographic research platform capable of supporting a wide range of oceanographic research activities conducted by academic groups.<ref>{{cite news |title=Navy Announces Research Vessel to be Named in Honor of Neil Armstrong |date=September 24, 2012 |publisher=United States Navy |url=http://www.navy.mil/submit/display.asp?story_id=69758 }}</ref>

The [[Space Foundation]] named Neil Armstrong as a recipient of its 2013 General James E. Hill Lifetime Space Achievement Award.<ref>{{cite web |title=Neil Armstrong and Sally Ride Are 2013 General James E. Hill Lifetime Space Achievement Award Honorees |publisher=Space Foundation |url=http://www.spacefoundation.org/media/press-releases/neil-armstrong-and-sally-ride-are-2013-general-james-e-hill-lifetime-space |accessdate=March 26, 2013}}</ref>

==See also==
{{Portal|Spaceflight|Biography}}
* [[List of Eagle Scouts]]
* [[List of spaceflight-related accidents and incidents]]
* [[Mission control center]]
* [[Project Mercury]]
* [[Space Shuttle program]]

==References==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* ''Cambridge Biographical Dictionary'' (1990). [[Cambridge]]: [[Cambridge University Press]].
* {{Cite book | last=Chaikin| first=Andrew | title=A Man on the Moon : The Voyages of the Apollo Astronauts | publisher=Penguin books| year=1995 |isbn=978-0140241464}}
* {{cite web | last =Cornish| first =Scott|author2=Rahman, Tahir |author3=McLeon, Bob |author4=Havekotte, Ken |author5= Reznikoff, John | title=Neil Armstrong Signature Exemplars| work=CollectSpace.com| url=http://www.collectspace.com/resources/autographs_armstrong.html | accessdate=May 14, 2011}}
* {{Cite book | last1=Francis | first1= French | authorlink1=Francis French | last2=Burgess | first2=Colin | authorlink2=Colin Burgess (author) | year= 2007 | title=[[In the Shadow of the Moon (book)|In the Shadow of the Moon]] | chapter=A Challenging Journey to Tranquility, 1965–1969}}
* {{Cite book | last=Hansen| first=James R. | title=[[First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong]] | publisher=Simon & Schuster | year=2005 | isbn=978-0743256315}}
* {{cite web| last=Jones| first=Eric | title=One Small Step| work =Apollo 11 Lunar Surface Journal| publisher=NASA| url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/alsj/a11/a11.step.html| year=1995| accessdate=May 14, 2001}}
* {{Cite book | last=Kranz | first=Gene | authorlink=Gene Kranz | title=Failure is not an Option: Mission Control From Mercury to Apollo 13 and Beyond | publisher=Simon & Schuster | year=2000 | isbn=978-0783556758}}
* {{Cite book | last=Nelson | first=Craig | title=Rocket Men: The Epic Story of the First Men on the Moon | location=New York, New York| publisher=John Murray | year=2009 | isbn=978-0-670-02103-1| ref={{harvid|Nelson|2009}}}}
* {{Cite book | first=Andrew | last=Smith | title=Mondust: In Search of the Men Who Fell to Earth | location=London | publisher=Bloomsbury | year=2005 | isbn=0-7475-6368-3}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | last=Barbree | first1=Jay | title=Neil Armstrong: A Life of Flight | location=New York | publisher=Thomas Dunne Books | year=2014 | isbn=978-1250040718}}
* {{cite web | last=Kirk | first=Mass Communication Specialist 1st Class Amy | title=Astronaut Legend Neil Armstrong Receives Naval Astronaut Wings | publisher=U.S. Naval Forces Central Command | date=March 11, 2010 | url=http://www.cusnc.navy.mil/articles/2010/021.html | accessdate =May 14, 2011}}
* {{cite web | last=Sherrod| first=Robert | title=Men for the Moon | publisher=NASA | date=July 30, 1975| url=http://history.nasa.gov/SP-350/toc.html}}
* {{Cite book | last=Thompson | first=Milton O. | title=At The Edge Of Space: The X-15 Flight Program | publisher=Smithsonian Books | year=1992 | location =Washington, D.C. | isbn=978-1560981077}}
* {{cite web | url=http://www.nasa.gov/vision/space/features/armstrong_ambassador_of_exploration.html | title=NASA Honors Neil Armstrong With Exploration Award | publisher=NASA | date=April 18, 2006 | accessdate=December 5, 2014}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links |wikt=no|commons=Neil Armstrong|b=no|n=Category:Neil Armstrong|q=Neil Armstrong|s=no|v=no|species=no|display=Neil Armstrong}}
<!--===============================================================================-->
<!--| WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS. Only a limited number of new links  |-->
<!--| should be added to this article. Consider adding links to the appropriate   |-->
<!--| category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org) and link back to that |-->
<!--| category using the {{dmoz}} template.                                       |-->
<!--| See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for further details |-->
<!--===============================================================================-->
* [http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/armstrong-na.html Armstrong's official NASA biography]
* [http://uc.edu/armstrong Neil Armstrong Commemorative Website] - [[University of Cincinnati]]
* {{Wayback |url=http://neilarmstronginfo.com/ |title=Armstrong website, formerly maintained by the Armstrong family |date=20130617234237}}
* {{IMDb name|0035842}}
* {{C-SPAN|neilarmstrong}}

{{S-start}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Ellsworth Bunker]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = [[Sylvanus Thayer Award|Sylvanus Thayer Award recipient]]|years = 1971}}
{{s-aft|after = [[Billy Graham (evangelist)|Billy Graham]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{People who have walked on the Moon| state=expanded}}
{{Congressional Space Medal of Honor}}
{{NASA Astronaut Group 2|state=autocollapse}}

{{Use American English|date=July 2015}} 
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2015}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Armstrong, Neil}}
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:1966 in spaceflight]]
[[Category:1969 in spaceflight]]
[[Category:2012 deaths]]
[[Category:Neil Armstrong| ]]
[[Category:American aerospace engineers]]
[[Category:American astronauts]]
[[Category:American deists]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Korean War]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scotch-Irish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American test pilots]]
[[Category:Apollo 11]]
[[Category:Apollo program astronauts]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Aviators from Ohio]]
[[Category:Burials at sea]]
[[Category:Collier Trophy recipients]]
[[Category:Congressional Gold Medal recipients]]
[[Category:Distinguished Eagle Scouts]]
[[Category:People from Indian Hill, Ohio]]
[[Category:Members of the United States National Academy of Engineering]]
[[Category:NASA civilian astronauts]]
[[Category:People from Auglaize County, Ohio]]
[[Category:People who have walked on the Moon]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Purdue University alumni]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Congressional Space Medal of Honor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Cullum Geographical Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Langley Medal]]
[[Category:Shot-down aviators]]
[[Category:United States Astronaut Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:United States Naval Aviators]]
[[Category:United States Navy officers]]
[[Category:USC Viterbi School of Engineering alumni]]
[[Category:Wapakoneta, Ohio]]
[[Category:X-15 program]]
</text>
</page>
<page>
<title>Buzz Aldrin</title>
<text>
{{More footnotes|date=October 2015}}
{{Infobox astronaut
| name          = Buzz Aldrin
| othername     = 
| image         = Aldrin.jpg
| caption       = Aldrin in July 1969
| type          = [[File:Buzz Aldrin Autograph.svg|150px]]<br/>[[NASA]] [[Astronaut]]
| status        = Retired
| nationality   = [[United States|American]]
| birth_name    = Edwin Eugene Aldrin Jr.
| birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|1930|01|20}}
| birth_place   = Mountainside Hospital, [[Montclair, New Jersey]], U.S. 
| occupation    = [[Fighter pilot]]
| alma_mater    = [[United States Military Academy]], B.S. 1951<br>[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]], Sc.D. 1963
| rank          = [[File:US-O6_insignia.svg|15px]] [[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]], [[United States Air Force|USAF]]
| selection     = [[List of astronauts by selection#1963|1963 NASA Group 3]]
| eva1          = 4
| eva2          = 7 hours 52 minutes
| time          = 12 days 1 hour and 52 minutes
| mission       = [[Gemini 12]], [[Apollo 11]]
| insignia      = [[File:Gemini 12 insignia.png|40px]] [[File:Apollo 11 insignia.png|40px]]
| Date of ret   = July 1, 1971
| awards        = [[File:USAF Master Astronaut badge.jpg|55px|link=astronaut badge|United States Air Force Master Pilot/Astronaut Wings]] [[File:Dfc-usa.jpg|20px|link=Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]] {{Presidential Medal of Freedom}} [[File:NASA Distinguished Service Medal.jpg|20px|link=NASA Distinguished Service Medal]]
| website       = {{URL|http://www.buzzaldrin.com/}}}}
'''Buzz Aldrin''' (born '''Edwin Eugene Aldrin, Jr.''', January 20, 1930) is an American [[engineer]] and former [[astronaut]]. As the [[Lunar Module]] Pilot on [[Apollo 11]], he was one of the first two humans to [[Apollo 11#Landing|land on the Moon]], and the [[Apollo 11#Lunar surface operations|second person to walk on it]]. He set foot on the [[Moon]] at 03:15:16 on July 21, 1969 ([[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]), following mission commander [[Neil Armstrong]]. He is a former [[United States Air Force|U.S. Air Force officer]] with the [[U.S. Air Force aeronautical rating#Pilot ratings|Command Pilot rating]].

==Biography==

===Early life===
Aldrin was born January 20, 1930, in Mountainside Hospital, which straddles both [[Glen Ridge, New Jersey|Glen Ridge]] and [[Montclair, New Jersey|Montclair]], in [[Essex County, New Jersey]]. His birth certificate lists Glen Ridge as his birthplace.<ref name=Record20090721>[http://www.northjersey.com/news/national/other_national_news/To_the_moon_and_beyond.html "To the Moon and beyond"], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', July 20, 2009; retrieved July 20, 2009. The source is indicative of the confusion regarding his birthplace. He is described in the article's first paragraph as having been "born and raised in [[Montclair, New Jersey]]", while a more detailed second paragraph on "The Early Years" states that he was "born Edwin Eugene Aldrin Jr. on January 20, 1930, in the Glen Ridge wing of Montclair Hospital".</ref><ref>{{cite book|last=Hansen|first=James R.|title=[[First Man: The Life of Neil A. Armstrong]]|publisher=Simon & Schuster|year=2005|isbn=0743257510|page=348}} "His birth certificate lists Glen Ridge as his birthplace."</ref> His parents were Edwin Eugene Aldrin Sr. (1896–1974), a career military man, and Marion (Moon) Gaddys (1903–1968), who lived in Montclair.<ref>{{Wayback|date=20080402060645|url=http://www.buzzaldrin.com/about/full/index.html|ittle=About Buzz Aldrin}}; retrieved November 8, 2012.</ref><ref name="NYT-2009-06-15">{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/21/magazine/21fob-q4-t.html|title=Questions for Buzz Aldrin: The Man on the Moon|last=Solomon|first=Deborah|author2=Oth, Christian|date=June 21, 2009|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=March 15, 2015}}</ref>  He is of [[Scottish people|Scottish]], [[Swedish people|Swedish]],<ref>Powell, Sarah. {{Wayback|date=20101224214129|url=http://www.burkespeerage.com/articles/scotland/saal7.aspx|title=From The Dollar To The Moon. Chapter 7 – That "giant leap for mankind"}}. burkespeerage.com; accessed October 25, 2015.</ref> and [[German people|German]] ancestry. Aldrin was a [[Boy Scouting (Boy Scouts of America)|Boy Scout]] and earned the rank of [[Ranks in the Boy Scouts of America#Tenderfoot Scout|Tenderfoot Scout]].<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.scouting.org/About/FactSheets/scouting_space.aspx|title=Scouting and Space Exploration|work=scouting.org}}</ref>

After graduating from [[Montclair High School (New Jersey)|Montclair High School]] in 1947,<ref name=Record20090721 /><ref name="ADKDailyEnterprise">{{cite web|url=http://news.nnyln.net/adirondack-enterprise/adirondack-enterprise-1969/adirondack-enterprise-1969-july%20-%200064.pdf|publisher=Adirondack Daily Enterprise|title=Aldrin Was A Classmate|date=July 14, 1969|accessdate=July 17, 2012}}</ref> Aldrin turned down a full scholarship offer from the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] (which he would later attend for graduate school), and went to the [[United States Military Academy]] at [[West Point, New York]].  The nickname "Buzz" originated in childhood: the younger of his two elder sisters mispronounced "brother" as "buzzer", and this was shortened to Buzz. Aldrin made it his legal first name in 1988.<ref name="Chaikin">{{cite book|last=Chaikin|first=Andrew|authorlink=Andrew Chaikin|title=A Man on the Moon|year=2007|publisher=Penguin|page=585|isbn=014311235X}}</ref>

===Military career===
Aldrin graduated third in his class at West Point in 1951, with a [[Bachelor of Science]] degree in [[mechanical engineering]]. He was commissioned as a [[Second lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]] in the [[United States Air Force]] and served as a jet [[fighter pilot]] during the [[Korean War]]. He flew 66 [[Aerial warfare|combat mission]]s in [[F-86 Sabre]]s and shot down two [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-15]] aircraft. The June 8, 1953, issue of ''Life'' magazine featured gun camera photos taken by Aldrin of one of the Soviet pilots ejecting from his damaged aircraft.<ref>{{cite news|title=Communist Pilot is Catapulted from Crippled MIG|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3EcEAAAAMBAJ|accessdate=November 8, 2012|date=June 8, 1953|work=Life|issn=0024-3019|page=29}}</ref>

After the war, Aldrin was assigned as an [[Air gunner|aerial gunnery]] instructor at [[Nellis Air Force Base]] in [[Nevada]], and next was an aide to the dean of faculty at the [[United States Air Force Academy]], which had recently begun operations in 1955. That same year, he graduated from the [[Squadron Officer School]] at [[Maxwell Air Force Base]] in [[Alabama]]. He flew [[F-100 Super Sabre]]s as a flight commander at [[Bitburg Air Base]], West Germany, in the [[22d Fighter Squadron]]. In 1963 Aldrin earned a [[Doctor of Science]] degree in [[Astronautics]] from [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]].<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/aldrin-b.html|title=Astronaut Bio: Buzz Aldrin|work=nasa.gov}}</ref> His graduate thesis was ''"Line-of-sight guidance techniques for manned orbital rendezvous"'',<ref>[http://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/12652 DSpace@MIT : Line-of-sight guidance techniques for manned orbital rendezvous]. Dspace.mit.edu; retrieved November 8, 2012.</ref> the dedication of which read, "In the hopes that this work may in some way contribute to their exploration of space, this is dedicated to the crew members of this country’s present and future manned space programs. If only I could join them in their exciting endeavors!"

On completion of his doctorate, he was assigned to the Gemini Target Office of the Air Force Space Systems Division in [[Los Angeles]] before his selection as an astronaut. His initial application to join the astronaut corps was rejected on the basis of never having been a test pilot; that prerequisite was lifted when he re-applied and was accepted into the third astronaut class.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

===NASA career===
{{Main|Gemini 12|Apollo 11}}
{{rquote|right|Magnificent desolation.|3=Aldrin's first impression of the Moon, standing on its surface.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.nmspacemuseum.org/halloffame/detail.php?id=59|title=International Space Hall of Fame :: New Mexico Museum of Space History: Inductee Profile|work=nmspacemuseum.org}}</ref>}}
[[File:Gemini XII EVA with Buzz Aldrin and the Earth in his visor's reflection.jpg|thumb|left|Aldrin during [[Gemini 12]] with the Earth reflecting off his visor]]
[[File:Lovell and Aldrin on Deck - GPN-2000-001356.jpg|thumb|upright||right|Aldrin and [[Jim Lovell]] after the Gemini 12 mission]]
[[File:Aldrin Apollo 11 original.jpg|thumb|left|Aldrin walks on the surface of the Moon during Apollo 11]]
[[File:Apollo 11 bootprint.jpg|thumb|right|Aldrin's lunar footprint in a photo taken by him on July 21, 1969]]
[[File:A11v 1094228.ogg|thumb|left|Video from the [[Apollo 11]] mission]]
Aldrin was selected as a member of the [[Astronaut Group 3|third group]] of [[NASA]] astronauts in October 1963. Because [[test pilot]] experience was no longer a requirement, this was the first selection for which he was eligible. After the deaths of the original [[Gemini 9A|Gemini 9]] prime crew, [[Elliot See]] and [[Charles Bassett]], Aldrin and [[Jim Lovell]] were promoted to backup crew for the mission. The main objective of the revised mission ([[Gemini 9A]]) was to rendezvous and dock with a target vehicle, but when this failed, Aldrin improvised an effective exercise for the craft to rendezvous with a co-ordinate in space. He was confirmed as pilot on [[Gemini 12]], the last [[Project Gemini|Gemini mission]] and the last chance to prove methods for [[extravehicular activity]] (EVA). He set a record for EVA, demonstrating that astronauts could work outside spacecraft.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

Aldrin was chosen for the crew of [[Apollo 11]] and made the first lunar landing with commander [[Neil Armstrong]] on July 20, 1969. The next day, Aldrin became the second person to walk on the Moon, keeping his record total EVA time until that was surpassed on [[Apollo 14]]. Aldrin's first words on the Moon were "Beautiful view." Then, in response to Armstrong asking, "Isn't it magnificent?", he responded, "Magnificent desolation."<ref>{{cite AV media|publisher=National Aeronautics and Space Administration| editor-last=Teague|editor-first=Kipp|last3=Aldrin|first3=Buzz|date=July 21, 1969|title=Apollo 11 – Buzz Aldrin Descends Ladder to Lunar Surface|url=http://history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/a11v_1094228.mpg|accessdate=December 22, 2013|format=MPEG-1|at=48 seconds|quote=Beautiful view. Magnificent desolation.|laysummary=http://history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/video11.html|laysource=Apollo 11 Video Library|laydate=September 6, 2011|ref=AldrinFootage}}</ref> He was also the first person to urinate on the moon.<!--Yes, that is what the following two references say. --><ref>{{cite news|last1=Diaz|first1=Jesus|title=Buzz Aldrin Was the First Man to Pee on the Moon—42 Years Ago Today|url=http://gizmodo.com/5822581/buzz-aldrin-was-the-first-man-to-pee-on-the-moon--42-years-ago-today|accessdate=September 23, 2015|publisher=Gizmodo|date=July 20, 2011}}</ref><ref>{{cite news|last1=Minard|first1=Anne|title=Buzz Aldrin, First Man (to Pee) on the Moon, Sounds Off|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2009/07/090716-moon-landing-buzz-aldrin-pee.html|accessdate=September 23, 2015|publisher=National Geographic News|date=July 16, 2009}}</ref><ref>{{cite news|last1=Graham|first1=Jane|title=Letter to my younger self - Buzz Aldrin|url=http://www.bigissue.com/features/letter-my-younger-self/2979/buzz-aldrin-interview-i-was-advised-not-say-anything-about-it|accessdate=April 8, 2016|publisher=Big Issue|date=September 3, 2013}}</ref>

There has been speculation about the extent of Aldrin's desire at the time to be the first astronaut to walk on the Moon and its impact on his pre-flight, in-mission and post-flight actions.<ref>{{Citation|publisher=NASA|url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-350/cover.html|title=Apollo Expeditions to the Moon|editor-last=Cortright|editor-first=Edgar M.|chapter=8|page=7}}</ref> According to different NASA accounts, the Lunar Module Pilot (i.e. Aldrin on Apollo 11) had originally been proposed as the first to step onto the Moon's surface in early versions of the EVA checklist, and when Aldrin became aware that this might be amended, he lobbied within NASA for the original procedure to be followed. A number of factors seem to have contributed to the final decision, including the physical positioning of the astronauts inside the compact lunar lander, which made it easier for Armstrong to be the first to exit the spacecraft. Also, Armstrong was the Mission Commander, and other senior astronauts who would command later Apollo missions (and who might have ended up making the first landing in the event of failure on Apollo 11) were not sympathetic to Aldrin's views.<ref>Chaikin, A. (2007). A Man on the Moon. Penguin Books. ISBN 014311235X</ref> Aldrin's pre-flight actions/record and post-flight responses on the issue seem to be adequately summed up by Apollo 11 Command Module Pilot Michael Collins's comment, "I think he resents not being first on the moon more than he appreciates being second." <ref>Collins, Michael (2001). Carrying the Fire; an Astronaut’s Journeys. Cooper Square Press. ISBN 081541028X</ref>

Aldrin, a [[Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)|Presbyterian]], was the first person to hold a religious ceremony on the Moon. After landing on the Moon, he radioed Earth: "I'd like to take this opportunity to ask every person listening in, whoever and wherever they may be, to pause for a moment and contemplate the events of the past few hours, and to give thanks in his or her own way." He took [[Eucharist|communion]] on the surface of the Moon, but he kept it secret because of a lawsuit brought by atheist activist [[Madalyn Murray O'Hair]] over the [[Apollo 8 Genesis reading|reading of Genesis]] on [[Apollo 8]].<ref>{{Citation|last=Chaikin|first=Andrew|authorlink=Andrew Chaikin|title=A Man on the Moon|page=204}}</ref> Aldrin, a church [[Elder (Christianity)|elder]], used a home communion kit given to him, and recited words used by his pastor at Webster Presbyterian Church, the Rev. Dean Woodruff.<ref>{{Citation|first1=Neil|last1=Armstrong|first2=Michael|last2=Collins|first3=Buzz|last3=Aldrin|first4=Gene|last4=Farmer|first5=Dora Jane|last5=Hamblin|title=First on the Moon – A Voyage with Neil Armstrong, Michael Collins, Edwin E. Aldrin, Jr.|place=London, UK|publisher=Michael Joseph|year=1970|page=251|ISBN=0-31605160-8}}</ref><ref>{{cite news|url=http://blog.wired.com/tableofmalcontents/2007/01/sundance_2007_b_1.html|work=Table of Malcontents – Wired Blogs|title=Sundance 2007: Buzz Aldrin Speaks|date=January 24, 2007|last=Hillner|first=Jennifer|accessdate=May 7, 2007}}</ref> The communion elements were the first food and liquid consumed on the Moon: in ''[[Guideposts]]'', Aldrin stated: "It was interesting to think that the very first liquid ever poured on the Moon, and the first food eaten there, were communion elements."<ref name="The Guardian">{{cite news|last=Cresswell|first=Matthew|title=How Buzz Aldrin's communion on the moon was hushed up|url=http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2012/sep/13/buzz-aldrin-communion-moon|newspaper=The Guardian|date=September 13, 2012}}</ref>

Later Aldrin commented on the event: "Perhaps, if I had it to do over again, I would not choose to celebrate communion. Although it was a deeply meaningful experience for me, it was a Christian sacrament, and we had come to the Moon in the name of all mankind – be they Christians, Jews, Muslims, animists, agnostics, or atheists. But at the time I could think of no better way to acknowledge the enormity of the Apollo 11 experience than by giving thanks to God."<ref name="The Guardian"/><ref>Aldrin, Buzz & Ken Abraham (2009). ''Magnificent Desolation: The Long Journey Home from the Moon''. Random House LLC. p. 27; ISBN 9780307463470</ref> Mindful of the controversy caused by the Bible readings made the Apollo 8 crew, the NASA management had warned the Apollo 11 crew against making any explicit religious comments during the flight. However, in the final Apollo 11 TV broadcast during the return journey to Earth, Aldrin quoted from Psalm 8 (verses 3 and 4)<ref>Ryan, P. (1969) ''The Invasion of the Moon 1969: The Story of Apollo 11.'' Penguin Books. Middlesex, England.</ref> "I’ve been reflecting the events of the past several days and a verse from the Psalms comes to mind to me.  'When I consider the heavens, the work of thy fingers, the moon and the stars which thou hast ordained, what is man that thou art mindful of him?'".<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.4thdayalliance.com/articles/space-exploration/apollo-space-program-bible-quotations/|title=4th Day Alliance - Creationism, Creation Science, and Creation Astronomy - Apollo Space Program Bible Quotations|work=4thdayalliance.com}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-09-19-3188379411_x.htm|title=Aldrin note up for auction - USATODAY.com|work=usatoday.com}}</ref> This particular quote seems to have been accepted as a personal observation and did not precipitate any controversy.

===Retirement===
[[File:Buzz Aldrin black and white dress uniform photo portrait.jpg|thumb|upright|Aldrin as Commandant of the Air Force Test Pilot School]]
After leaving NASA in July 1971, Aldrin was assigned as the Commandant of the [[U.S. Air Force Test Pilot School]] at [[Edwards Air Force Base]], [[California]]. In March 1972, Aldrin retired from active duty after 21 years of service, and returned to the Air Force in a managerial role, but his career was blighted by personal problems. His autobiographies ''Return to Earth,'' published in 1973, and ''[[Magnificent Desolation (book)|Magnificent Desolation]],'' published in June 2009, both provide accounts of his struggles with [[clinical depression]] and [[alcoholism]] in the years following his NASA career.<ref>{{cite book|last=Aldrin|first=Buzz|title=Magnificent Desolation: The Long Journey Home from the Moon|publisher=Harmony|year=2009}}</ref> 
Aldrin's life improved considerably when he recognized and sought treatment for his problems. Since retiring from NASA, he has continued to promote space exploration. In 1987 he founded the Space Studies graduate program at the [[University of North Dakota]]. Later, he produced a computer strategy game called ''[[Buzz Aldrin's Race Into Space]]'' (1993). To further promote space exploration, and to commemorate the 40th anniversary of the first lunar landing, Aldrin teamed up with [[Snoop Dogg]], [[Quincy Jones]], [[Talib Kweli]], and [[Soulja Boy]] to create the rap single and video, "Rocket Experience", with proceeds from video and song sales to benefit Aldrin's non-profit foundation, ShareSpace.<ref name="timesonline">[http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/arts/music/article2417581.ece Buzz Aldrin and Snoop Dogg reach for the stars with Rocket Experience], ''[[The Times]]'', June 25, 2009.</ref>

He referred to a "[[Phobos monolith]]" in a July 22, 2009, interview with [[C-SPAN]]: "We should go boldly where man has not gone before. Fly by the comets, visit asteroids, visit the moon of [[Mars]]. There's a monolith there. A very unusual structure on this potato shaped object that goes around Mars once in seven hours. When people find out about that they're going to say 'Who put that there? Who put that there?' The universe put it there. If you choose, God put it there…"<ref>{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bDIXvpjnRws&eurl=http%3A%2F%2F|title=Buzz Aldrin Reveals Existence of Monolith on Mars Moon|publisher=C-SPAN|date=July 22, 2009}}</ref>

Aldrin has voiced parody versions of himself in two of [[Matt Groening]]'s animated series: ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episode "[[Deep Space Homer]]", in which he accompanies [[Homer Simpson]] on a trip into space as part of NASA's plan to improve its public appearance, and the ''[[Futurama]]'' episode "[[Cold Warriors]]". In 2011, Aldrin appeared as himself in the film ''[[Transformers: Dark of the Moon]]'', where he explains to [[Optimus Prime]] and the [[Autobot]]s that the Apollo 11 mission also discovered a Cybertronian ship on the Moon whose existence was concealed from the public.

In 2012, he made a cameo appearance in Japanese drama film ''[[Space Brothers (manga)|Space Brothers]]''. Aldrin appeared as himself in the ''[[Big Bang Theory]]'' episode, "The Holographic Excitation", which aired on October 25, 2012. Aldrin also lent his voice talents to the 2012 video game ''[[Mass Effect 3]]'', playing a stargazer who appears in the game's final scene.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

===Aldrin cycler===
In 1985, Aldrin proposed the existence of a special spacecraft [[trajectory]] now known as the [[Aldrin cycler]].<ref>Aldrin, E. E., "Cyclic Trajectory Concepts," SAIC presentation to the Interplanetary Rapid Transit Study Meeting, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, October 1985.</ref><ref>{{cite journal|author=Byrnes, D. V., Longuski, J. M., and Aldrin, B.|title=Cycler Orbit Between Earth and Mars|journal= Journal of Spacecraft and Rockets|volume=30|issue=3|year=1993|pages=334–336|doi=10.2514/3.25519|url=https://engineering.purdue.edu/people/james.m.longuski.1/JournalArticles/1993/CyclerOrbitbetweenEarthandMars.pdf|accessdate=October 25, 2015}}</ref>
Aldrin's system of cycling spacecraft makes travel to Mars possible using far less propellant than conventional means, with an expected five and a half month journey from the Earth to Mars, and a return trip to Earth of about the same duration on a twin-cycler. Aldrin is still working on this with engineers from Purdue University.<ref>"Aldrin Mars Cycler". buzzaldrin.com.</ref>

===Bart Sibrel incident===
On September 9, 2002, Aldrin was lured to a [[Beverly Hills, California|Beverly Hills]] hotel on the pretext of being interviewed for a Japanese children's television show on the subject of space.  When he arrived, [[Moon landing conspiracy theories|Apollo conspiracy]] proponent [[Bart Sibrel]] accosted him with a film crew and demanded he swear on a [[Bible]] that the Moon landings were not faked, insisting that Aldrin and others had lied about walking on the Moon. After a brief confrontation, in which Sibrel called him "a coward and a liar",<ref>{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/video?id=8114632|title=ABC U.S. News Videos & Video Clips Online|author=ABC News|work=ABC News}}</ref> Aldrin punched Sibrel in the jaw, which was caught on camera by Sibrel's film crew. The police determined that Aldrin was provoked and no charges were filed.<ref name="news">{{cite news|title=Ex-astronaut escapes assault charge|publisher=BBC News|date=September 21, 2002|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2272321.stm|accessdate=July 7, 2012}}</ref> Aldrin dedicates a chapter to this incident in his autobiography ''Magnificent Desolation''.<ref>{{cite book|last=Aldrin|first=Buzz|title = Magnificent Desolation|publisher=Harmony Books|year=2009|page=281}}"A Blow Heard 'Round the World".</ref>

==Views==
[[File:Buzz in Mission Control - cropped.jpg|right|thumb|Aldrin in Mission Control with NASA spokesman [[Josh Byerly]] and Flight Director Ron Spencer in 2009]]

===Criticism of NASA's 2003 return-to-Moon objectives===
In December 2003, Aldrin published an opinion piece in ''[[The New York Times]]'' criticizing NASA's objectives.<ref name="Fly Me To L1">{{cite web|last=Aldrin|first=Buzz|title=Fly Me To L1|work=The New York Times|date=December 5, 2003|url=http://buzzaldrin.com/space-vision/rocket_science/l1-gateport|accessdate=November 14, 2009}}</ref> In it, he voiced concern about NASA's development of a [[Orion (spacecraft)|spacecraft]] "limited to transporting four astronauts at a time with little or no cargo carrying capability" and declared the goal of sending astronauts back to the Moon was "more like reaching for past glory than striving for new triumphs".<ref name="Fly Me To L1"/>

===Support of a manned mission to Mars===
In June 2013, Aldrin wrote an opinion, published in ''The New York Times'', supporting a [[manned mission to Mars]] and which viewed the Moon "not as a destination but more a point of departure, one that places humankind on a trajectory to homestead Mars and become a two-planet species."<ref name="NYT-20130613">{{cite news|last=Aldrin|first=Buzz|title=The Call of Mars|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/14/opinion/global/buzz-aldrin-the-call-of-mars.html|date=June 13, 2013|work=[[New York Times]]|accessdate=June 17, 2013}}</ref> In August 2015, Aldrin, in association with the [[Florida Institute of Technology]], presented a "master plan", for NASA consideration, for astronauts, with a "tour of duty of ten years", to colonize Mars before the year 2040.<ref name="AP-20150827">{{cite news|last=Dunn|first=Marcia|title=Buzz Aldrin joins university, forming 'master plan' for Mars|url=http://apnews.excite.com/article/20150827/us-sci-buzz-aldrin-c7bc5ba293.html|date=August 27, 2015|work=[[AP News]]|accessdate=August 30, 2015}}</ref>

===Climate change===
In 2009, Aldrin commented on [[climate change]] by saying: "I think the climate has been changing for billions of years. If it's warming now, it may cool off later. I'm not in favor of just taking short-term isolated situations and depleting our resources to keep our climate just the way it is today. I'm not necessarily of the school that we are causing it all, I think the world is causing it."<ref name="Buzz Aldrin calls for manned flight to Mars to overcome global problems">{{cite web|last=Aldrin|first=Buzz|title=Buzz Aldrin calls for manned flight to Mars to overcome global problems|work=The Daily Telegraph|date=July 3, 2009|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/5734525/Buzz-Aldrin-calls-for-manned-flight-to-Mars-to-overcome-global-problems.html|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}</ref>

==Books==
[[File:Buzz Aldrin by Gage Skidmore 2.jpg|upright|thumb|Buzz Aldrin speaking at an event in Phoenix, Arizona to promote his book, ''No Dream is Too High'', in April 2016.]]
Books co-authored by Aldrin include ''Return to Earth'' (1973), ''Men From Earth'' (1989), ''Reaching for the Moon'' (2005), ''Look to the Stars'' (2009) and ''Magnificent Desolation'' (2009). He has also co-authored with [[John Barnes (author)|John Barnes]] the science fiction novels ''[[Encounter with Tiber]]'' (1996) and ''[[The Return (2000 novel)|The Return]]'' (2000). His book ''[[Mission to Mars (book)|Mission to Mars]]'' was published in May 2013. In April 2016, he released his latest book, ''No Dream is Too High''.

==Personal life==
Aldrin has been married three times. His first marriage was to Joan Archer (1930-2015), the mother of his three children (James, Janice and Andrew). His second marriage was to Beverly Zile. His third marriage was to Lois Driggs Cannon, from whom he filed for divorce on June 15, 2011, in Los Angeles, citing "[[irreconcilable differences]]".<ref>Roberts, Roxanne and Argetsinger (June 16, 2011).  [http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/reliable-source/post/love-etc-buzz-aldrin-divorces-hef-gets-revenge-on-ex/2011/06/16/AGDaDrXH_blog.html "Love, etc.: Buzz Aldrin divorces; Hugh Hefner gets revenge on ex"].  ''The Washington Post''.</ref> The divorce was finalized on December 28, 2012.<ref>{{cite web|title=Buzz Aldrin – Officially Divorced|url=http://www.ghanamma.com/2013/01/buzz-aldrin-officially-divorced|publisher=Ghanamma|accessdate=January 7, 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/20130927034637/http://www.ghanamma.com/2013/01/buzz-aldrin-officially-divorced|archivedate=September 27, 2013}}</ref> He has one grandson, Jeffrey Schuss, born to his daughter, Janice.

His battles against depression and alcoholism, upon returning home from the Apollo 11 mission, have been documented, most recently in ''Magnificent Desolation''.<ref>{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/TECH/07/17/life.after.moon.landing|publisher=CNN|title= After walking on moon, astronauts trod various paths|accessdate=April 27, 2010|date=July 17, 2009}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://bipolar.about.com/od/businessmenpoliticians/p/buzzaldrin.htm|title=Buzz Aldrin|work=Bipolar|publisher=About|first=Kimberly|last=Read|date=January 4, 2005|accessdate=November 2, 2008}}</ref>
Aldrin is an active supporter of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]], headlining fundraisers for GOP members of [[United States Congress|Congress]].<ref>{{Citation|format=PDF|url=http://combatveteransforcongress.org/sites/default/files/2-26-10-invite.pdf|publisher=Combat Veterans For Congress|title=Invite}}</ref>

In 2007, Aldrin confirmed to ''Time'' magazine that he had recently had a [[face-lift]];<ref name="timelift">{{cite web|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1659730,00.html#ixzz11ko5JooF|title=10 Questions for Buzz Aldrin|publisher=Time.com|date=September 6, 2007|accessdate=March 2, 2014}}</ref> he joked that the [[G-force]]s he was exposed to in space "caused a sagging jowl that needed some attention."<ref name="timelift"/>

Aldrin commented on the death of his Apollo 11 colleague, Neil Armstrong, saying that he was "deeply saddened by the passing. I know I am joined by millions of others in mourning the passing of a true American hero and the best pilot I ever knew. I had truly hoped that on July 20th, 2019, Neil, Mike and I would be standing together to commemorate the 50th Anniversary of our Moon landing...Regrettably, this is not to be."<ref name="ALDRIN Twitter 25 AUGUST 2012">{{cite web|work=The real Buzz|url=https://twitter.com/TheRealBuzz/status/239488144288927744|first=Buzz|last=Aldrin|title=About passing of Neil Armstrong|publisher=Twitter|date=August 25, 2012|accessdate=August 25, 2012}}</ref><ref name="ALDRIN Official Statement 25 AUGUST 2012">{{cite web|first=Buzz|last=Aldrin|type=Official statement|title=On the Passing of Neil Armstrong|url=http://buzzaldrin.com/buzz-aldrins-official-statement-on-the-passing-of-neil-armstrong|date=August 25, 2012|accessdate=October 25, 2015}}</ref>
{{Clear}}

==Awards and honors==
<center>&nbsp;
{|
|colspan=3 align=center|[[File:USAF Master Astronaut badge.jpg|200px]]
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=oak|ribbon=Air Force Distinguished Service ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Legion of Merit ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Flying Cross ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|- 
|{{ribbon devices|number=2|type=oak|ribbon=Air Medal ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Air Force Commendation ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Outstanding Unit ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Presidential Medal of Freedom with Distinction (ribbon).PNG|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=NasaDisRib.gif|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=USA - NASA Excep Rib.png|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=service-star|ribbon=National Defense Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=2|type=service-star|ribbon=Korean Service Medal - Ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=4|type=oak|ribbon=Air Force Longevity Service ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Korean Presidential Unit Citation.png|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=United Nations Service Medal for Korea Ribbon.svg|width=103}}
|{{ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Korean War Service Medal ribbon.png|width=103}}
|}

{| class="wikitable"
|-
|colspan=3 align=center|[[Astronaut Badge#U.S. Air Force astronauts|Air Force Master Astronaut badge]]
|-
|align=center|[[Air Force Distinguished Service Medal]]<br>with [[Oak leaf cluster|cluster]]
|align=center|[[Legion of Merit]] 
|align=center|[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]]<br>with cluster
|-
|align=center|[[Air Medal]]<br>with two clusters
|align=center|[[Air Force Commendation Medal]]
|align=center|[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award|Outstanding Unit Award]]
|-
|align=center|[[Presidential Medal of Freedom|Presidential Medal of Freedom<br>with Distinction]]
|align=center|[[NASA Distinguished Service Medal]]
|align=center|[[NASA Exceptional Service Medal]]
|-
|align=center|[[National Defense Service Medal]]<br>with one [[Service star|star]]
|align=center|[[Korean Service Medal]]<br>with two stars
|align=center|[[Air Force Longevity Service Award]]<br>with four clusters
|-
|align=center|[[Republic of Korea Presidential Unit Citation|Presidential Unit Citation<br>(Korea)]]
|align=center|[[United Nations Korea Medal]]
|align=center|[[Korean War Service Medal]]
|}
</center>
* Civilian awards and decorations include the [[Robert J. Collier Trophy]], the [[Dr. Robert H. Goddard Memorial Trophy]], and the [[Harmon Trophy]].
* Aldrin and his Apollo 11 crewmates were the 1999 recipients of the [[Langley Gold Medal]] from the [[Smithsonian Institution]].
* The crater [[Aldrin (crater)|Aldrin]] on the Moon near the Apollo 11 landing site and Asteroid 6470 Aldrin are named in his honor.
* In 1967, Aldrin received an [[Honorary degree|Honorary]] [[Doctorate of Science]] from [[Gustavus Adolphus College]].{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}
* In 1985, Aldrin was inducted into the [[Scandinavian-American Hall of Fame]], a signature event of [[Norsk Høstfest]].<ref>{{cite web|url=http://hostfest.com/sahf/sahf-inductees/buzz-aldrin|title=Scandinavian-American Hall of Fame:Buzz Aldrin|publisher=Hostfest.com |accessdate=March 2, 2014}}</ref>
* In 1994, Aldrin was anonymously honored on a [[List of people on stamps of the United States|United States postage stamp]]. The 29¢ stamp, commemorating the silver anniversary of the landing, was based on a famous photograph of Aldrin, captured by Neil Armstrong, in which Aldrin's face is obscured by his reflective visor. Postal rules at the time prohibited directly featuring living persons on stamps.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://home.hiwaay.net/~krcool/Astro/moon/moonstamps/ms1994b.gif|title="First Moon Landing, 1969" United States postage stamp|accessdate=March 2, 2014}}</ref>
* In 2001, [[George W. Bush|President Bush]] appointed Aldrin to the [[Commission on the Future of the United States Aerospace Industry]].<ref>[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2001/08/20010822-6.html Personnel Announcements] – August 22, 2001 White House Press Release naming the Presidential Appointees for the commission.</ref>
* Aldrin received the 2003 Humanitarian Award from [[Variety, the Children's Charity]], which, according to the organization, "is given to an individual who has shown unusual understanding, empathy, and devotion to mankind."<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.varietychildrenscharity.org/about_variety/humanitarian_awards.php|title=Variety International Humanitarian Awards|publisher=Variety, the Children's Charity|accessdate=May 7, 2007}}</ref>
* Aldrin is on the [[National Space Society]]'s Board of Governors, and has served as the organization's Chairman; an inductee of the [[U.S. Astronaut Hall of Fame]], [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] and the [[New Mexico Museum of Space History|International Space Hall of Fame]]; and a member of [[The Planetary Society]], with Aldrin's pre-recorded voice appearing on nearly every episode of the Society's ''[[Planetary Radio]].''
* In 2006, the [[Space Foundation]] awarded Aldrin its highest honor, the General [[James E. Hill]] Lifetime Space Achievement Award.<ref>{{Wayback|date=20090203060101|url=http://www.nationalspacesymposium.org/symposium-awards|title=Symposium Awards}}; nationalspacesymposium.org</ref>
* For contributions to the television industry, Aldrin was honored with a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]].<ref name="HWOFDB">{{cite web|url=http://www.hwof.com/stars?recipient=Buzz Aldrin|title=Hollywood Walk of Fame database|publisher=HWOF.com}}</ref>
* Inducted into the [[New Jersey Hall of Fame]] in 2008.<ref>[http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2007/10/frank_bruce_and_buzz_among_fir.html Frank, Bruce and Buzz among first inducted into NJ hall of fame], ''The Star-Ledger'', October 25, 2007. Retrieved May 3, 2010.</ref>
* In 2009, [[Barack Obama|President Obama]] signed legislation conferring the [[Congressional Gold Medal]] upon Aldrin and his Apollo 11 crewmates, [[Neil Armstrong]] and [[Michael Collins (astronaut)|Michael Collins]].
* In a 2010 Space Foundation survey, Aldrin was ranked as the No. 9 (tied with astronauts [[Gus Grissom]] and [[Alan Shepard]]) most popular space hero.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.spacefoundation.org/news/story.php?id=1038|title=Space Foundation Survey Reveals Broad Range of Space Heroes|publisher=spacefoundation.org|date=October 27, 2010}}</ref>
* In 2011, Aldrin was nominated for Best Cameo at the 2011 [[Scream Awards]] for his role playing himself in ''[[Transformers: Dark of the Moon]]''.
* In 2015, Aldrin was named as the Chancellor of the [[International Space University]].<ref>{{cite tweet|user=TheRealBuzz|author=Buzz Aldrin|number=654331595579523072|title=I am so honored to be the new Chancellor of ISU at the #IAC2015 following in Arthur C Clarke's footsteps.|date=October 14, 2015}}</ref>

==Detached adapter panel sighting==
[[File:Buzz Aldrin by Gage Skidmore.jpg|left|upright|thumb|Buzz Aldrin speaking at an event in April 2016.]]
In 2005, while being interviewed for a documentary titled ''First on the Moon: The Untold Story'', Aldrin told an interviewer that they saw an [[unidentified flying object]]. Aldrin told David Morrison, a [[NASA Astrobiology Institute]] senior scientist, that the documentary cut the crew's conclusion <!--see my query above-->that they were probably seeing one of four detached spacecraft adapter panels. Their [[S-IVB]] upper stage was {{convert|6000|mi}} away, but the four panels were jettisoned before the S-IVB made its separation maneuver so they would closely follow the Apollo 11 spacecraft until its first midcourse correction.<ref>{{cite web| url=http://history.nasa.gov/alsj/a11/A11_MissionOpReport.pdf| title=Apollo 11 Mission Op Report| format=PDF|work=NASA}}</ref> When Aldrin appeared on ''[[The Howard Stern Show]]'' on August 15, 2007, Stern asked him about the supposed UFO sighting. Aldrin confirmed that there was no such sighting of anything deemed extraterrestrial, and said they were and are "99.9 percent" sure that the object was the detached panel.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://astrobiology.nasa.gov/ask-an-astrobiologist/question/?id=1568| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721050308/http://astrobiology.nasa.gov/ask-an-astrobiologist/question/?id=1568|archivedate=July 21, 2011|date=July 26, 2006|author=Morrison, David|title=NASA Ask an Astrobiologist|work=NASA}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.ufoevidence.org/cases/case592.htm|title=Astronaut Buzz Aldrin Recounts Apollo 11 UFO Encounter|date=July 18, 1969|publisher=ufoevidence.org|accessdate=October 25, 2015}}</ref>

Interviewed by the [[Science Channel]], Aldrin mentioned seeing unidentified objects, and according to Aldrin his words were taken out of context; he asked the Science Channel to clarify to viewers he did not see alien spacecraft, but they refused.<ref name="SkepticalInquirer">{{cite journal|journal=Skeptical Inquirer|volume=33|issue=1|year=2009|pages=30–31|title=UFOs and Aliens in Space|last=Morrison|first=David|url=http://www.csicop.org/si/show/ufos_and_aliens_in_space|accessdate=October 25, 2015}}</ref>

==Film and television==

===Filmography===
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|+Film and television roles
|-
! Year
! Title
! Role
! class="unsortable" | Notes
|-
| 1976
| ''[[The Boy in the Plastic Bubble]]''
| Himself
| TV movie
|-
| 1994
| ''[[The Simpsons]]''
| Himself (voice)
| Episode: "[[Deep Space Homer]]"
|-
| 1997
| ''[[Space Ghost Coast to Coast]]''
| Himself
| 2 episodes
|-
|1999
| ''[[Disney's Recess]]''
| Himself (voice)
| Episode: "[[Space Cadet]]"
|-
| 2003
| ''[[Da Ali G Show]]'' 
| Himself
| 2 episodes
|-
| 2006
| ''[[Numb3rs]]''
| Himself
| Episode: "[[Killer Chat (Numb3rs)|Killer Chat]]"
|-
| 2007
| ''[[In the Shadow of the Moon (film)|In the Shadow of the Moon]]''
| Himself
| Documentary
|-
| 2008
| ''[[Fly Me to the Moon (film)|Fly Me to the Moon]]''
| Himself
|
|-
| 2010
| ''[[30 Rock]]'' 
| Himself
| Episode: "[[The Moms]]"
|-
| 2010
|''[[Dancing with the Stars (U.S. TV series)|Dancing with the Stars]]''
| Himself/contestant
| 2nd eliminated in [[Dancing with the Stars (U.S. season 10)|season 10]]
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Transformers: Dark of the Moon]]''
| Himself
|
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Futurama]]''
| Himself (voice)
| Episode: "[[Cold Warriors]]"
|-
| 2012
| ''[[Space Brothers (manga)|Space Brothers]]''
| Himself
|
|-
| 2012
| ''[[The Big Bang Theory]]''
| Himself
| Episode: "The Holographic Excitation"
|-
| 2012
| ''[[Mass Effect 3]]''
| The Stargazer (voice)
| Video Game
|-
| 2015
| ''[[Jorden runt på 6 steg]]''
| Himself
| Successfully tested [[six degrees of separation]]
|}

===Portrayed by others===
Aldrin has been portrayed by:
* [[Cliff Robertson]] in ''[[Return to Earth (film)|Return to Earth]]'' (1976)
* Larry Williams in ''[[Apollo 13 (film)|Apollo 13]]'' (1995)
* [[Xander Berkeley]] in ''[[Apollo 11 (film)|Apollo 11]]'' (1996)
* [[Bryan Cranston]] in ''[[From the Earth to the Moon (TV miniseries)|From the Earth to the Moon]]'' (1998) and ''[[Magnificent Desolation: Walking on the Moon 3D]]'' (2005)
* [[James Marsters]] in ''[[Moonshot (film)|Moonshot]]'' (2009)
* Cory Tucker as a younger Buzz Aldrin of 1969 in ''[[Transformers: Dark of the Moon]]'' (2011)
* The name of the Toy Story character [[Buzz Lightyear]] was inspired by Buzz Aldrin. Aldrin acknowledged the tribute when he pulled a Buzz Lightyear doll out during a speech at NASA, to rapturous cheer, a clip of which can be found on the Toy Story 10th Anniversary DVD.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.traileraddict.com/trailer/toy-story-3/featurette-buzz-lightyear|title=Toy Story 3 Featurette - Buzz Lightyear|publisher=Trailer Addict|date=June 18, 2010|accessdate=2010-08-29}}</ref>

==Bibliography==
* Aldrin, Col. Edwin E., Jr. 1970. [http://apollotutoring.com/aldrin_1970.pdf Footsteps on the Moon]. ''Edison Electric Institute Bulletin''. Vol. 38, No. 7, pp.&nbsp;266–272.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Wayne Warga. 1973. ''Return to Earth''. New York, Random House.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Malcolm McConnell. 1989. ''Men from Earth''. New York: Bantam Books.
* Aldrin, Buzz and John Barnes. 1996. ''Encounter with Tiber''. London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1996.
* Aldrin, Buzz and John Barnes. 2000. ''The Return''. New York: Forge.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Wendell Minor. 2005. ''Reaching for the Moon''. New York: Harper Collins Publishers.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Ken Abraham. 2009. ''Magnificent Desolation: The Long Journey Home from the Moon''. New York: Harmony Books.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Wendell Minor. 2009. ''Look to the Stars''. Camberwell, Vic.: Puffin Books.
* Armstrong, Neil; Michael Collins; Edwin E. Aldrin; Gene Farmer; and Dora Jane Hamblin. 1970. ''First on the Moon: A Voyage with Neil Armstrong, Michael Collins, Edwin E. Aldrin, Jr.'' Boston: Little, Brown.
* Aldrin, Buzz. 2013. ''Mission to Mars''. Washington, D.C.:  The National Geographic Society.
* Aldrin, Buzz and Marianne Dyson. 2015. ''Welcome to Mars: Making a Home on the Red Planet''. Washington, D.C.:  National Geographic Children's Books.

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|United States Air Force|Spaceflight}}
* [[Space rendezvous]]
* [[List of spaceflight records]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Buzz Aldrin}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.buzzaldrin.com/ Official website of Buzz Aldrin]
* [http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/aldrin-b.html Aldrin's official NASA biography]
* [http://www.astronautix.com/astros/aldrin.htm Astronautix biography of Buzz Aldrin]
* [http://www.spacefacts.de/bios/astronauts/english/aldrin_buzz.htm Spacefacts biography of Buzz Aldrin]
* [http://www.setp.org/winners/iven-c-kincheloe-recipients.html Iven C. Kincheloe Awards]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/7910275.stm A February 2009 BBC News item about Buzz Aldrin's Moon memories, looking forward to the 40th anniversary of the first Moon landing]
* [http://www.cosmosmagazine.com/node/545 "Satellite of solitude"] by Buzz Aldrin: an article in which Aldrin describes what it was like to walk on the Moon, ''Cosmos'' science magazine
* [http://www.muldrake.com/aldrin.html ''To the Moon...'' with Buzz Aldrin]
* [http://www.spaceacts.com/STARSHIP/seh/aldrin.htm Aldrin at Spaceacts]
* [http://www.daviddarling.info/encyclopedia/A/Aldrin.html Aldrin at Encyclopedia of Science]
* {{IMDb name|0004696|Buzz Aldrin}}
* [http://www.nationalaviation.org/aldrin-buzz/ Buzz Aldrin] at the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]]
* [http://www.radiolive.co.nz/Graeme-Hill-meets-Buzz-Aldrin/tabid/491/articleID/12454/Default.aspx Video interview with Buzz Aldrin] Buzz is shown an enlarged print of Tranquility Base and talks Graeme Hill through the points of significance.
* [http://astrotalkuk.org/2008/04/20/episode12journey-to-the-moon/ Video interview] on AstrotalkUK
* [http://www.nmspacemuseum.org/halloffame/detail.php?id=59 Aldrin at International Space Hall of Fame]
*[http://www.heightcelebs.com/2015/02/buzz-aldrin-quotes/ Buzz Aldrin's Quotes]
*{{C-SPAN|Buzz Aldrin}}

{{The Moon}}
{{People who have walked on the Moon|state=expanded}}
{{NASA Astronaut Group 3|state=autocollapse}}
{{US Air Force navbox}}
{{Dancing with the Stars Season 10}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aldrin, Buzz}}
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:1966 in spaceflight]]
[[Category:1969 in spaceflight]]
[[Category:20th-century American businesspeople]]
[[Category:American astronauts]]
[[Category:American autobiographers]]
[[Category:American aviators]]
[[Category:American businesspeople]]
[[Category:American engineers]]
[[Category:American Freemasons]]
[[Category:American male writers]]
[[Category:American mechanical engineers]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Korean War]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Swedish descent]]
[[Category:American Presbyterians]]
[[Category:Apollo 11]]
[[Category:Apollo program astronauts]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Aviators from New Jersey]]
[[Category:Collier Trophy recipients]]
[[Category:Congressional Gold Medal recipients]]
[[Category:Florida Institute of Technology faculty]]
[[Category:Harmon Trophy winners]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Massachusetts Institute of Technology alumni]]
[[Category:Members of The Planetary Society]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:New Jersey Republicans]]
[[Category:Participants in American reality television series]]
[[Category:People from Montclair, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People who have walked on the Moon]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Force Distinguished Service Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Cullum Geographical Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Langley Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the NASA Distinguished Service Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the NASA Exceptional Service Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the NASA Space Flight Medal]]
[[Category:United States Air Force astronauts]]
[[Category:United States Air Force officers]]
[[Category:United States Astronaut Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:Writers from New Jersey]]
</text>
</page>
